<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The compleate copy-holder wherein is contained a learned discourse of the antiquity and nature of manors and copy-holds, vvith all things thereto incident, as surrenders, presentments, admittances, forfeitures, customes, &amp;c. necessary both for the lord and tenant : together, with the forme of keeping a copy-hold court, and court baron / by Sir Edward Coke, Knight.</title>
            <title>Complete copy-holder</title>
            <author>Coke, Edward, Sir, 1552-1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12410148</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12410148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33630)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 658:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The compleate copy-holder wherein is contained a learned discourse of the antiquity and nature of manors and copy-holds, vvith all things thereto incident, as surrenders, presentments, admittances, forfeitures, customes, &amp;c. necessary both for the lord and tenant : together, with the forme of keeping a copy-hold court, and court baron / by Sir Edward Coke, Knight.</title>
                  <title>Complete copy-holder</title>
                  <author>Coke, Edward, Sir, 1552-1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 179 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Cotes for W. Cooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: W.C.</note>
                  <note>1st edition, 1630.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: "The forme of keeping a copy-hold court, and court baron" is lacking in filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Manors.</term>
               <term>Land tenure --  Law and legislation --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61518:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61518:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COMPLEATE COPY-HOLDER.</p>
            <p>Wherein is contained a Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Diſcourſe of the Antiquity and Nature of <hi>Manors</hi> and <hi>Copy-Holds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVith all things thereto incident, </p>
            <list>
               <head>As.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Surrenders.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Preſentments.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Admittances.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Forfeitures.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cuſtomes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Neceſſary, both for the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Tenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together, with the forme of keeping a <hi>Copy-hold Court,</hi> and <hi>Court Baron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Sir EDVVARD COKE, <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Cotes,</hi> for <hi>W. Cooke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at <hi>Furnivalls-Inne</hi> Gate in <hi>Holborne.</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61518:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61518:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Copy comming to my hands, peruſed, and reverenced by men learned in the Lawes. J thought moſt worthy of Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. The very name of the <hi>Compoſer,</hi> who hath beene an Ornament to our Kingdome, is enough to give it ſufficient authority, and indeere it to every wiſe opinion. But the profit which doth attend, is moſt conſiderable, it being a ſubject ſo materiall, declaring the Antiquitie of <hi>Manors</hi> and <hi>Copyholds;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:61518:3"/> and written for the good of <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants;</hi> and by conſequence of all men: it cannot but receive a becomming entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In the confidence of this truth, J referre it to all judicious peruſall, not a little congratulating my owne happineſſe, to have beene an inſtrument of bringing ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Piece from obſcurity, for the benefit of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61518:3"/>
            <head>MANORS AND COPY-HOLDS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough a Manor and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold have ſuch mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reſpect, and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call reference one to the other, as that they are almoſt in nature of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latives, yet the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the one cannot be attained unto, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the ſenſe of the other be truely appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: for a Manor is as the bodie, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyholds certaine members of this bodie. In
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61518:4"/> this Treatiſe I will diſcourſe of them ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally apart, and beginne with the Manor it ſelfe eſpecially, when common reaſon teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, that <hi>totum magis illuſtrat partes, quam partes aliquae illuſtrant totum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SEC. II.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Saxons</hi> (who held <hi>England</hi> in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection immediately before the comming of the <hi>Normans</hi>) were unacquainted with theſe Manors, yet in effect they had Manors in thoſe dayes in circumſtance peradventure ſomething varying in ſubſtance, ſurely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing differing from our Manors at this day; they wanted neither demeſnes nor ſervices, the two materiall cauſes of a Manor, as <hi>Fulbecke</hi> termeth them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fulbecke</hi> in his fourth Dica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</note> their demeſnes they termed Inlands, becauſe the Lords kept them in their own hands, and enjoyed them in their owne poſſeſſion, their Services they termed Vtlands, becauſe thoſe lands were in the manurance and occupation of certaine Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, who in conſideration of the profits ariſing out of theſe lands, were bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme unto their Lords, certaine duties and ſervices: their Demeſnes were of two ſorts; and their ſervices likewiſe were of two ſorts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61518:4"/>
               <head>SEC. III.</head>
               <p>ONe ſort of their Demeſnes was termed Bockland, becauſe they paſſed by booke, and they in effect differed nothing from our Freehold lands at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SEC. IV.</head>
               <p>TH'other ſort of their Demeſnes was termed Folklands, becauſe they paſſed by Polls, and were claymed and challeng'd by the Tenants; not by any aſſurance in Writings, but onely by the mouth of the people; <hi>Per vocem populi,</hi> and they in effect differed in nothing from Copy-hold Lands at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SEC. V.</head>
               <p>TOuching their Services, one ſort of their Services were <hi>Servicia libera,</hi> which conſiſted moſt commonly in Render, as to pay yearly ſuch a Rent, or in Vſer, as where the Lord reſerved Common for his Cattell, or in <hi>Prender,</hi> as where the Lord reſerved three ſhillings, and foure loads of Eſtovers for fuell to be taken yearely in his Tenants grounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:61518:5"/>
               <head>SEC. VI.</head>
               <p>TH'other ſort of Services, were <hi>Servitia villana,</hi> which conſiſted altogether in Feſance, as to ſcoure the Lords ditches, to tyle his houſes, to thatch his barnes, or ſuch like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SEC. VII.</head>
               <p>ANd in the reſervation of theſe Services, the Lords had a ſpeciall reſpect unto the qualitie of the Land, did they transferre their Bockelands, <hi>hoc eſt,</hi> Free-hold Lands, they would never reſerve Villeine Services; did they transferre their Folk-lands, <hi>hoc est,</hi> Coppy-hold Lands, they would never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve free Services, but ſtill they ſuited their Services according to the nature of the Land: the reaſon I gather was this, in thoſe dayes none but men of good account and reckoning enjoyed the ſaid Bock lands, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Holblands were in the hands of men of meaner ſort and condition, and therefore had not the Lords care beene extraordinary in reſerving apt Service they ſhould have much wronged their Tenants;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lamb.</hi> in his explication of the <hi>Saxon</hi> word, <hi>Terra ex-ſcripta.</hi>
                  </note> and thus much <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> verifieth, ſaying, <hi>Terra ex ſcripto fuit haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaria, libera, at que immunis: terra vero ſine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61518:5"/> ſcripto officioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quadam ſervitute f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it obligata: priorem plerum que nobiles at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ingenui, poſterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem vero rustici feri &amp; pagani poſsidebant. Lambert</hi> termeth theſe Bocklands, <hi>Terras liberas atque immunes, non quod ab omnibus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitiis fuerunt liberae aut immunes, ſed quod te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentes ipſi fuerunt liberi &amp; ſervitiis tantum liberis onerati.</hi> But I much wonder, why this Bockland doth to this day retaine the name of Free-hold Land, ſithence time hath bred ſuch an alteration, that in the point of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, a man can ſcarce diſcerne any difference betweene Free-hold Lands, and Copy-hold Lands. The favourable hand of time hath ſo infranchiſed theſe Copy-holders, that whereas in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time, their Services did conſiſt wholly in Feaſance; now they conſiſt in Render, in Vſer, and in Prender: as Free-holders Services did in thoſe dayes: And on the other ſide, time hath dealt ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favourably with Free-holders, and hath ſo abridged them of their former freedome; that if you compare the Service of the Free-holders, with the Service of the Copy-holders, <hi>Senties hunc potius quam illum fore liberum,</hi> How many Free-holders are there at this day, charged with baſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, as many (I doubt not) as there are Copy-holders? No marvell then that many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61518:6"/> able men turne Copy-holders, and many Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zants turne Freeholders; no marvell, I ſay, that men of all ſorts and conditions, promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly, both Free-holders and Copy-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſithence there is ſuch ſmall reſpect had unto the quality of the Land in the reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our Services. Yet obſerve, I pray, though time hath ſo infranchiſed theſe Copy-holders, that they have in a manner ſhaken off all villaine Service; yet they retaine a badge of their former bondage, for they remaine ſtill ſubject to their Lords will; therefore at this day they are termed Tenants at will: but with Free-holders otherwiſe it is, for they are not in that ſubjection to their Lords; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure in this reſpect onely Bocklands may be termed Free-hold Lands, and Folk-land Villaine Lands; and yet time hath dealt very favourably with Copy-holders in this point of will, as well as in the point of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SEC. VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bract lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tr. <hi>3.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi> numb. <hi>5.</hi> Fleta lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap <hi>51.</hi>
                  </note>FOr, as I conjecture, in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time; ſure I am, in the <hi>Normans</hi> time, thoſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py-holders were ſo farre ſubject to the Lords will, that <hi>eorum tenentes tempeſtive &amp; intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive pro voluntate Domini poſſent reſumi &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocari,</hi> as <hi>Bracton,</hi> and <hi>Fleta</hi> both ſpeake;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61518:6"/> the Lords upon the leaſt occaſion, ſometimes without any colour of reaſon, onely upon diſcontentment and malice; ſometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine upon ſome ſudden fantaſticke humour, onely to make evident to the world, the height of their power and authority, would expell out of houſe and home their poore Copy-holders, leaving them helpleſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe by any courſe of Law, and driving them to ſue by way of Petition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SEC. IX.</head>
               <p>BVt now Copy-holders ſtand upon a ſure ground, now they weigh not their Lords diſpleaſure; they ſhake not at every ſuddaine blaſt of wind, they eate, drinke, and ſleepe ſecurely, onely having a ſpeciall care of the mainechance <hi>(viz.)</hi> to performe carefully what duties and ſervices ſoever their Tenure doth exact, and Cuſtome doth require; then let Lord frowne, the Copy-holder cares not, knowing himſelfe ſafe, and not within any danger, for if the Lords anger grow to expulſion, the Law hath provided ſeverall weapons of remedy; for it is at his election, either to ſue a <hi>Subpena</hi> or an Action of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt the Lord. Time hath dealt very favourably with Copy-holders in divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:61518:7"/>
               <head>SEC. X.</head>
               <p>BVt I perceive my ſelfe raſhly running into an inextricable Labyrinth, I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaile no longer in theſe unknowne coaſts, but will haſten homewards, I will content my ſelſe with this. I know amongſt the <hi>Saxons</hi> th'eſſentiall parts of a Manor were knowne; but whether there then were the ſame forme of Manors which is at this day, that I dare not examine, for feare of being accounted more curious than judicious, and therefore leaving the <hi>Saxons,</hi> I draw ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what nearer home, and come to the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> from whom wee had the very forme of Manors, which is obſerved amongſt us at this preſent houre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XI.</head>
               <p>I Confeſſe indeede, that ſithence the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall creation of Manors, Time hath brought in ſome innovations and alterations, as in giving a large freedome unto Copy-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, both in the nature of their Service, and in the manner of their Tenure. Yet I may boldly ſay, that the ſelfe-ſame forme of Manors remaine unaltered in ſubſtance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61518:7"/> though ſomething altered in circumſtance, Demeſne termed in Latine <hi>Demanium, Doma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</hi> or <hi>Dominicum,</hi> is taken in a double ſenſe, <hi>proprie,</hi> and <hi>improprie; proprie,</hi> for that Land which is in the Kings owne hands;<note place="margin">Chopimus de demonio froute lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and the <hi>Chopimus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Domanium eſt illud quod conſecratum unitum, &amp; incorporatum eſt regiae Coronae,</hi> take <hi>Domanium</hi> in this ſenſe, and then you exclude all common perſons from being ſeized in <hi>Dominico:</hi> for admit the King paſſe over the Demeſne Lands, as ſoone as they come into a common perſons hands, <hi>deſinunt eſſe terrae Dominicales;</hi> for though the Kings Pattentee, hath the land granted to him, and to his Heires, yet comming from the King muſt neceſſarily be holden of the King, it is contrary to the nature of Demeſne Lands to be holden of any; therefore though thoſe Lands which commonly are termed ancient Demeſne, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch Lands as were <hi>quondam</hi> in the hands of <hi>Edw. the Confeſſor,</hi> may properly be termed generally ancient Demeſne, becauſe they were in ancient time in the Kings owne poſſeſſion, yet to terme them at this day the Lords Demeſnes, or the Tenants Demeſnes being ſevered from the Crowne is improper <hi>ca. qua ſuper.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61518:8"/>
               <head>SEC. XII.</head>
               <p>THen by this it appeareth that thoſe lands are termed <hi>impropriè</hi> Demeſne, which are in the hands of an inferiour Lord or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, nor can ſuch a one in proprietie of ſpeech be ſaid to ſtand ſeized of any Land whatſoever <hi>in Dominico ſuo,</hi> but if you obſerve narrowly the manner of pleadings, the words are uſed in a proper ſenſe, for you ſhall never finde that an inferiour Lord or Tenant, will plead that he is ſimply ſeized <hi>in Dominico,</hi> but ſtill with this addition, <hi>in Dominico ſuo ut de feodo,</hi> and that very aptly, for this word Fee implieth thus much, that his eſtate is not abſolute, but depending upon ſome ſuperior Lord: therefore I conclude with the <hi>Feudiſts,</hi> that a common perſon may aptly be ſaid to ſtand ſeized in <hi>Feodo,</hi> or in <hi>Dominico ſuo ut de ſeod.</hi> but improperly in <hi>Dominico</hi> ſimply; the King <hi>è converſo</hi> may properly be ſaid to ſtand ſeized <hi>Dominico</hi> ſimply, but in <hi>Feodo</hi> improperly, or in <hi>Dominico ſuo ut de feodo. Bracton</hi> divideth theſe Demeſne Lands into two branches; under the firſt are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended thoſe Lands which the Lord injoyeth in his owne poſſeſſion; under the ſecond, thoſe Lands which are in the hands of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61518:8"/> Copy-holders: His words are theſe, <hi>Dominicum dicitur quod quis habet ad menſam ſuam &amp; idcirco Anglice vocat. Bordland;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bract. lib. <hi>4.</hi> tract. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi> numb. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur etiam Dominicum villinagium quod tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur villanis, quod quis tempeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve &amp; intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive reſumere poſſit, pro voluntate ſua &amp; revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fleta</hi> agreeth with <hi>Bracton</hi> in this diviſion,<note place="margin">Fleta lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> and unto theſe two he addes more ſorts of Demeſne Lands: His words are theſe; <hi>Dominicum est multiplex; est autem Dominicum proprie terra ad menſam aſsignata &amp; villinagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quod traditur villanis ad excolendum, quae tempeſtive, &amp; intempeſtive pro voluntate Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mimi &amp; poterit revocari ſicut eſt de terra commiſſa tenend qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diu co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſori placuerit: po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit &amp; dici dominicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de quo quis habet liberum tenementum alius uſum fruct. &amp; etiam ubi quis habet liberum tenementum aliter curam de cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode dicipoterit &amp; curatore quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> unus dicitur ab homine, alius in jure, Dominicum etiam dicitur ad differentiam ejus quod tenetur in ſervitio. Dominicum denique eſt omne illud tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum de quo anteceſſor obiit ſeſitus, nec refert, cum uſu fructu vel ſine, &amp; de quo ſi ejectus eſſet recuperare poſſit per aſsiſam nove deſeiſme licet alius haberet uſum fructu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſicut dici poterit de il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61518:9"/> qui tenent in villenagio qui utuntur &amp; fruun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur non nemine proprio ſed nomine domini ſui.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XIV.</head>
               <p>THis opinion of <hi>Bract.</hi> and <hi>Fleta,</hi> bo h conſenting in one, that Copy-hold Land is parcell of the Lords demeſnes, wanteth not moderne authority to ſecond it, for 15. <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the <hi>Excheq.</hi> I finde it adjudged in the caſe of a common perſon, howſoever it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the Kings Caſe; That if the Lord of a Manor granteth a way, <hi>Omnes terras ſuas dominicales;</hi> the Copy holds parcell of the Manors paſſe by theſe generall words; neither doth this want Reaſon to confirme it; for in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. and <hi>E.</hi> 2. when <hi>Bract.</hi> and <hi>Fleta</hi> lived, Copy-holders were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted meere Tenants at will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore after a ſort their Lands reputed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill in the Lords hands, and now, though cuſtome hath afforded them a ſurer founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to build upon, yet the Francke Tenement at the common Law, reſting in the Lord, it can be no ſtrange thing to place their lands under the rancke of the Lords demeſnes. But to deliver my minde more freely in this point, I thinke that howſoever, according to the ſtrict rules of Law, theſe Copy-holds are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61518:9"/> parcell of Lands demeſnes, yet in propriety of ſpeech (if propriety can be in improprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) they are the more aptly called the Copy-holders demeſnes; for though the Franke te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement be in the Lord by the Common Law, yet by the cuſtome, the inheritance abideth in the Copy-holders; and it is not denied, if a Copy-holder be impleaded in making tytle to his Copy-hold, he may juſtly plead, <hi>quod eſt ſeiſitus in Dominico ſuo,</hi> with this addition, <hi>ſecundum conſuetud. Manerii.</hi> Therefore I conclude, that howſoever the Common Law valueth the tytle of the Copy-holder, yet he hath ſuch an intereſt confirmed unto him by Cuſtome, that the Lord having no power to reſume his Lands at your owne pleaſure they are (though improperly) called (yet peradventure truly accounted) the Lords demeſnes, and that in the eye of the world, howſoever it be in the eye of the Law, that theſe Lands alone can properly challenge the name of the Lords demeſnes (if any Lands in the poſſeſſion of inferior Lords, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly challenge that name) which the Lord reſerveth in his owne hands, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his owne Boord or Table, be it his waſte ground, his arable ground, his paſture ground, or his medow; be it his Copy-hold which he hath by eſcheate, by forfiture, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61518:10"/> by purchaſe, or be it any part of his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Land, of which I muſt ſpeake a word by the way, not to prove that it is demeſne, for <hi>manifeſta probatione non indigentes,</hi> but to ſhew you in what ſenſe it is taken, and how farre it extendeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XV.</head>
               <p>A Freehold is taken in a double ſenſe; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 'tis named a Freehold in reſpect of the ſtate of the Land, or in reſpect of the ſtate of the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XVI.</head>
               <p>IN reſpect of the ſtate of the Land, ſo Copyholders may be Freeholders; for any that hath any eſtate for his life, or any greater eſtate in any Land whatſoever, may in this ſenſe be termed a Freeholder.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XVII.</head>
               <p>IN reſpect of the ſtate of the Law, and ſo it is oppoſed to Copy holders, that what Land ſoever is not Copyhold is Freehold, and in this ſenſe I take throughout this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:61518:10"/>
               <head>SEC. XVIII.</head>
               <p>THe name of Freeholders extendeth not onely unto Lands held <hi>per ſervitium mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litare,</hi> as it did by th'ancient Lawes of <hi>Scots;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Skens. de verb. ſign. tit. milit.</note> and amongſt whom Freeholders were knowne by the name of <hi>milites,</hi> but it reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth likewiſe to lands holden <hi>per ſervitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Socae,</hi> whether in <hi>libero Socagio,</hi> or in <hi>villano Socagio: Liberum Socagium</hi> is, where any Tenant holds of any Lord by paying yearely a certaine ſumme of money in lieu of tillage, and ſuch like ſervices, and not by eſcuage; and this is termed ſometimes common Socage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socagium villanum</hi> is where the ancient ſervices of carrying the Lords dung into the fields,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat.</hi> 37 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 20. It is ſo called.</note> of plowing his ground at certaine dayes, of plaſhing his hedges, and ſuch are not turned into money; but remaine ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altered; and if you doubt that ſuch Land as is held <hi>per villanum Socagium</hi> cannot come within the compaſſe of Freehold Land: for your ſatisfaction, reade <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>num.</hi> 8. <hi>Hactenus de primo defunctionis membro ad ſecundum properemus &amp; pauca de ſervitiis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino debitis periractemus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Services in <hi>individuo</hi> are manifold, in <hi>ſpecie</hi> threefold. 1. Corporall ſervices. 2. Annuall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61518:11"/> ſervices. 3. Accidentall ſervices.</p>
               <p>Corporall ſervices are of two ſorts; Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Submiſſion, ſervices of Profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XIX.</head>
               <p>SErvices of Submiſſion, are homage and fealty, which are certaine Ceremonies uſed among tenants, whereby they ſubmit themſelves unto their Lords, and binde themſelves by ſolemne oath, or by faithfull promiſe, from that day forward to become the Lords men for life, for member, for ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene honour, or <hi>adminimum,</hi> to owe unto him faith, for the Lands which they hold of him. Both theſe Ceremonies are uſed at the firſt entrance or admittance of any Tenant, and both tend to one end, <hi>viz.</hi> to inforce eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tenant to acknowledge and confeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Tenant unto his immediate Lord, yet they differ in many materiall points.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XX.</head>
               <p>IN regard of their ſeverall manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance: for in doing fealty, the Tenant taketh a ſolemne oath, in doing homage only giveth his faithfull promiſe; and thence it is that fealty is accounted the more ſacred ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61518:11"/> though homage be the more humble ſervice, and performed with farre greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence than fealty in many reſpects, for in doing homage, the Tenant kneeleth, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fealty he ſtandeth; in doing homage, the Tenant muſt remaine uncovered; in doing fealty, he may remaine covered; in doing homage, the Lord kiſſeth his Tenant, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fealty he kiſſeth him not. Laſtly, in doing homage, the Tenant promiſeth to become the Lords man for life, for member, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene honor. In doing fealty he onely ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to become the Lords faithfull Tenant: the reaſon of this difference I learne to be this,<note place="margin">Skens. de verb. ſignum <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe homage eſpecially concerneth ſervice in warre, &amp; properly appertaineth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Knights ſervice; but fealty chiefely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth ſervice at home, and properly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to Socage tenure; and though now 'tis held, that a Tenant by Socage may doe homage, and that homage <hi>ex ſe</hi> maketh Socage tenure, and not Knights ſervice; yet originally homage was invented for Tenants by Knights ſervice, and ſuch as were bound by their tenure to attend their Lords in the warres; but fealty was primarily deviſed for Tenants in Socage, and ſuch as were bound by their tenure to manure the Lords ground, and carefully to diſcharge all rurall affaires;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61518:12"/> and this agreeth with the ancient Lawes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for amongſt them none were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Freeholders, but onely Tenants by Knights ſervice, and conſequently none but they could doe homage; and therefore marvell not why in doing homage, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant promiſeth to become the Lords man for life, for member, for terrene honor, in doing fealty hee onely ſweareth to become the Lords faithfull Tenant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They differ in regard of the perſons to whom they are performed, and that two wayes. In reſpect none is capable of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving homage, but the Lord in perſon, but the Lords Steward, or his Bailiffe is capable to receive fealty in the Lords behalfe. 2. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that a Lord who hath but an eſtate for his life in his Seigniory cannot receive ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, but ſuch a Lord may receive fealty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They differ in regard of the perſons to whom they are performed, and that two wayes. 1. In reſpect th t no Copyholder is capable of doing homage, but he is of doing fealty, witneſſe common experience. 2. In reſpect that a Tenant for life or yeares, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to doe homage, for tis a ground in Law, that none can doe homage but tenant in fee-ſimple, or <hi>ad minimum,</hi> tenant in tayle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61518:12"/>
               <head>SEC. XXI.</head>
               <p>BVt a Tenant for life or yeares,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Brudnal</hi> and <hi>Yoxley</hi> 5. <hi>H.</hi> 7. The Juſtices of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Place, 10. <hi>H</hi> 6. held, that Leſſee for years cannot doe fealty.</note> are both able to doe fealty, according to <hi>Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> rule, that fealties are incident to every tenure, except tenures in Franck-almoigne, and tenants at will, contrary to ſome erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us opinions, they differ in regard that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage can be but once done unto one Lord by the ſame Tenant; and therefore 'tis agreed, that if Lands deſcend unto me, which is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>I. S.</hi> by homage, and I doe unto him homage, and after other Lands deſcendeth unto me by another Anceſtor, which is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the ſame Lord by homage, I ſhall not doe homage againe, but fealty onely, becauſe I cannot twice become the Lords man; but the ſelfe-ſame Tenant may ſeverall times doe fealty unto the ſelfe-ſame Lord; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if a Copyholder ſurrendreth Whiteacre unto me, for his Whiteacre I ſhould doe fealty unto the Lord. If after another ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendreth unto me Blackeacre, I ſhall doe feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie likewiſe unto the ſame Lord. And thus much for ſervices of Submiſſion,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:61518:13"/>
               <head>SEC. XXII.</head>
               <p>SErvices of Profits are of two ſorts tending to the publique profit of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, as when the Lord injoyneth his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to amend high wayes, to repaire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed bridges, or <hi>ſimilia.</hi> 2. Tending to the private profit of the Lord, as where the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is injoyned to be the Lords Carver, Butler, or Brewer, or is tyed to payle the Lords Parkes, to tyle the Lords Houſes, to thatch the Lords Barnes, and <hi>ſimilia.</hi> And thus much for corporall ſervices.</p>
               <p>Annuall ſervices are in number infinite, in nature all one, for they all tend to th'increaſe of the Lords Coffers, and are reſerved in their duties, as well for Copyhold. Land, as Freehold-Land; though in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time, and long after the Conqueſt, they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or ſeldome reſerved for Copyhold-Land, but onely for Freehold-Land. I will not enumerate many particulars of annuall ſervices, for that were as endleſſe, as num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the ſands of the Sea; onely this I ſay, that thoſe annuall ſervices which here come within the compaſſe of my meaning, conſiſt all in Render, none in Feaſance, for thoſe annuall ſervices, as well as accidentall ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61518:13"/> which conſiſt in Feaſance, I comprehend under corporall ſervices; thus leaving both corporall ſervices and annuall, I bend my courſe towards accidentall ſervices, which before I begin to particularize, obſerve theſe two things by the way:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That accidentall ſervices differ from corporall and annuall ſervices in this, that moſt accidentall ſervices are incident to the Fee, and are due wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hout ſpeciall reſervation of the Lord; but moſt corporall ſervices, and all annuall ſervices are due upon ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and are not incident unto the Fee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſervice is taken in a double ſenſe, in <hi>ſtrictiori ſenſu,</hi> and in <hi>latiori ſenſu;</hi> In <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiori ſenſu,</hi> and in that ſenſe the <hi>Feudiſts</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine, <hi>ſervitium fore munus obſequii clientelario, &amp;c.</hi> that duty which the Tenant oweth unto his Lord, either in performing ſome corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall function, or in diſcharging ſome annuall payment. In <hi>latiori ſenſu,</hi> and ſo it ſignifieth any duty whatſoever accruing unto the Lord, by reaſon of his Seigniorie; and in this ſenſe, theſe accidentall ſervices follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (which <hi>prima facie,</hi> may ſeeme better to ranke under the title of juriſdictions, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the name of the fruits of a Manor) may very fitly be reduced to this kinde of ſervices.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:61518:14"/>
               <p>The ſervices I ayme at, and which I meane to treate of particularly in this place are theſe following,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Wardſhips.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Herriots.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Reliefes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Amerciaments.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Forfeitures.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Eſcheates.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now touching every one of theſe apart, and firſt with <hi>Wardſhips.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVArſhipp. est cuſtodia heredis infra aetatem exiſtentis, Polidore Virgil</hi> ſaith, that this <hi>was novi vectigalis genus excogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> to helpe, <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. being oppreſſed with much poverty, by reaſon hee received the Kingdome greatly waſted by warres of his Anceſtors, and therefore needing extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary helpe to uphold his eſtate, the uſe of Wardſhips was ſet abroach. But the 33. Chapter of the grand Cuſtomary maketh mention of this to have beene uſed among the <hi>Normans,</hi> immediatly after the erection of Manors, and that the uſe of Wardſhips was a foote before <hi>H.</hi> the thirds time, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth manifeſtly by <hi>Glanvil,</hi> who writeth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61518:14"/> very largely in many places in his Booke,<note place="margin">Fleta. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> and lived in <hi>H. the ſeconds</hi> time; Guardians are either termed <hi>Custodes,</hi> or <hi>Curatores, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodes a lege, curatores ab homine,</hi> as <hi>Fleta</hi> ſpeaketh. The Civilians make three ſorts of <hi>Guardians, Tutor testamentarius.</hi> 2. <hi>Tutor a-Praetore datus.</hi> 3. <hi>Tutor legittimus:</hi> This in every point agreeth with our Common Law, ſo wee have <hi>Tutorem teſtamentarium, viz.</hi> where a man poſſeſſed of certaine goods and chattells demiſeth theſe unto his child, and withall, committeth the care of his childs body, and diſpoſition of his ſubſtance unto ſome friend, this committee is <hi>Tutor testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarius,</hi> unto whom belongeth the care and cuſtody of the childs body, and the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſubſtance, untill hee accompliſh the full age of foureteene yeares, and then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly hee ſhall be out of Ward for his body, but his goods may be kept longer, for as for them they ſhall remaine in the truſtees hands, ſo many yeares as the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor appointed by his laſt Will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for though it be not in the Fathers power to reſtraine the libertie of his childs bodylonger then to the age of 14. yet the diſpoſing of his goods he may commit to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for as long time as himſelfe ſhall thinke expedient: So by the Stat. 32. and 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61518:15"/> If a man be ſeiſed of Socage Lands, not hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the King in Capite, hee may by his laſt Will and Teſtament commit the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Theoglands, to what friend ſoever, for as many yeares as ſhall ſeeme moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and that friend is <hi>Tutor teſtamentari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> otherwiſe it is of Lands holden by Knights ſervice; for it is not in any mans power by his laſt Will and Teſtament, to deprive the Lord of that duty which, <hi>de jure,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to him, and therefore if a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder dieth, his heire under the age of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene. In regard that this priviledge of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the heires a Guardian for their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold Land, untill he accompliſh the age of fourteene, <hi>de jure,</hi> appertaineth unto the Lord. It ſeemeth that the father cannot prejudice the Lord in this kinde, by appointing him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Guardian by his laſt Will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>haec de Tutore teſtamentario.</hi> 2. Wee have <hi>Tutorem a Praetore datum, viz.</hi> where a man deviſeth goods unto his childe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth him not Guardian, then it is in the Ordinaries hand to commit the ordering of the Infants goods unto ſome truſtie friend, unto the age of foureteene; at what time the Infant himſelfe may chuſe a Guardian: for it is a rule in the Civill Law, <hi>Invito curator non datur,</hi> and this Committee <hi>eſt Tutor a Praetore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61518:15"/> datus.</hi> Theſe Guardians termed amongſt the Civilians, <hi>Tutores a Praetore dati,</hi> are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Guardians, <hi>pur nurture;</hi> and thus in words we ſomewhat differ, in matter nothing. 3. We have <hi>Tutorem ligi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mum, viz.</hi> where the intereſt doth <hi>de jure</hi> belong unto any, without the nomination of a private perſon, or the appointment of any publique Officer: and this Guardian is twofold, either <hi>ligiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus jure naturae,</hi> or <hi>ligi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imus jure Comuni; ligitimus jure naturae,</hi> as where the Father or the Mother hath the Wardſhip of their heires apparent, be it heire male or female: <hi>Ligitimus jure comuni;</hi> and that Guardian is twofold, either Guardian in Chivalrie, or Guardian in Soccage; Guardian in Chivalry is, where any Tenant ſeized of Land, holden by Knights ſervice dieth, his heire male under the age of fourteene, and unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; then ſhall the Lord have the Ward, both of the Lands, and body of this heire male, unto the age of 21. becauſe the Law intendeth, that before that age, the heire is unable to performe Knights ſervice, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tenure; but the heire female ſhall be in Ward, no longer than to the age of ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene, becauſe the heire female, though ſhee her ſelfe be unable to performe Knights ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61518:16"/> yet at ſixteene, ſhe is able to take a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who in her behalfe may doe Knights ſervice; and therefore at thoſe yeares ſhee ſhall be out of Ward; nay, ſometimes ſhee ſhall be out of Ward before ſixteene; and that is either, where ſhee is married at the death of her Anceſtor, or where ſhee is any whit above fourteene: when her Anceſtor dieth in neither of theſe Caſes ſhall ſhe be in Ward at all; for though the <hi>Stat.</hi> of <hi>W.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. giveth unto the Lord two yeares next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the fourteenth, yet that is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, where ſhee is under the age of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene, and unmarried at her Anceſtors death, and not otherwiſe. This for Guardian in Chivalry. Guardian in Socage, is, where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one ſeized of Socage Lands dieth, his heire under the age of fourteene, then the next friend unto the heire, to whom the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance cannot deſcend, ſhall have the Ward of the heires body, and of his Land, untill the age of fourteene, as if the Land deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth unto the heire by the fathers ſide; then the mother, or next coſin of the mothers ſide ſhall have the Ward; and if the Land deſcendeth to the heire by the mothers ſide, then the father, or next coſin on the fathers ſide ſhall have the Ward. To conclude, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this difference betweene Guardian in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61518:16"/> Chivalry, and Guardian in Socage, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one receiveth the commodities of the Land to his owne uſe, without giving any account; th'other onely to the uſe of the heire, to whom he ſhall be accountable whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe the heire to call him to account after th'age of foureteene. Thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Wardſhips; a word concerning Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXIV.</head>
               <p>HErriot, or Harriot commeth of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine word <hi>herus, Dominus,</hi> becauſe it is a duty appropriated to the Lord; or it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>here exercitus,</hi> becauſe in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time, when the name of Herriot was firſt knowne, Herrior ſignified nothing elſe but a tribute given to the Lord for his better preparation towards warre, as a horſe trapped, or a ſpeare, or armour, or a ſword, or ſome ſuchlike Military weapon; and therefore in this ſenſe importing a thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the warre, and being due unto the Lord, by reaſon of this ſervice which Tenants owe unto their Lords, many warlike imployments,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Lamb.</hi> in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Saxons</hi> words, <hi>tit. Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot.</hi>
                  </note> it may very fitly be derived from hence: This their Herriot among the <hi>Saxons</hi> little differed from our Reliefe at this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61518:17"/> day, howſoever now they differ <hi>ex diame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro:</hi> But let us examine the nature of our Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iots at this day, and not ſearch into the nature of their Herriots in thoſe dayes; for that were to examine the nature of Reliefes not Herri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots. <hi>Britton</hi> thus ſpeaketh; A Herriot is a Render,<note place="margin">Britton. cap. <hi>69.</hi>
                  </note> made at the death of a Tenant to his Lord, of the beſt beaſt found in the poſſeſſion of the Tenant deceaſed, or of ſome other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ordinance and aſſignment of the party deceaſed to the uſe of the Lord, which toucheth not the Land at all, nor the heire, nor his inheritance, neither hath any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon to a Relief, for it proceedeth rather of grace and good will, than of right, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from villaines, than freemen: to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſpeaketh <hi>Fleta,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fleta lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Herriottum eſt quaedam praeſtatio ubi tenens, liber vel ſervus in morte ſua dominum ſuum reſpicit de meliori averio ſuo vel de ſeeundo meliori, quae quidem praeſtatio magis, fuit de gratia quam de jure &amp; nullam habet comparationem ad relevium eo quod heredi non continget quia factum anteceſſoris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This our Herriot is twofold; Herriot Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Herriot Cuſtome; Herriot Service, is that Herriot which is never due, without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reſervation, and is ſeldome reſerved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any leſſe eſtate, than an eſtate of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Herriot Cuſtome, is that Herriot
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61518:17"/> which is never due upon ſpeciall reſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but is challenged upon ſome particular Cuſtome, and is uſually payd upon an eſtate for life, and for yeares, as well as upon an eſtate of inheritance. Touching the originall of theſe Herriots, doubtleſſe they are not of that antiquity which the name doth promiſe, for though among the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the name of Herriot was knowne, yet the nature of both theſe, Herriot Services, and Herriot Cuſtome, was utterly unknowne, untill the comming of the <hi>Normans;</hi> who immediately upon the Conqueſt changed the name of the <hi>Saxons</hi> Herriot, and termed it by the name a of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, leaving notwithſtanding ſome d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them, for where the <hi>Saxons</hi> Herriot, conſiſted uſually in the payment of ſome military weapon; our Reliefe in thoſe dayes conſiſted wholly in the payment of a certaine ſumme of money, and preſently after the <hi>Normans</hi> had thus wholly altered the name, and ſomewhat altered the nature of the <hi>Saxons</hi> Herriot, then upon the parcelling of their lands unto inferior Tenants, they inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this new kinde of ſervice unknowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and termed it by the name of the Herriot Service, afterward, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the infranchiſement and manumiſſion of certaine villaines; theſe Herriot Cuſtomes, were given to the Lords as a continuall, <hi>future
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61518:18"/> gratulation:</hi> ſo that originally, as <hi>Britton,</hi> and <hi>Fleta</hi> well note, they were granted meerely, <hi>ex gratia,</hi> but now time hath effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted it, that they are challenged, <hi>ex debito.</hi> Thus much of Herriots; a word of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXV.</head>
               <p>REliefe is a certaine ſumme of money which every Freeholder payeth unto his Lord,<note place="margin">Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>v. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> being at full age at the death of his Anceſtor, which in effect foundeth all one, with theſe words of <hi>Glanvil, Haeredes majores ſtatim poſt deceſſum anteceſſorum ſuorum poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt ſe tenere in haereditate ſua licet Domini poſsint feodum ſuum cum herede in manus ſuas capere: ita tamen moderate id fleri debet, ne ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam diſſeiſinam haeredibus faciant, poſſunt enim, haeredes ſi opus fuerit, violentiae Dominorum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtere, dum tamen parati ſunt Relivium altare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro ſervitia eis inde facere;</hi> with this agreeth the definition of <hi>Hotoman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hotoman Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. de verbo ſeod &amp; verbo Relivium.</note> 
                  <hi>Relivium eſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norarium quod novus vaſſallus introitus cauſâ patrono largitur quaſi morte uſuali altius vel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o quo caſu feodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceciderit quod jam a novo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levatur.</hi> This reliefe by the ancient Civill Law was termed <hi>Introitus;</hi> and <hi>Vincentius</hi> termeth it <hi>Praeſtantionem ſeu ſaluationem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61518:18"/> pro confirmatione ſeu renovatione poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> and that very aptly: for indeede Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe is the key, which opens the gate to give the heire free paſſage to the poſſeſſion of his inheritance. <hi>Bracton</hi> giveth this reaſon why it is called a Reliefe,<note place="margin">Bracton lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>86.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quia haereditas quae jacens fuit per anteceſſoris deceſſum Releviatur in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus haeredis &amp; propter factam relevationem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciend. erit ab haerede quaedam praeſtatio quae dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Relevium.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Skene de verbo ſignum tit. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Skene</hi> fondly imagineth that it taketh his name, <hi>a relevando,</hi> in another ſenſe; for ſaith he, Reliefe is given by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or Vaſſall, being of perfect age, after the expiring of the Wardſhip, to the Lord, of whom he held his Land by Knights ſervice, it is by Ward and Reliefe, and by payment thereof he relieves, and as it were, raiſeth up againe his lands after they were fallen downe into his ſuperiors hands; by reaſon of Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.<note place="margin">Glanvil lib <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> But theſe words of <hi>Glanvil</hi> will ſerve to convince him of error; <hi>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dam vero eode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad aetate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pervenie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, &amp; facta e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haereditutis restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione quietas erit a Relivio ratione cuſtodiae:</hi> this Reliefe is twofold. 1. Reliefe Service. 2. Reliefe Cuſtome: Reliefe Service, is that which is paid upon the death of any Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder. Reliefe Cuſtome, is that which is paid upon the death, change, or alienation of any Freehold, according to the Cuſtome of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61518:19"/> the place, in many places halfe a yeares pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, in many places a whole yeares profit, and therefore where <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith; <hi>Quod dat Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Relevium qui ſuccedit jure haereditatis, non autem is qui acquirit;</hi> that is to be taken with this caution; <hi>niſi illud etiam conſuetudine, praeſtare debet qui acquirit.</hi> Theſe Reliefes are paid, as well for lands-holden in Soccage, as Lands holden by Knights ſervice: for lands holden in Soccage in this manner. If a Tenant in Soccage die, his heire above the age of fourteene, then ſhall the heire double the Rent that his Anceſtors was wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to pay to the Lord, as if the Tenant holdeth of his Lord by fealty and five ſhillings; then ſhall the heire double the Rent, and ſhall pay ten ſhillings, <hi>viz.</hi> five ſhilling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the name of a Reliefe, over and above the five ſhillings, which hee payeth for his Rent. For Lands holden by Knights ſervice in this manner; if a Tenant by Knights ſervice dieth, his heire of full 21. if he holdeth by an intire Knights Fee, hee payeth five pound, if by halfe a Knights Fee, then he payeth fiftie ſhillings, if by a quarter of a Knights Fee, hee payeth 25. ſhillings, and ſo proportionably, who ſo holdeth more, payeth more, and who hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth leſſe, payeth leſſe; yet for the fuller ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the quantity of a Reliefe: let us
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61518:19"/> examine what a Knights Fee ſignifieth. A knights Fee, is ſo much land as in ancient time was accounted a ſufficient living for a Knight, but whether this was rated accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the quantity, or according to the value, <hi>Cauſidici certant, &amp; adhuc ſub j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di ce lis eſt.</hi> Some hold according to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, and that according to the ſeverall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations uſed in ſeverall places. A Knights Fee was either more or leſſe; as in the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> a Knights Fee contained foure hydes of land, every hyde foure carnes of land, every carne foure yard lands, every yard thirty acres; and every Knights Fee 1920. acres. According to other computations, a Knights Fee contained, 680; but according to moſt computations, a Knights Fee contained five hides of land, evey hide foure yard lands, every yard land 24. acres, according to which computation; a Knights Fee contained 480. acres: ſo that according to ſeverall computations, a Knights Fee was more or leſſe. Others hold, that a Knights Fee was meaſured according to the quality, not according to the quantity; according to the value, not according to the content: and amongſt theſe, ſome hold that land to the value of fifteene pound <hi>par annum</hi> made a Knights Fee; and therefore,<note place="margin">Camden in ſua Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tan. pag.</note> 
                  <hi>Camden</hi> ſaith, that, <hi>Sub Henrich tertio quodammodo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acti fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t equites fieri quot quot libras quindece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:61518:20"/> exannuis terrarum redditibus colligarunt;</hi> and out of <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> hee writeth, that <hi>anno,</hi> 1256. <hi>Exit edictum regium preceptumque eſt &amp; acclamatum per totum regnum ut qui haberet</hi> 16. <hi>libratas terrae &amp; ſupradict. armis redimitus tirocinio donaretur, ut Anglia, ſicut Italia mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia roboraretur, &amp; qui nollent, vel qui non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt honorem ſtatus militaris ſustinere pecunia ſe redimerent.</hi> Others hold, that <hi>cenſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris,</hi> was fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e pound revenue in Freehold land: and of this opinion is Sir <hi>Thomas Smith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Smith. de rep pag. <hi>31, 32, 33.</hi>
                  </note> others held, that <hi>cenſus equestris,</hi> was twentie pound revenue; and this opinion is confirmed by many authorities, and reaſons cited in <hi>Anth. Lowes</hi> Caſe, by an ancient Treatiſe, <hi>de modo tenendi Parliamentum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Regis Edwardi filii Etheldred,</hi> where it appeareth, <hi>quod comitatus constabat ex viginti feodis unius militis quolibet feodo computato ad viginti libratas. Baronia conſtabat, ex</hi> 13. <hi>in feodis ac tertia parte unius feodi militis ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum computationem predicta unum feodum militis conſtabat ex terris ad valentiam</hi> 20. <hi>li.</hi> and therefore where the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>militibus,</hi> provideth that a Knights Living ſhall be meaſured by the value of twenty pound <hi>per annum;</hi> this is but an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmance of the Common Law- 2. This is ſtrengthened by the words of the Statute of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61518:20"/> 
                  <hi>W.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 36. and by <hi>Fitch.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fitch. nat. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um. fo <hi>62.</hi>
                  </note> this ſeemeth ſomething pregnant, for in both theſe places, Soccage land to the value of twentie pound <hi>par annum,</hi> are put in equipage with a Knights Fee. 3. In a Writ of meſne, brought <hi>per Ranul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum de Normanvile petentem verſus Luciam de Kyme tenentem P.</hi> 3. <hi>E.</hi> 1. appeareth, that twelve carnes of Land made a Knights Fee, every carne being in ancient time of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of five nobles <hi>per annum;</hi> according to which account, a Knights Fee amounted to twenty pound <hi>per annum.</hi> Theſe are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall opinions, touching the quantity of a Knights Fee, imbrace of theſe, which ſhall ſeeme moſt conſonant to reaſon. For my owne part, I thinke that in the ancient time, a Knights Fee, was meaſured according to the number of the acres; but in thoſe dayes, according to the value of the land: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this alteration is; that though in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time, as well as in theſe dayes, ſome lands were farre more fruitfull than others; yet the value of every quantity of land was certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rated, according to the Cuſtome of the places, and never upon any occaſion was the land increaſed or decreaſed; and therefore were they to examine whether any man had a ſufficient living for a Knight, they would looke no further than to the quantitie of his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61518:21"/> land, for by the quantitie, they could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently judge the value; but now the value is not certainely rated in any place, but increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and decreaſeth upon every occaſion; and therefore reaſon requireth, that in theſe dayes a Knights Fee, ſhould be meaſured, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the value, not according to the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Land, for by reaſon of the different value of the land, one man may be better able to maintaine the dignity of a Knight, with two hundred acres in ſome place, and of ſome land, than another with foure hundred acres of other land. But howſoever it is, whether a Knights Fee be rated according to the value, or according to the quantity let it here reſt.</p>
               <p>Now give mee leave to examine at what time, and by what Law it was firſt provided, that for every Knights Fee, the fourth part of a Knights Revenue ſhould be payd in the name of a Reliefe, <hi>viz.</hi> 5. <hi>li.</hi> for every Barons Fee, the fourth part of a Barons Revenue, <hi>viz.</hi> one hundred markes; for every Earles Fee, the fourth part of an Earles Revenue, <hi>viz.</hi> one hundred pound; ſurely Reliefes were paid in this manner, before the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Glan vil. lib <hi>9.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> and that is ſomewhat pregnant by this, that by the very words of that <hi>Statute.</hi> This Reliefe is termed <hi>Antiquum Relevium;</hi> and by <hi>Glanvil,</hi> who writ before the making of this <hi>Statute,</hi> this is ſome what manifeſt; for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61518:21"/> he ſpeaketh to this effect, <hi>Dicitur rationabile relevium alicujus juxta conſuetudinem regni de feodo unius militis centum ſolidos? de Socca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio vero quantum valet, cenſus illius Socca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii per annum de Boronia vero nihil cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſtatutum eſt quia juxta voluntatem &amp; miſricordiam Domini Regis ſolent Baroniae capital. de relevis ſuis Domino Regi ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfacere:</hi> from whence I gather, that <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was in part an affirmance of the Common Law, in part an inſtitution of a new Law.</p>
               <p>Touching Reliefe paid by Knights, it was but an affirmance of the Common Law, becauſe they were certaine before the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</hi> Touching Reliefes paid by Barons, it was an inſtitution of a new Law, becauſe they were before uncertaine; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why Dukes and Vicounts, are not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this <hi>Statute,</hi> as well as Earles, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, and Knights is this, becauſe when that <hi>Statute</hi> was made, there was neither Duke, Marqueſſe or Vicount in <hi>England.</hi> The firſt Duke that ever was in <hi>England</hi> ſithence the Conqueſt, was the Blacke Prince, eldeſt ſonne to <hi>Ed. the</hi> 3. The firſt Marqueſſe that ever was in <hi>England,</hi> was <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Oxford,</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>R.</hi> 2. and the firſt Vicount that ever was in <hi>England Dominus de Bello monte,</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>H.</hi> 6.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:61518:22"/>
               <p>But though at the making of this <hi>Statute,</hi> theſe dignities were unknowne, yet they are comprehended under the equitie of the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> and according to their ſeverall dignities ſhall pay Reliefe unto the King, a Duke two hundred <hi>li.</hi> a Marqueſſe two hundred markes, and ſo ratably and proportionably. But to conclude, let us compare Herriots and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefes together, and obſerve in what they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They differ in this, that a Herriot lieth in Prender, and a Reliefe in Render. 2. In this, that a Herriot is paid in the name of a Tenant deceaſed; but a Reliefe in the name of an heire, who is become Tenant. 3. In this, that Heriots are paid by Copyholders, as well as Freeholders; but Reliefe by Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders only. 4. In this, that Herriots are ever due upon a ſpeciall reſervation, or upon ſome particular Cuſtome; but Reliefes are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Fee, and are due without reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Cuſtome, contrary to the opinion of <hi>Vincentinus,</hi> who holdeth a Reliefe <hi>extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam fore praeſtationem &amp; non in eſſe feodo.</hi> Thus much touching Reliefes, a word touching Amerciaments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:61518:22"/>
               <head>SEC. XXVI.</head>
               <p>AMerciament is a Pecuniarie puniſhment for any offence committed againſt the Lord of any Manor, or (as ſome more at large define it) it is a certaine ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney impoſed upon the Tenant by the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by oath, and preſentment of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; for the breach of any by Law made, either for the profit of the whole Kingdome, or for the benefit of the little Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth among themſelves, or for default of doing ſute, or for other miſdemeanors, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by the ſame Court, infinite in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and quality; and this word Amerciament taketh his name fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being in the Lords mercy, to be puniſhed more or leſſe at his will and pleaſure, and it differeth from a Fine in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers reſpects.</p>
               <p>In that whoſoever is fined may lawfully be impriſoned, but whoſoever is a mercied can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. 2. In this, that Amerciaments are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent unto Court Barons, as well as unto Court Leets, and Fines are never incident to any Court Barons, but to Court Leets onely, or other Cou ts of Record. 3. That Amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaments are incident unto every Manor whatſoever; but Fynes are incident unto ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61518:23"/> few Manors onely: the reaſon of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is partly grounded upon the former difference; for ſithence Amerciaments are incident unto every Court Baron, and Court Barons are incident unto every Manor: <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur ex conſequente,</hi> that unto every Manor amerciaments are incident, but <hi>ex adverſo,</hi> Fines being incident unto Court Leets onely, and thoſe Court Leets being in ſome few Manors onely, not in every Manor expreſly <hi>ſequitur,</hi> that Fines are not incident unto eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Manor, but unto ſome few Manors onely. 4. In this, that Amerciaments are afferable <hi>Per pares, per ſacramentum prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum &amp; legalium hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de viceneto qui ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delicti ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jori vel minori amerciame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to delinquent. mulctare poſſunt:</hi> but Fines are never afferable in this kinde; for looke what Fine ſoever the Court impoſeth upon the delinquent, that bindeth ſufficiently, without further afferance. Give me but leave to aske two queſtions, when had this afferance his firſt conception or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation? 2. How may Amerciaments in Court Leets be diſcerned and diſtinguiſhed from Fines impoſed in the ſame Court, ſince they are both pecuniary puniſhments for offences committed? Touching the firſt queſtion, I thinke this Law of afferance was before the <hi>Statute of Magna Charta;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Glanv. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> for <hi>Glanvile</hi> thus
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61518:23"/> ſpeaketh of it, <hi>Eſt autem miſericordia Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Regis, quo quis per juramentum legalium hominum de viceneto eatenus amerciandus eſt ne aliquid de ſuo honorabili contenen. amittat;</hi> and therefore by this appeareth, that this <hi>Stat.</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> was but an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Common Law in this point of afferance. Touching the ſecond queſtion, know that 'tis not in the power of the Court to impoſe a Fine, or an Amerciament at their election for any offence committed, but ſtill the quality of the puniſhment muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſute with the qualitie of the offence, from the ſeverall natures of offences committed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe the ſeverall names of puniſhments infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The offences in reſpect of the place are twofold, and in reſpect of the perſons two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. In reſpect of the place, offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, <hi>extra curiam,</hi> of which the Steward by no common poſſibilitie can have cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance without the preſentment of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and therefore the power of preſenting them, and impoſing puniſhments for them, belongeth unto the Jurors of the Leet, and not unto the Steward; and theſe puniſhments thus impoſed are termed Amerciaments. 2. Offences committed in <hi>Curia,</hi> of which the Steward can take ſufficient notice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helping hand of the homage, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61518:24"/> therefore the puniſhments of theſe offences belong unto the Steward, not unto the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and theſe puniſhments thus impoſed are termed Fines. Thus in reſpect of the place, offences are twofold. In reſpect of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they are likewiſe twofold: Offences committed by private perſons. 2. Offences committed by publike Officers, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Court, in the adminiſtration of their office, puniſhments impoſed for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the former ranke are termed Amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaments, of the latter ranke Fines, the one afferable <hi>per pares,</hi> th'other not; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> in this point of afferance, extendeth not unto any offences committed in Court by private Perſons,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>8.</hi> Greiſlegt. Cafe.</note> or publique Officers: neither unto any offences committed <hi>extra curiam,</hi> by publique Officers in adminiſtration of their Office, is this, becauſe though the words of the <hi>Statute</hi> are generally extending unto all offences whatſoever; yet th'intent of the <hi>Statute</hi> makers was not to make the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Afferors <hi>in omnibus delictis mulctandis, ſed in iis tantummodo puniendis quorum cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam poſsint habere notitiam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fleta lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>98.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> as <hi>Fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> ſpeaketh, and therefore ſithence the Steward hath more certaine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of offences committed in <hi>curia</hi> by what
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61518:24"/> perſons ſoever then the Jurors have, and can better judge and diſcerne of the natures and qualities of offences committed, <hi>Extra curiam</hi> by publike Officers than Jurors can; therefore ſurely the intent of this <hi>Statute,</hi> was to leave the puniſhment of theſe offences, to the diſcretion of the Steward, and not the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance of the homage. Thus much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Amerciaments: a word concerning For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXVII.</head>
               <p>FOrfeiture commeth of the <hi>French</hi> word <hi>Forfaict, ſcelus, quia ſcelerum &amp; delictorum perpetratio est forisfacturarum cauſa &amp; origo.</hi> In our Language it ſignifieth the effect of tranſgreſſing, rather than the tranſgreſſion it ſelfe, I meane, it ſignifieth the penalty for the offence committed, rather than the act it ſelfe, whereby the offence it ſelfe is perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and it extendeth both unto Lands and unto Goods; unto Lands, both Copyhold and Freehold.</p>
               <p>Touching the cauſes from whence ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the forfeiture of Copyhold Lands. I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake more liberally in another place, and therefore I will ſilently paſſe them over, ſpeaking ſome few words
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61518:25"/> touching the cauſes from whence Forfeitures of Freehold Land ariſe.</p>
               <p>The cauſes are many, amongſt the which I have obſerved. 1. That if any Freeholder alieneth his Land in Mortmaine, hee forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his Freehold. 2. If a Freeholder ceaſeth for the ſpace of two whole yeares, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſuch Services, or to pay ſuch Rents, as he is tied unto by his Tenure, and hath not upon his Land ſufficient goods or chattels to be diſtrained, he forfeiteth his Freehold. 3. If any Freeholder infringeth any conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereunto hee is tied, hee forfeiteth his Freehold.</p>
               <p>Touching the cauſes from whence grow the forfeitures of goods, they are likewiſe in number many, and from the ſeverall cauſes of forfeiting, goods ariſe ſeverall names of goods forfeited. 1. If a Felon ſtealeth goods, and upon purſuite made, waiveth theſe goods, and leaveth them in any part of the Manor, and be not attached upon the freſh ſuite of the owner; then are theſe goods forfeited to the Lord, and are termed waives. 2. If any beaſts are, found wandering in any place, and be proclaimed in three market Townes adjoyning, and are not claimed by the owner in a yeare and a day; then are the beaſts for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited to the Lord, who hath ſuch a liberty, and are termed Eſtrayes. 3. If any ſuffer
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61518:25"/> Shipwracke upon the Seas, and through the violence of the Waves, goods are caſt upon the Shore; and being ſeized by the Bayliffe, are not claymed within a yeare and a day after the ſeiſure; then are theſe goods forfeited to the Lord, who hath that Franchize, and are termed Wrecks. 4. If one come to a violent end, without the fault of any reaſonable creature, then immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atley that thing which is the cauſe of that untimely death, becommeth forfeited un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord; and it is termed a Deodand; as this old Verſe teſtifieth; <hi>Omnia quae movent ad mortem ſunt Deodanda:</hi> as if a Horſe ſtriketh his Keeper, and killeth him: or if a man driveth his Cart, and ſeeking to redreſſe it, falleth, and the Cart wheele running over him, preſſeth him to death; or if one felling a tree, giveth warning to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers by to look to themſelves, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding warning given, ſome body is ſlaine by the fall of the tree, the Horſe in the firſt Caſe; the Cart and the Horſes in the ſecond Caſe, &amp; the Tree in the third Caſe, are forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lord as Deodands: many other ſorts of forfeited goods I might adde unto this, but I will forbeare to enumerate any more in this kind; and to ſpeake more largely of theſe which I have already enumerated, for three ſpeciall reaſons;</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:61518:26"/>1. Becauſe they are duties accruing unto the Lord, not meerely from the Tenants, nor ſolely by the Act of the Tenants, but moſt commonly from ſtrangers, and by the ſole act of ſtrangers, and therefore I confeſſe are not aptly ranked under the name of Services. 2. Becauſe a perfect Manor may well ſubſiſt, without their aſſiſtance, ſince they adde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the perfection of the eſſence of a Manor. 3. becauſe they are not incident un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every Manor, but into ſuch Manors onely as can challenge them, either by ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, or by Patent from the King; for primarily and originally theſe forfeitures of goods, belonged to the King for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, eſpecially, becauſe what goods ſoever have no certaine owner knowne to challenge intereſt in them, as waives, eſtrayes, and wreckes, the propertie of ſuch goods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto the King, <hi>virtute praerogativae;</hi> and thus much <hi>Bracton</hi> intimateth, when he ſaith, <hi>Sunt alia quaedam quae in nullius bonis eſſe dicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſicut wreccum maris, &amp;c. &amp; aliae res, quae Dominum non habent ſicut animalia vagantia, &amp; quae ſunt Domini Regis propter privilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um marium:</hi> the reaſons why <hi>Deodands</hi> are forfeited to the King, is this;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deodands</hi> were originally invented for the pacifying of Gods wrath, and the appeaſing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61518:26"/> of Gods anger, and theſe things thus forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, were according to the true intendment of the Law to be ſold, and money diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the poore; and therefore upon whom could the Law have better confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this benefit, or rather impoſed this charge then upon the King, who repreſenteth Gods perſon upon the earth, and whom the Law preſumeth will deale more juſtly, and truely, nay, more liberally and bountifully with the poore in this kinde, than any inferior Lord, who peradventure out of his unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſe, peradventure out of want, will be ſo farre from adding any thing to that which is due, that hee will rather unjuſtly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract part, or unconſcionably detaine the whole.</p>
               <p>Since therefore, theſe Forfeitures of goods neither adde to the perfection of a Manor, neither are incident unto every Manor, to ſpend any further time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a ſubject ſo ſuperfluous would ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme this ſmall Treatiſe, wherein the ſcope and end I ayme at, is this, onely to preſent to your view what things ſoever are neceſſarily requiſite to the eſſence of every Manor, and what Services ſoever are incident unto every Manor: and thus much concerning Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; a word concerning Eſcheats.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:61518:27"/>
               <head>SEC. XXVIII.</head>
               <p>EScheates cometh of the <hi>French</hi> word <hi>Echear excidere,</hi> &amp; are termed <hi>excadentiae,</hi> which imports Lands fallen into the Lords hand for want of heire, generall or ſpeciall to inherit them, but before the Lord enter into an Eſcheate in this kinde, the homage ought to preſent it, and being preſented pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation ought to be made to give notice to the world, that if any man come in, and juſtly claime, he ſhall be received; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage then finding it cleare intitle the Lord, as to Lands Eſcheated.</p>
               <p>Beſides this ordinary ſort of Eſcheate, there is another ſort of Eſcheate, and that is, where any Freeholder committeth Felony, and is attainted, the King ſhall have <hi>animum diem &amp; vaſtum;</hi> and then it commeth unto the Lord as an Eſcheate; thus much concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the nature of Services in generall, and there are ſo many particular Services in <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduo,</hi> that I might inſiſt in millions more, but feare of incurring the cenſure of being over tedious, reſtraineth the forwardneſſe of my hand: yet ſithence occaſion is ſo favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me, I will preſume ſo much upon your patience, as to lay open the ſeverall remedies
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61518:27"/> which the Law hath provided for the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe ſeverall Services before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, if perchance they be wrongfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Tenants; and for method ſake, I will begin with corporall Services.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXIX.</head>
               <p>IF any Freeholder refuſeth to do homage, or fealty, which are corporall Services of ſubmiſſion; or to mend high wayes, repaire decaied Bridges; or <hi>ſimilia,</hi> which are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Services, tending to the publique pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Common-weale, or to diſcharge the office of a Carver, a Butler, a Brewer, or ſuch like; or to payle the Lords Parke, to tyle the Lords Houſes, or to thatch his Barnes, or <hi>ſimilia;</hi> which are corporall Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces tending to the private profit of the Lord; If, I ſay, any Freeholder refuſeth to do any of theſe Services, being bound unto them by his Tenure; then may the Lord lawfully di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreine his cattle or his goods, and detaine them untill ſatisfaction be given, by perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſuch Services as the Law doth require, and the ſame remedy which the Law hath provided for Corporall Services, is likewiſe provided for Annuall Services.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:61518:28"/>
               <head>SEC. XXX.</head>
               <p>FOr if any Freeholder refuſeth to pay any annuall Rent, or to diſcharge any annuall payment, according to his Tenure; then may the Lord lawfully diſtreine and in a Replevin brought by the Tenant, may avow the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and juſtifie the taking. But no action of debt will lye for theſe annuall Services, no more than for Corporall Services; for it is a ground in Law, that as long as the Rent continueth of any eſtate or Franke tenement, no action of debt lyeth for the arrearages of the Rent, nor for any other Service what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and therefore if a Leaſe for life be made reſerving rent, the Leſſor cannot main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine an action of debt for the arrearages of this Rent, as long as the eſtate continueth, but preſently upon the determination of the eſtate an action of debt lyeth for the arrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of the Rent incurred before the time of the determination: but what hath the Law provided no other remedy for thoſe annuall Services, then a diſtreſſe? Surely no, before ſeiſein, none, but after ſeiſein once gained, 'tis at his election, either to diſtreine, or to bring an Aſſize: and thus much touching remedies for corporall and annuall Services.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:61518:28"/>
               <head>SEC. XXXI.</head>
               <p>ACcidentall Services are gotten by many differing meanes; By ſeiſure onely, as the Wardſhip of the heires body together with the Waives, Eſtraies, Wreckes, Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dands, and ſuch like forfeitures of goods. 2. By th'entry onely, as the Wardſhip of the heires Land, together with Lands forfeited to the Lord, either upon the breach of ſome condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or upon an alienation in Mortmaine. 3. By Seiſure or Diſtreſſe, as Herriot Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, contrary to the opinion of ſome who held them gaineable by Diſtreſſe only, &amp; not by Seiſure, or action, as Herriot Cuſtomes; for upon the eloignement of the beſt beaſt, the Lord may maintain an action of deti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue againſt the heire. 5. By entry, or action as Lands forfeited to the Lord, by the ceſſing of his Tenant, or Eſcheat, accruing unto the Lord, either upon the attaindeur or death of his Tenant without heire; in the firſt, the Lord may enter or maint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine a Writ of Ceſſavit; in the ſecord, the Lord may enter or maintaine a Writ of Eſcheate. 6. By Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe or Action, as Reliefes and Amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For Reliefes the Lord may diſtreine, or bring an action of debt; neither doth this any whit impugne the former ground, that as long as the rent doth continue, &amp;c. becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede Reliefe is the fruit and approvement
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61518:29"/> of Services rather than any ſervice, and for Amerciaments the Lord may either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreine or bring an account of debt, other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy the Law hath provided againſt ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, for detaining of theſe duties from the Lord, as to inſiſt in one: if a ſtranger will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine the Wards body or the Wards land from the right Lord, a writ <hi>de recto de cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia terrae &amp; heraedis</hi> lyeth againſt the ſtranger, but to meddle with ſtrangers were to wander out of the little Common weale, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to keepe my ſelfe within my bounds and limits, I will here conclude, touching the two materiall cauſes of a Manor, <hi>viz.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes and Services: a word touching the efficient cauſe of a Manor, and then I will end the definition of a Manor.</p>
               <p>The efficient cauſe of a Manor is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in theſe words, of long continuance, for indeede time is the mother, or rather the nurſe of Manors; time is the ſoule that giveth life unto every Manor, without which a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor decayeth and dyeth, for tis not the two materiall cauſes of a Manor, but the efficient cauſe (knitting and uniting together thoſe two materialll cauſes) that maketh a Manor. Hence it is that the King himſelfe cannot create a perfect Manor at this day, for ſuch things as receive their perfection by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61518:29"/> of time, come not within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of a Kings Prerogative, and therefore the King cannot grant Freehold to hold by Copie, neither can the King create any new cuſtome, nor doe any thing that amounteth to the creation of a new cuſtome, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a compoſition made betweene the King and his Tenant, where he hath Herriot cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to pay 10. <hi>li.</hi> in Levie thereof every time it falleth, is no binding compoſition: for this amounteth to the creation of a new cuſtome. <hi>Et haec omnia &amp; ſimilia ſunt temporum non regum ſeu principum opera,</hi> which fully verifieth the old ſaying, <hi>Plus valet vulgaris conſuetudo quam regalis conceſsio,</hi> this is the ſole cauſe why the King cannot create a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Manor at this day, and this is the chiefe cauſe why a common perſon cannot create a perfect Manor, but not the ſole cauſe; for there is this cauſe farther, a perfect Manor cannot ſubſiſt without a perfect tenure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene very Lord and very Tenant: but a Common perſon cannot create a perfect te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, and conſequently cannot create a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Manor, before the Stat. of <hi>Quia emptores terrarum,</hi> if any Tenant ſeized of Land in Fee ſimple had infeoffed a ſtranger, he might have reſerved what ſervices hee thought fit, or had he reſerved no ſervices, yet the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61518:30"/> Law would have imployed a perfect tenure, betweene the Feoffor and the Feoffee, for the Feoffee was to hold off the Feoffor by the ſame ſervices, that the Feoffor held over on his Lord Paramount, but ſince this Statute, If a Tenant ſeiſed of Land in Fee, infeoffeth a ſtranger neither by the expreſſe reſervation of the Feoffor, nor by the implyed reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Law, can there bee a perfect tenure created at this day betweene the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offor and the Feoffee; for the Feoffee ſhall hold immediately of the Lord Paramount not of the Feoffor, and further, as the King can doe nothing which amounteth to the creation of a new cuſtome: ſo a common perſon can doe nothing which amounteth to the creation of a new tenure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if there be Lord and Tenant by 10. <hi>s.</hi> rent, and the Lord will confirme the eſtate of a Tenant <hi>Tenend.</hi> by a Hawke, a paire of gilt ſpurres, a Roſe or <hi>ſimilia,</hi> this is a voyd confirmation; otherwiſe had it beene if the Lord had confirmed the eſtate of the Tenant <hi>Tenendum per</hi> 5. <hi>s.</hi> that had beene a good confirmation, becauſe it tendeth onely to the abridgement of an old tenure, and not to the creation of a new, and as it is with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, ſo it is with a compoſition upon the reaſon of this ground, it is, that if the Lord
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61518:30"/> of a Manor purchaſe forraine land lying without the Precincts and bounds of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor he cannot annex this unto the Manor though the Tenants be willing to doe their Services, for this amounteth to the creation of a new tenure, which cannot be effected at this day; And therefore if a man having two Manors, and the Lord would willingly have the Tenants of both theſe Manors to doe their ſute and ſervice to one Court, this is but loſt labour in the Lord to practiſe any ſuch union; for notwithſtanding this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they will be ſtill two in Nature, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Lord covet to make them one in Name, and the one Manor hath no warrant to call the Tenants to the other Manor, but every act done in the one to puniſh the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the other is traverſable; yet if the Tenants will voluntary ſubmit themſelves to ſuch an innovation, and the ſame bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued without contradiction, time may make this union perfect, and of two diſtinct Manors in nature, make one in name and uſe: and ſuch Manors peradventure there are thus united by the conſent of the Tenants and continuance of time, but the Lords power of it ſelfe is not ſufficient to make any ſuch union, <hi>cauſa qua ſupra,</hi> But if one Manor hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of another, by way of Eſcheate theſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61518:31"/> two Manors may be united together, <hi>fortior enim eſt diſpoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tio legis quam hominis.</hi> But in this, that I exclude common perſons from being able to create a tenure, I may ſeeme to impugne many authorities which hold at this day, that a tenure may bee created by a common perſon, for to cleare this colour of contradiction, know that tenures are two fold. Firſt imperfect, as where a man maketh a Leaſe for yeares or for life, or a gift in tayle, here is an imperfect tenure betweene the Leſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the Leſſee, the Donor and the Donee; and this imperfect tenure I confeſſe may be created by a common perſon at this day. Secondly, perfect betweene very Lord and very tenant in Fee, and ſuch a tenure a common perſon could never create ſince the Stat. of <hi>Quia Emptores terrarum,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently a common perſon cannot create a perfect Manor ſithence, for without a perfect tenure a perfect Manor cannot ſubſiſt. Thus much touching the definition of a Manor, thus much I ſay touching the two materiall cauſes, together with the efficient cauſe. A word of another cauſe of a Manor which appeareth not in the defini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly as the other cauſes doe, this is a cauſe which among the Logicians is termed, <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> and that is a Court Baron; for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61518:31"/> indeede that is the chiefe prop and Pillar of a Manor, which no ſooner faileth but the Manor falleth to ground: if wee labour to ſearch out the antiquity of theſe Court Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, we ſhall finde them as ancient as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors themſelves. For when the ancient Kings of this Realme, who had all the lands of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Demeſne</hi> did conferre great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of land upon ſome great perſonages,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Lamb</hi> in his explication of <hi>Saxon</hi> words <hi>verbo Thanus. Bacon</hi> in his elements of the Law. <hi>fol.</hi> 41. 42. 43.</note> with liberty to parcell the land out to other inferiour Tenants, reſerving ſuch duties and Services as they thought convenient, and to keepe Courts where they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe miſdemeanors within their Precincts; puniſh offences committed by their Tenants, and deſide and debate controverſies ariſing within their juriſdiction; and their Courts were termed Court Barons, becauſe in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time ſuch perſonages were called Barons, and came to the Parliament, and ſate in the upper houſe; but when time had wrought ſuch an alteration, that Manors fell into the hands of meane men, and ſuch as were farre unworthy of ſo high a calling: then it grew to a cuſtome that none but ſuch as the King would ſhould come to the Parliament, ſuch as the King for their extraordinary wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or qualitie thought good to call by writ, which writ, ran <hi>hac vice tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um,</hi> yet
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61518:32"/> though Lords of Manors loſt their names of Barons, and were deprived of that dignity which was inherent to their names, yet their Courts retaine ſtill the name of Court Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, becauſe they were originally erected, for ſuch perſonages as were Barons; neither hath time beene ſo injurious as to eradicate the whole memory of their auncient dignity, in their name there is ſtamps left of their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, for they are ſtill intituled by the name of Lords. Theſe Courts differ from Court Leets in diverſe reſpects: In this, that Court Barons by the Law may be kept once every three weekes, or (as ſome thinke) as often as it ſhall pleaſe the Lord, though for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eaſe both of Lords and Tenants, they are kept but very ſeldome; but a Court Leete by the Statute of <hi>magna Charta</hi> is to bee kept but twice every yeare; one time within the moneth after Eaſter,<note place="margin">Magna Charta C. <hi>35. 31.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> Ca. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> and another time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a moneth after <hi>Michal.</hi> 2. In this, that Court Barons may bee kept in any place within the Manor, (contrary to the opinion of <hi>Brian.</hi>) But a Court Leete by the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> is to be kept in <hi>certo loco ac determinato,</hi> within the Precinct. 3. In this, that originally Court Barons belonged unto inferior Lords of Manors, but Court Leets originally belonged unto the King. 4. In
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61518:32"/> this, that Court Barons are incident unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y Manor, ſo that every Lord of a Manor may keepe a Court Baron, but few have Leets; for inferiour Lords of Manors cannot keepe Court Leetes without ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, or ſome ſpeciall Patent from the King. 5. In this, that in Court Barons the ſuitors are Iudges, but in Court Leets the Steward is Iudge. 6. In this, that in Court Barons the Iewrie conſiſteth oftentimes of leſſe than twelve, in Court Leets never; the reaſon of that is, becauſe none are impanel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon the Iewrie but Freeholders, in Court Barons of the ſame Manor, but in Court Leets ſtrangers are oftentimes impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelled. 7. In this, that Court Barons cannot ſubſiſt without two ſuitors <hi>adminimum</hi> but Court Leets can well ſubſiſt without any ſuitors. 8. In this, that Court Barons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of no offences committed againſt the King, but Court Leetes inquire of all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, under High Treaſon committed againſt the Crowne and dignity of the King. In many other reſpects they differ, as that a writ of errour, lyeth upon a judgement given in a Court Leete, but not in a Court Baron. So in a Court Leete a Capias lyeth, but in a Court Baron in ſteade of a Capias is uſed an Attachment by goods; So in a Court Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61518:33"/> an action of debt lyeth for the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe the ſuitors are Judges, but in a Court Leete the Lord cannot maintaine any action for himſelfe, becauſe the Steward is Iudge; but omitting theſe with many more, I come to the Etymologie of a Manor. Some derive the word Manor <hi>a manendo,</hi> and then it taketh his name either from the Manor-houſe which the Lord maketh his dwelling place, or elſe <hi>a manendo quia Dominus ac te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentes in Manerii ſui circuit cohabitant ac ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</hi> Some thinke tis termed Manor from manuring the ground, and then it taketh its name either from the Lords Demeſnes, which the Tenants are bound to Manure, or elſe from the Land remaining in the Tenants hands, which are likewiſe tilled and manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; others are of opinion that it is derived of the <hi>French</hi> word <hi>meſner,</hi> which ſignifieth to governe or guide, becauſe the Lord of a Manor hath the guiding and directing of all his Tenants within the limits of his juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and this I hold the moſt probable Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie and moſt agreeing with the nature of a Manor: for a Manor in theſe dayes ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the juriſdiction and royalty incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, rather than the Land or Scite; Thus much touching the Etymologie. A word touching the diviſion of a Manor; A Manor
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61518:33"/> is twofold, <hi>re &amp; nomine:</hi> 2. <hi>Nomine tantum, re &amp; nomine,</hi> as where the two materiall cauſes of a Manor, the efficient cauſe, <hi>&amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſine qua non,</hi> doe meete and joyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>nomine tantum,</hi> as where any of theſe cauſes is wanting, as to inſiſt in the two mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cauſes, if the Lord will transferre over to ſome ſtranger the ſervices of all his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and reſerve unto himſelfe the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes; or if he will paſſe away the Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnes, and reſerve the ſervices: in both cauſes the Lord peradventure hath a Manor, <hi>nomine</hi> but not otherwiſe, becauſe in the one cauſe he wanteth Demeſnes, in the other ſervices. So if a Manor diſcendeth to Co-parteners and they make partition, and the intire De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes are allotted to the one and th' intire ſervices to the other, the Manor is now in ſuſpence, for neither of them hath any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor but in name onely: but if part of the Demeſnes and part of the Services be allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to each one, then have they each of them a Manor, not <hi>nomine tantum,</hi> but <hi>re &amp; nomine.</hi> To inſiſt in the efficient cauſes, If the King at this day will grant a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of land to any Subject, injoyning him certaine duties and ſervices, and withall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that this ſhould beare the name of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, howſoever this may chance to gaine
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61518:34"/> the name of a Manor, yet it will not be a Manor in th' eſtimation of the law; to inſiſt in this cauſe, <hi>ſine qua non,</hi> If the King grant away a Manor to <hi>I. S.</hi> excepting the Courts and perquiſites, the Grantee hath a Manor in name onely: So if all the Freeholders dye but one, if the Lord purchaſe all the Freeholders land, or paſſe away the Services of the Freeholders, or releaſe unto his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders all their ſervices, notwithſtanding the Demeſnes and the Services of the Copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, yet the Lord hath but a Manor in name, becauſe the Freeholders are wanting which are the maintainers and upholders of the Court Baron, and conſequently neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry helpe to the perfection of a Manor. So if the Lord granteth away the inheritance of all his Copyholders, or demiſeth all his lands granted by Copie to another for 2000. yeares, the Grantee in the one caſe and the leſſee in the other, have a kinde of Seigniority in groſſe, and may keepe a Cuſtomary Court, where the Steward ſhall be Judge, and ſhall take ſurrenders, and make admittances; and this in the eye of the world is a Manor, though in the judgement of the law it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth far ſhort of one. Thus much touching the diviſion of a Manor. I might here handle many collaterall juriſdictions, appropriated
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61518:34"/> to Lords of Manors, as that our erecting Dove-houſes, of proving the Wills of their Tenants deceaſed within their Precincts in many places; of incloſing Common, leaving ſufficient beſides for the other Commoners, with many of the like; <hi>Sed haec lubens libenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que omitio.</hi> And thus cloſing up this part of my Treatiſe touching Manors. I come to the other part touching Copyhold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXII.</head>
               <p>INeede not ſtand to diſcourſe at large th'antiquitie of the Copyholders; for if you caſt your eye backe to that is paſt, you ſhall eaſily perceive that Copyholders, though very meanely diſcended, yet they come of an ancient houſe; and therefore if in this point you deſire ſatisfaction, call to minde what I have already ſpoken; and (if I miſtake not) it will ſufficiently anſwer your deſire. Give me leave to goe a ſteppe further, and to examine the ſeverall names which Copyholders have had from time to time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted unto them, together, with their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Etymologies immediatly upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt: they were knowne by the name of Villaines or Tenants in Villanage; ſo termed by the <hi>Normans,</hi> either in reſpect of Imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillity
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61518:35"/> and incertainty of their eſtates, which were grounded upon a very weake foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wholly depending upon the will of the Lord, and Ouſtable at his pleaſure; or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Services, which ſavoured of nothing but ſlavery, whether they were, <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ac determinata,</hi> or <hi>incerta ac indeterminata, ubi ſciri non poterit veſpere, quale ſervitium fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere deberent in Craſtino,</hi> as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſpeaketh; contrary to the opinion of ſome, who hold, that the Service of Copiholders were never ſubject to ſuch incertainties: or laſtly, in reſpect of the perſons, who for the moſt part were Villaines; howſoever ſome free men did ſometimes hold Land by the ſame Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure: the leaſt of theſe three reaſons is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make them deſerve that name, but joyne them together, and then hee that judgeth moſt favorably of them, will thinke this the trueſt title that could be beſtowed upon them, yet ſome there are, who in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of theſe Tenants, ſticke not to maintaine (howſoever in reſpect of their eſtates, they may not unfitly be termed Tenants in Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, being in ſuch ſtrange ſubjection to their Lords) that neither in reſpect of their Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor their Perſons they could merit that name; eſpecially if we take the word in that reproachfull ſenſe that it is uſually taken in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61518:35"/> at this houre. But if wee account thoſe vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine Services which any way touch Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, as Plowing, Sowing, Reaping, and ſuch like; and theſe men villaines, who exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe themſelves in any point of Husbandry, then they agrue, that their Tenure could in no wiſe have an apter terme than this; for they confeſſe, that theſe Copyholders were for the moſt part, <hi>Ruſtici &amp; Pagani,</hi> and their Services whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, <hi>ad Ruſticitatem tendentia:</hi> Howſoever, I dare not wholly diſallow of this opinion, though I cannot altogether ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it, for I admit, and in a manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that amongſt the <hi>Normans,</hi> theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, which wee call Rurall Services, were called <hi>villaine</hi> Services; and thoſe men whom we terme Husbandmen were termed Villaines; and doe hold that the Copyhold Services in thoſe dayes were more ſlaviſh, than Rurall; and they themſelves rather Bondmen, than Husbandmen; otherwiſe we ſhould make their Tenure differ in nothing from ancient Soccage Tenure, which I aſſure my ſelfe is otherwiſe: for though Soccagres were Ruſtiques, and in that ſenſe Villaines; yet their Tenure was never noted by the name of a Tenure in Villenage, till in many places their Corporall Services begun to be turned into money: then for diſtinction ſake,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:61518:36"/> the one began to be called <hi>Liberum Soccagium;</hi> the other, <hi>Villanium Soccagium.</hi> But long before theſe Coppiholders, were termed <hi>Villeynes,</hi> and therefore without all doubt their Tenure was in baſeneſſe and ſlavery, a degree above the ancient Soccage Tenure; till at length the Lords of Manors being fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to more civility, began then to thinke it a moſt uncharitable part to keepe their poore Tenants in that bondage; therefore out of the remorſe of their owne conſciences, and the compaſſion of their Tenants miſeries, by little and little, they infranchiſed them, and releaſed them of their heavier burthens, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Services of another nature in liew of them. Thus having ſhaken off the fetters of their bondage, they were preſently freed of their opprobrious name, and had other new gentle ſtiles, and titles conferred upon them; they were every where then called Tenants by Copy of Court Roll, or Tenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s at will, according to the Cuſtome of the Manor: which ſtyles import unto us three things. 1. <hi>Nomen.</hi> 2. <hi>Originem.</hi> 3. <hi>Titulum.</hi> His name is Tenant by Copy of Court Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; for he is not called Tenant by Court-Role, but by Copy of Court-Roll; and this is the ſole Tenant in Law, who holdeth by Copy of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Record, Charter, Deede, or any other
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61518:36"/> thing. 2. His commencement is at the will of the Lord. For theſe Tenants in their birth, as well as the Cuſtomary Tenants upon the borders of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who have the name of Tenant; were meere Tenants at will: and though they keepe the Cuſtomes inviolated, yet the Lord might, ſans controll, eject them: neither was their eſtate hereditarie, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; as appeareth by <hi>Britton:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Britton Ca. <hi>66.</hi>
                  </note> for if they died, their eſtate was preſently determined, as in caſe of a Tenant at will at common Law; and in ſome points, to this preſent houre, the Law regardeth them no more, than a meere Tenant at will; for the Freehold at the Common Law, reſteth not in them, but in their Lords; unleſſe it be in Copyholds of Franke Tenure, which are moſt uſuall in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Demeſne; though ſometimes out of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Demeſne, wee ſhall meete with the like ſort of Copyholds, as in <hi>Northamton-Shire,</hi> there are Tenants which hold by Copy of Court-Roll, and have no other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and yet hold not at the will of the Lord. Theſe kinde of Copyholders have the Franke Tenure in them, and it is not in their Lords, as in caſe of Copyholds in baſe Tenure. Beſides, Copyholders ſhall not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne upon the granting away of the Manor, no more than Tenants at will at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61518:37"/> Law; and their eſtate can be no infran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſement to a villaine, no more then a meere eſtate at will. And further, their Lands are parcell of the Lords Demeſnes, as well as Lands granted away at Will, according to the courſe of the Common Law; and for his Title and Aſſurance, that is according to the Cuſtome of the Manor: For the Cuſtome of the Manor hath ſo eſtabliſhed, and ſo fixed them in their Land, that if they doe their Services and Duties, and performe the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the Manor, they are as well inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, according to the Cuſtome, as he that hath a Franck Tenement at the Common Law: and ſithence Cuſtome is the life and ſoule of Copyhold Eſtates, and whatſoever ſhall, or can be ſpoken touching Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, ariſeth from this Head, and from this Fountaine; Give mee leave in the ſecond place to ſpeake ſomething concerning them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXIII.</head>
               <p>CVſtomes are defined to be a Law, or Right not written, which being eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by long uſe, and the conſent of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, hath beene, and is daily practiſed.</p>
               <p>Cuſtome, Preſcription, and Vſage; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61518:37"/> there be correſpondencie amongſt them, and dependancie one on the other,<note place="margin">Cuſtome, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, and Vſage, how they differ.</note> and in common ſpeech, one of them is taken for another, yet they are three diſtinct things; Cuſtome and Preſcription differ in this. 1. Cuſtome cannot have any commencement ſince the memory of man, but a Preſcription may, both by the Comon-Law, and the Civill: and therefore where the <hi>Statute.</hi> 1. <hi>H.</hi> 8. ſaith, that all actions popular, muſt be brought within three yeares after the offence commi ted; whoſoever offendeth againſt this <hi>Statute,</hi> and doth eſcape uncalled for three yeares, he may be juſtly ſaid to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe an immunity againſt any ſuch action. 2. A Cuſtome toucheth many men in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; Preſcription, this, or that man in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: and that is the reaſon why Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is perſonall, and is alwayes made in the name of ſome perſon certaine, and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, or thoſe whoſe eſtate he hath; but a Cuſtome having no perſon certaine in whoſe name to preſcribe, is therefore called and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged after this manner. In ſuch a Borough, in ſuch a Manor, there is this or that Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome. And for Vſage, that is the efficient cauſe, or rather, the life of both; for Cuſtome and Preſcription loſe their being if Vſage faile. Should I goe about to make a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61518:38"/> of ſeverall Cuſtomes, I ſhould with <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphus ſaxum volvere,</hi> undertake an endleſſe piece of worke, therefore I will forbeare, ſince the relation would be an argument of great curioſity, and a taske of great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: I will onely ſet downe a briefe diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Cuſtomes, and leave the particulars to your owne obſervation. Cuſtomes are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generall or particular; generall, which are part of the Common law, being currant through the whole Common-wealth, and uſed in every County, every City, every Towne, and every Manor. Particular, which are confined to ſhorter bounds and limits, and have not ſuch choyce of fields to walke in, as generall Cuſtomes have. Theſe particular Cuſtomes are of two ſorts, either diſallowing what generall Cuſtomes doe allow, or allowing what generall Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes doe diſallow, as for example ſake. By the generall Cuſtomes of Manors it is in the Copiholders power to ſell to whom he pleaſeth, but by a particular Cuſtome uſed in ſome places, the Copyholder before he can inforce his Lord to admit any one to his Copihold, is to make a proffer to the next of the blood, or to the next of his Neighbours <hi>ab oriente ſolis,</hi> who giving as much as the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to whom the Surrender was made, ſhould
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61518:38"/> have it: ſo on the other ſide by the generall Cuſtomes of Manors, the paſſing away of Copyhold land by deede for more than for one yeare without licence is not warranted; yet ſome particular cuſtomes in ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors doe it: ſo by the generall Cuſtomes of Manors Preſentments, or any other act done in the Leete, after the moneth expired, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Statute of <hi>magna Charta,</hi> and 31. <hi>E</hi> 3. are voyd, yet by ſome particular Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes ſuch acts are good, and ſo in millions of the like, as in the ſequell of this diſcourſe ſhall be made manifeſt. And therefore, not to inſiſt any longer in dilucidating this point, let us in few words learne the way how to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the validitie of a Cuſtome: For our direction in this buſineſſe, wee ſhall doe well to obſerve theſe ſixe Rules, which will ſerve us for exact tryall. 1. Cuſtomes and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions ought to be reaſonable, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Cuſtome that no Tenant of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſhall put in his Chattell to uſe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>in Campis ſeminatis:</hi> after the Corne ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, untill the Lord have put in his Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, is a voyd Cuſtome, becauſe unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, for peradventure the Lord will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put in his Chattell, and then the Tenants ſhall loſe their profits: ſo if the Lord will preſcribe that he hath ſuch a Cuſtome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61518:39"/> his Manor, that if any mans beaſts be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by him upon his Demeſnes damage Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, that he may detaine them untill the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the beaſts give him ſuch recompence for his harmes as he himſelfe ſhall requeſt; this is an unreaſonable Cuſtome, for no man ought to be his owne Judge. 2. Cuſtomes and Preſcriptions ought to be according to common right, and therefore if the Lord will preſcribe to have of every Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der belonging to his Manor, for every Court he keepeth, a certaine ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, this is a voyd preſcription, becauſe it is not according to common Right, for hee ought for Iuſtice ſake to doe it <hi>Gratis;</hi> but if the Lord preſcribe to have a certaine Fee of his Tenants, for keeping an extraordinary Court, which is purchaſed onely for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of ſome particular Tenants, to take up their Copyholds and ſuch like; this is a good preſcription, and according to common right. 3. They ought to be upon good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and therefore if the Lord will preſcribe that whoſoever paſſeth through the Kings High way which lyeth through his Manor, ſhould pay him a peny for paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, this preſcription is voyd, becauſe it is not upon a good conſideration; but if hee will preſcribe to have a peny of every one
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61518:39"/> that paſſeth over ſuch a bridge within his Manor, which bridge the Lord doth uſe to repaire, this is a good preſcription and upon a good conſideration. So if the Lord will preſcribe to have a fine at the marriage of his Copyholder, in which Manor the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome doth admit the husband to be Tenant by the curteſie, or the feme Tenant in Dower of a Copyhold, this preſcription is good and upon a good conſideration; but in ſuch Manors where theſe eſtates are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, the Law is otherwiſe. 4. They ought to be compulſary, and therefore if the Lord will preſcribe that every Copyholder ought to give him ſo much every moneth to beare his charges in time of warre, this preſcription is voyd; but to preſcribe they ought to pay ſo much money for that purpoſe is a good preſcription, for a payment is compulſary, but a gift is Arbitrary at the voluntary liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the giver. 5. They ought to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; and therefore if the Lord will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe that whenſoever any of his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders dye without heire, that then another of the Copyholders ſhall hold the ſame lands for the yeere following, this preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is voyd., for the incertainty; but if the Lord will preſcribe to have of his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, 2. <hi>d.</hi> an Acre Rent, in time of warre
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61518:40"/> foure pence an Acre, this preſcription is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine enough. 6. They ought to be bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to them that alledge the preſcription; and therefore if the Lord preſcribeth that the cuſtome hath alwayes beene within the Manor, that what diſtreſſe ſoever is taken within his Manor for any common perſons cauſe, is to be impounded for a certaine time within his pound; this is no good preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the Lord is hereby to receive a charge and no commoditie: but if the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription goeth further, that the Lord ſhould have for every beaſt ſo impounded a certaine ſumme of money, this is a good preſcription. If we deſire to be more fully ſatisfied in the generall knowledge of preſcriptions and Cuſtomes, wee ſhall finde many Maximes which make very materiall for this purpoſe, amongſt which I have made choyſe of theſe three, as moſt worthy of your obſervation. 1. Things gained by matter of Record one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, cannot be challenged by preſcription, and therefore no Lord of a Manor can preſcribe to have fellons goods, fugitives goods, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dands and ſuch like; becauſe they cannot bee forfeited untill it appeare of Record: but waves, eſtraies, wreckes and ſuch like may be challenged by preſcription, becauſe they are gained by uſage without matter of Record.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61518:40"/> 2. A cuſtome never extendeth to a thing newly created, and therefore if a Rent be granted out of Gavelkind-land, or Land in <hi>Borough-Engliſh,</hi> the rent ſhall deſcend, acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courſe of the Common Law, not according to the Cuſtome. If before the <hi>Statute</hi> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. Lands were deviſeable in any Borough, or City by ſpeciall Cuſtome; A Rent granted out of theſe Lands was not deviſeable by the ſame Cuſtome; for what things ſoever have their beginning, ſince the memory of man, Cuſtome maintaines not. If there be a Cuſtome within a Manor, that for every houſe or cottage two ſhillings fine ſhall be paid, if any Tenant within theſe liberties maketh two houſes of one, or buildeth a new houſe, hee ſhall not pay a fine for any of theſe new houſes; for the Cuſtome onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to the old. So if I have Eſtovers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant to my houſe, and I build a new houſe, I ſhall not have Eſtovers for this new built houſe upon this ground. It hath beene doubted, if a man by Preſcription hath courſe of water to his Fulling-mill, hee converting theſe into Corne-mills, whether by this converſion the Preſcription is not deſtroyed, in regard that theſe Come-mills are things newly created; but becauſe the qualitie of the thing, and not the ſubſtance is altered;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61518:41"/> therefore this alteration is held inſufficient to overthrow the Preſcription; for if a man by Preſcription hath Eſtovers to his houſe, although they alter the Roomes and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the houſe, as by making a Parlor where there was a Hall, <hi>vele converſo,</hi> yet the Preſcription ſtands ſtill in force: and ſo if by Preſcription I have an ancient Window to my Hall, and I convert this into a Parlor, yet my neighbours upon this change cannot ſtoppe my Window; <hi>Cauſa qua ſupra.</hi> 3. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes are likewiſe taken ſtrictly, though not alwayes literally. There is a Cuſtome in <hi>London,</hi> that Citizens and Freemen may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe in Mortmayne. A Citizen that is a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiner, cannot deviſe by this Cuſtome. An Infant by the Cuſtome of <hi>Gavelkind,</hi> at th'age of fifteene, may make a Feoffment; yet he cannot by the Cuſtome make a Will at that age to paſſe away his Land; to make a Leaſe, and a Releaſe, which amounteth to a Feoffment. If there be any Cuſtome that Copyhold-Lands may be leaſed by the Lord, <hi>vel per Superviſor. vel deputatum ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoris:</hi> This Cuſtome giveth not power to the Lord, to authorize any by his laſt Will and Teſtament, to keepe a Court in their owne name, and to make Leaſes, <hi>Secundum conſuetudinem Manerii:</hi> but theſe Cuſtomes
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61518:41"/> have this ſtrict conſtruction, becauſe they tend to the derogation of the Common Law; yet they are not to be confined to literall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; for if there be a Cuſtome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any Manor, that Copyhold Lands may be granted in <hi>Feodo ſimplici,</hi> by the ſame Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome they are grantable to one, and the heires of his body, for life, for yeares, or any other eſtate whatſoever; becauſe, <hi>Cui licet quod majus, non debet quod minus eſt non licere;</hi> ſo if there be a Cuſtome that Copyhold Lands, may be granted for life; by the ſame Cuſtome they may be granted, <hi>Durante vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duitate,</hi> but not <hi>e converſo,</hi> becauſe an eſtate during Widdowhood, is leſſe than an eſtate for life. Before the <hi>Statute</hi> of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. Lands in certaine Boroughs were deviſable by Cuſtome. By the ſame Cuſtome was <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite</hi> warranted, authorizing Executors to ſell Lands deviſable. Now with your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I will onely point at the manner of pleading of Cuſtomes, I finde a foure-fold kinde of Preſcribing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To preſcribe in his Predeceſſors, as in himſelfe, and all thoſe whoſe eſtate hee hath.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To preſcribe generally, not tying his Preſcription to place, or perſon, as where a Chiefe Juſtice preſcribeth, that it hath beene
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61518:42"/> uſed, that every Chiefe Juſtice may grant Offices; or where a Sergeant preſcribeth, <hi>Quod talis habetur conſuetudo,</hi> that Sergeants ought to be impleaded by originall Writ, and not by Bill.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To Preſcribe in a place certaine.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To Preſcribe in the place of another.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſort of theſe Preſcriptions, a Copyholder cannot uſe, in regard of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity of his eſtate; for no man can Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe in that manner, but onely Tenants in Fee ſimple at the Common Law.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort of theſe may be uſed ſometimes by Copyholders in the pleading of a generall Cuſtome, but in alleadging of a particular Cuſtome, a Copyholder is driven to one of the laſt, and as occaſion ſerveth, he uſeth ſometimes the one, ſometimes the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If he be to clayme Common, or other profit in the ſoyle of the Lord, then he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preſcribe in the name of the Lord, for the Lord cannot preſcribe to have Common or other profit in his owne ſoyle; but then the Copyholder muſt of neceſſity preſcribe in a place certaine, and alleadge, that within ſuch a Manor, there is ſuch a Cuſtome, that all the Tenants within that Manor, have uſed to have Common in ſuch a place, parcell of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61518:42"/> the Manor: but if he be to claime Common, or other profit in the ſoyle of a ſtranger, then he ought to preſcribe in the name of his Lord, ſaying, that the Lord of the Manor, and all his Anceſtors, and all thoſe whoſe eſtate he hath, were wont to have a Common in ſuch a place for himſelfe, and his Tenants at will, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXIV.</head>
               <p>THus much of Cuſtomes. I come now home to Copyholders: and in the third place I hold it the beſt courſe to dilate upon the manner and meanes of granting Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds; wherein I will onely rely upon theſe five parts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Vpon the perſon of the Grantor.</item>
                  <item>2. Vpon the perſon of the Grantee.</item>
                  <item>3. Vpon the Grant it ſelfe.</item>
                  <item>4. Vpon the thing Granted.</item>
                  <item>5. Vpon the Inſtruments, through whoſe hands, as through Conduit-pipes, the Lands are <hi>Gradatim,</hi> conveyed to the Purchaſor.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And firſt, of the perſon of the Grantor. Sometimes the Lord himſelfe is Grantor; ſometimes a Copyholder. In voluntary Grants made by the Lord himſelfe, the Law
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61518:43"/> neither reſpecteth the quality of his Perſon, nor the quantity of his Eſtate; for be hee an Infant, and ſo through the tenderneſſe of his age, inſufficient to diſpoſe of any Land at the Common Law, or <hi>non compos mentis,</hi> an Idiot, or a Lunatique; and ſo for want of common reaſon, unable to traffique in the world; or an Out-law in any perſonall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo excluded from the protection of the Law; or an Excommunicate, &amp;c. and ſo reſtrained, <hi>ab omnium fidelium communione,</hi> or at leaſt, <hi>à Sacramentorum partitipatione:</hi> notwithſtanding theſe infirmities and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, yet he is capable enough to make a voluntary grant by Copy, for if a <hi>feme ſeignio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſe</hi> take Baron, and they two joyne in a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Grant by Copy, this ſhall ever binde the <hi>Feme</hi> and her heires, and yet ſhe is not <hi>ſui juris,</hi> but <hi>ſub poteſtate viri,</hi> becauſe the Cuſtome of the Manor is the chiefe <hi>baſis,</hi> upon which ſtands the whole fabricke of the Copyhold eſtate, and therefore what Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome doth confirme to a Copyholder, the Law will ever allow, and never ſeeke to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it, in reſpect of any ſuch imperfection in the Grantors perſons, and the quantity of the Lords eſtate is no more reſpected than the qualitie of his perſon: for if his intereſt be lawfull, be his eſtate never ſo great, or never
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:61518:43"/> ſo little 'tis not materiall; for be it in Fee, or be it in tayle or dower, or as Tenant by cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, for life or for yeares, as Guardian, or as Tenant by Statute, or as Tenant by Elegit, or at will; the leaſt of theſe eſtates, is a ſufficient warrant to the Lord, to Grant any Copyhold eſheated unto him: for as long time as the Cuſtome doth allow; the ancient Rents and Services, being truely reſerved, and theſe Grants ſhall ever binde them that have the Inheritance, or Franck-Tenement of the Manor, as well as offices granted for life, by the chiefe Juſtice of the <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> whoſe office is but at will, ſhall ever conclude the ſucceeding Juſtice. The reaſon of the Law is this. A Copyholder upon voluntary Grants made by Copy, doth not derive his eſtate out of the Lords eſtate onely, for then the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders eſtate ſhould ceaſe, when the Lords intereſt determineth, <hi>Nam ceſſante: primitivo ceſſat derivativus,</hi> but the life of the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders eſtate is the Cuſtome of the Manor; and therefore whatſoever befalleth the Lords intereſt in his Manor, be it determined by the courſe of time, by death, by forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or other meanes; yet if the Lord were <hi>Legitimus Dominus pro tempore;</hi> how ſmall ſo ever his eſtate was, that is enough, for the ſame Cuſtome that fixeth a Copyholder in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61518:44"/> in his land upon his admittance, will likewiſe preſerve, and protect his intereſt, to the end, in ſuch manner, that though the Lords intereſt faileth, yet his ſhall never fall to ground, being upheld by ſuch a proppe, ſuch a pillar, unleſſe perchance the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder offer violence to his Founder in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Cuſtome. If the Lord granteth a Copyhold, and after doth ſever this Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder from the Manor, by granting the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance to a ſtranger, though now one of the chiefe pillars of a Copyhold eſtate is wanting, <hi>viz.</hi> to be parcell of the Manor; yet becauſe the Land, at the time of the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders admittance, had this neceſſary inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, this ſeverance, being a matter <hi>ex poſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> cannot amount to the deſtruction of the Copyhold, eſpicially being the ſole act of the Lord himſelfe. If a Manor be granted upon Condition, and before the Condition is broken, the Land is granted by Copy, then the Manor become forfeited, and the Feoffer entreth; yet the Copyhold eſtate remaineth untouched, becauſe lawfully eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Cuſtome, and yet all meane eſtates and charges whatſover, granted by the Feoffee at the Common Law were void<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able upon the entry of the Feoffer; for wee have a ground in Law, that when an entry is
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61518:44"/> made for breach of a Condition, the party to all intents and purpoſes, is in the ſame plight that he was in at the time of the making of the eſtate. If a man ſeized of a Manor in Fee, dieth ſeized, having iſſue, a daughter; and his wife being <hi>privement inſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt</hi> with a ſonne, and the daughter granteth Lands by Copy, this Grant ſhall ſtand good againſt the ſonne, for the daughter was <hi>Legitim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Domina pro tempore.</hi> So if the Feoffee of a Manor, upon Condition to infeoffe a ſtranger, the next day maketh a voluntary Grant by Copy, this ſhall binde, and yet his intereſt was to have but ſmall continuance. If a Manor be Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a <hi>feme</hi> in Francke marriage, and there is a divorce had, <hi>cauſa paercontractus;</hi> ſo that now the intereſt of the Manor is now granted to the <hi>feme</hi> onely, and by relation, the marriage is void, <hi>ab initio:</hi> yet becauſe the Baron was <hi>Legitimus Dominus pro tempore,</hi> any Copyholders eſtates granted, before the divorce, remaine good. So if a man eſpouſeth a <hi>feme ſeignioreſſe,</hi> under the age of conſent; and after ſhe doth diſagree, though the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage by relation was voide, <hi>ab initio,</hi> yet Copyholds granted before diſagreement, ſhall never be avoided, <hi>cauſa qua ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Lord of a Manor committeth felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61518:45"/> or murder, and proces of Outlawry, be awarded againſt him, after the Exigent, hee granteth Copyhold eſtates, according to the Cuſtome, and then is attainted, theſe Grants are authenticall, though by relation, the Manor was forfeited, from the time of the Exigent awarded. So if the Lord had beene attainted by Verdict, or Confeſſion, any Grant by Copy, after the Felony, or murder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſhall ſtand good, notwithſtanding the relation. If the Lord of a Manor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a Statute, and then granteth Lands by Copy; and after the Manor is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Cogniſee in extent; the Grant cannot by this be impeached. And if the Lord of a Manor taketh a wife, and after maketh Copyhold eſtates, according to the Cuſtome, and dieth, though the <hi>feme</hi> hath this Manor aſſigned unto her for her Dower, yet cannot ſhee avoide theſe Copyhold eſtates, becauſe the Copyholders are in by a title Paramount, the title of the <hi>feme, viz.</hi> by Cuſtome. But paradventure, if the heire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of his Anceſtor, before the Aſſignment made unto the <hi>feme</hi> for her Dower, had granted Lands by Copy, the <hi>feme</hi> might avoide theſe Grants, becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly upon the death of the Baron, her title received his perfection, and nothing more
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61518:45"/> was wanting to the confirmation of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: but though the quantity of the Lords eſtate in the Manor be not reſpected, yet the quantity of his eſtate in the Copyhold is regarded. For if a Copyholder in Fee ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render to the uſe of the Lord for life, the Remainder over to a ſtranger, or reſerveth the Reverſion to himſelfe, if the Lord will Grant this by Copy in Fee, whatſoever eſtate the Lord hath in his Manor; yet having but an eſtate for life in the Copyhold; no larger eſtate ſhall paſſe, then hee himſelfe hath, <hi>Quia nemo potest plus juris in alium transferre quam ipſe habet:</hi> and further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that ſometimes the Law reſpecteth the quantity of the Lords eſtate in the Manor; for what Acts ſo ever are not confirmed by Cuſtome, but onely ſtrengthned by the power, authority, and intereſt of the Lord, have no longer continuance than the Lords eſtate continueth, and therefore it is held, that if a Tenant for life of a Manor, granteth a licence to a Copyholder to alien, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the Licence is deſtroyed, and the power of alienation ceaſeth. As for the quality of the Lords eſtate in the Manor, that is much more now reſpected, than either the qualitie of his eſtate, or the qualitie of his perſon: for if the Lord, or he who ſoever it be that maketh a voluntary Grant
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61518:46"/> by Copy, hath no lawfull intereſt in the Manor, but onely an uſurped title, his Grant ſhall never ſo bind the right owner; but that upon his entry hee may avoide them, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wee ſhould make Cuſtome an agent in a wrong, which the Law will never ſuffer; and yet if the Lord of a Manor by his Will in writing deviſeth, that his Executor ſhall Grant Copy hold eſtates, <hi>Secundum conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Manerii,</hi> for the payment of his debts, &amp;c. and they make voluntary Grants accordingly: theſe Grants are good, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Executor hath no intereſt in the Manor, nor is <hi>Dominus pro tempore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Diſſeinor of a Manor dieth ſeized, notwithſtanding his heire come in by ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe of deſcent, yet becauſe the Tort commenced by his Anceſtor, is ſtill inherent to his eſtate, if any Copihold eſtate be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the heire, it may be avoided by the Diſſeinor, immediatly upon his recovery, or upon his entry; and ſo if the Diſſeinor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feoffe a ſtranger of the Manor; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Feoffee come in by title, yet no grant made by him of Copyhold-Land, ſhall ever binde the Diſſeined, no more than a Grant made by the Diſſeinor himſelfe.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Tayle of a Manor diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61518:46"/> and dieth; and after the diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance Granteth Copyhold, eſtates, the heire recovering in a Formidon in the Diſcender, may avoid theſe Grants; for though the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continue come in under a juſt title, yet his intereſt being determined by the death of the Tenant in Tayle, the continuance of the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion is a Tort to the heire, and Acts done by Tort-ſciſors tending to the diſ-inheritance of the right owners Cuſtome, will never ſo ſtrengthen, but they may be adnihilated. So if a man ſeized of a Manor in right of his wife, Alieneth this Manor and dieth, any Grant made of Copyhold eſtates, after his death may be avoided by the <hi>feme,</hi> upon her entry, or upon her recovery, in a <hi>Gui in vita.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Manor be Granted, <hi>pr. aut. vie,</hi> and <hi>Ceſtay que vie</hi> dyeth, and the Grantee continueth ſtill in the Manor, and maketh Grants by Copy, theſe ſhall not binde the Grantor of the Manor; for immediately upon the death of <hi>Ceſtay que vie,</hi> the Grantee was but a Tenant at ſufferance, and had no Manor of Lawfull intereſt, for a Writ of Entry, <hi>ad terminum qui preter sit,</hi> lieth againſt him, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Deforceor.</p>
               <p>And ſo if a Tenant for life of a Manor
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61518:47"/> maketh a Leaſe for yeares of the ſame Manor and dieth, Copyhold eſtates granted by the Leſſee, after the death of the Tenant for life, are voideable by the firſt Leſſor.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for yeares of a Manor granteth a Copyhold in Reverſion, and before the Reverſion eſchue, the terme is expired, the Grant is void; and ſo I take the Law to be, if the Leſſee ſurrendreth his terme, and then before his Leaſe ſhould have ended in point of limitation, the Reverſion falleth, yet the Grantee ſhall not have it.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made for yeares of a Manor, the Leaſe to be voide upon the breach of a certaine Condition, if the Condition be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and afterwards the Leſſee before the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Leſſor, granteth eſtates by Copy, theſe Grants ſhall never exclude the Leſſor: for preſently upon the breach of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; the Leaſe is voyde, but had the Manor beene granted for life, in Tayle or in Fee, I thinke Law would have fallen out o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, for before entry, the Franck-Tenement had not beene avoided, and whereſoever a man may enter and avoide any eſtate of Franck-Tenement, upon the breach of a Condition, the Law adjudgeth nothing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61518:47"/> to be in him before entry, and he may waive the advantage which hee might take by the breach of the Condition if he will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore notwithſtanding the accruer of the title of the Grantor; yet before this title be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by entry, the Grantee hath ſuch a lawfull intereſt, that what eſtate ſoever hee granteth by Copy, in the interim ſhall ſtand good againſt the Grantor. And ſo if an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant infeoffe me of a Manor, though hee may enter upon me at his pleaſure; yet Grants made by me by Copy before his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſhall never be defeated by any ſubſequent entry.</p>
               <p>And the ſame Law is of Grants made by a Villayne purchaſer of a Manor, before the entry of the Lord, or of Grants made after an alienation in Mortmayne, before the Lord Paramount hath entred for a forfeiture.</p>
               <p>If a Parſon after Inſtitution, and before In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, a Manor being parcell of his Gleab Lands, Grants Lands by Copy, and after is inducted: this admitting of the Copyholders is no binding act, for though, as to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualties, he be a compleate Parſon, preſently upon the inſtitution, yet as to the temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he is not compleat before Induction. So if a Parſon be admitted inſtituted and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61518:48"/> but doth not ſubſcribe to the Articles, according to the Statute of 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and granteth Lands by Copy, as before. This Grant ſhall not conclude the ſucceeding In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent becauſe his Admiſſion, Inſtitution, and Induction were wholly voide in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but had the Parſon beene deprived for crime or hereſie, or for being meere <hi>Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> although he be declared by ſentence, to be uncapable of a Benefice; and ſo his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, voide <hi>(ab initio)</hi> yet becauſe the Church was once full, untill the ſentence declaratory came; for though the deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall relate to ſome purpoſes, yet becauſe the Preſentment, is not in it ſelfe voide, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a relation ſhall never be ſo much favoured, as to avoid a Copyhold eſtate in this kinde.</p>
               <p>So much of Grants made by the Lords themſelves. In Grants made by Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as the Law reſpecteth the quality of the Copyholders eſtate, ſo doth it reſpect both the quality of his perſon, and quantity of his eſtate.</p>
               <p>The quality of perſon, for whoſoever is uncapable of diſpoſing of Land at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, cannot without ſpeciall Cuſtome paſſe away any Copyhold. The quantity of his eſtate, for no Copyholder can poſſibly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61518:48"/> paſſe away more than is in him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if there be joynt Tenants of a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, one cannot aliene the whole. But if there be two joynt Tenants of a Manor, and a Copyholder eſcheateth, one of them may grant this Copyhold, and his Companion ſhall never avoide any part of it.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder for life, the remainder over in Fee to a ſtranger ſurrendreth in Fee, and the Lord admits accordingly, yet an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate for life onely paſſeth.</p>
               <p>So if the Lord of a Manor granteth a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold for life, where an eſtate in Fee, is warrantable, and the ſame Grantee ſurrenders in Fee, to the uſe of a ſtranger; and the Lord admits him, <hi>ſecundum officium ſurſumreddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis;</hi> I thinke no Fee paſſeth: for though the Lords admittance may, <hi>prima facie,</hi> ſeeme to amount to a confirmation of the eſtate ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred; the Reverſion reſting in him to diſpoſe of, according to the Cuſtome; as where a Leſſee for yeares at the Common Law maketh a Feoffment in Fee, and maketh a Letter of Attorney to his Leſſor, to deliver Livery and ſeiſin, who executeth it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, though the Leſſor be uſed as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to performe the will of the Leſſee; yet this being his voluntary act, the Law
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61518:49"/> taketh it as a conſent for the paſſing away of the whole inheritance; but if you looke nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly into both Caſes you ſhall finde the difference in the Latter Caſe, by the Feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Fee is deveſted out of the Leſſor; and therefore a conſent will ſerve to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the Reverſion; but in the former Caſe, the Reverſion is not pluckt out of the Lord, by the Surrender, and therefore an implied conſent is too weake to remove it. I will onely adde one obſervation more, and ſo I will end with the Grantor.</p>
               <p>The Law is not ſo ſtrict to a Copyholder, as that he muſt come perſonally into Court upon the making of every Surrender, but they may Surrender by Attorney, as well as Livery and Seiſin may be made by Attorney at the Common Law; and ſhould the Law be otherwiſe, great inconveniencie would enſue; for how ſhould Copyholders that are in priſon, or languiſhing upon bed, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, ſurrender but by Attorney?</p>
               <p>But note this difference, if a man hath a bare Authority joyned with a Confidence without intereſt, this Authority cannot be executed by Attorney; &amp; therfore if I deviſe, that my Executor ſhall ſell my Land, they
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61518:49"/> cannot ſell by Attorney, for that were to make an Attorney upon Attorney, which the Law will in no wiſe permit; and though a man have an Authority joyned with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, yet if the Authority be warranted by ſpeciall Cuſtome onely, it cannot be executed by an Attorney: and therefore if there be a ſpeciall Cuſtome, that a Copyholder for life may make eſtate, for 20. yeares to continue after his death, theſe eſtates cannot be made by Attorney. So if there be a ſpeciall Cuſtome, that an Infant at the age of diſcretion may ſurrender a Copyhold; this ſurrender being confirmed by ſpeciall Cuſtome onely, cannot be made by Attorney. And ſo if there be a Cuſtome, that a Copyholder out of the Court may ſurrender into the hands of the Lord, by the hands of two Cuſtomary Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, ſuch Surrenders muſt be done in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>But whereſoever there is a generall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, accompanied with an intereſt, that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority may be executed by Attorney, as <hi>Ceſtuy que uſe,</hi> after the Statute of 1. <hi>R.</hi> 3. and before the Statute 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. might have aliened by Attorney; for at that time he had an abſolute authority to diſpoſe of the Land at his pleaſure, without any confidence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in him. And thus much of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:61518:50"/> A word of the Grantee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXV.</head>
               <p>THe ſame perſons that are capable of a Grant by the Common Law, are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a Grant by Copy, according to the Cuſtome of the Manor.</p>
               <p>An Infant, a man of <hi>non ſanae memoriae;</hi> an Idiot, a Lunatique, an Out-law, or an excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, may be Grantees of a Copyhold eſtate.</p>
               <p>The Lord himſelfe may take a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold to his owne uſe, one joynt Tenant may receive a Copyhold from the hands of his joynt companion, becauſe it paſſeth by Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, not by Livery.</p>
               <p>A <hi>feme</hi> covert may be a purchaſer of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold, and this purchaſe ſhall ſtand in force, untill her husband diſagreeth. Nay, further, a <hi>feme</hi> covert may receive a Copyhold eſtate by ſurrender from her husband, becauſe ſhe commeth not in immediately by him, but by mediate meanes, <hi>viz.</hi> by the admittance of the Lord according to the ſurrender.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:61518:50"/>
               <p>As the <hi>ſeme</hi> is capable of receiving a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold from the hands of the Baron; ſo by ſpeciall Cuſtome, the Baron may take a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold from the hands of his <hi>ſeme,</hi> for in ſome Manors, Cuſtome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth enable the <hi>feme</hi> to deviſe a Copyhold to the Baron, but this Cuſtome hath beene much impugned, therefore I dare not juſtifie the validity of it.</p>
               <p>What perſons ſoever are capable of a Grant by Copy, may well take by Attorney, not that the Lord ſhall be enforced to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any one by Attorney, becauſe upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry admittance, there is fealty due by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty admitted, which is a duty ſo inſeparably annexed to the perſons, that it cannot be diſcharged by deputy, and therefore no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Lord ſhould be inforced to admit by Attorney, but if hee will admit him, it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth good.</p>
               <p>It is not neceſſary that upon Surrenders of Copiholds, the name of the partie to whoſe uſe the Surrender is made, be preciſely ſet downe; but if by any manner of circumſtance, the Grantee may be certainely knowne, it is ſufficient. And therefore a Surrender made to the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or the Lord Major of <hi>London,</hi> or the high Sheriffe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:61518:51"/> of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> without mentioning, either their Chriſtian-name, or Sir-name, are good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and certaine enough, becauſe they are certainely knowne by this name, without further addition. So if I Surrender to the uſe of the next of my blood, to the uſe of my wife, to the uſe of my brother or ſiſter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but one brother, or one ſiſter, theſe Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renders are good without any additions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Grantee may certainly be knowne by theſe words.</p>
               <p>If I Surrender generally into the hands of the Lord, not expreſſing to whoſe uſe the Surrender ſhall be, this Surrender is a good Surrender, and ſhall enure to the benefit of the Lord.</p>
               <p>If I ſurrender to the uſe of my ſonne <hi>W.</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more ſonnes than one of that name, yet by an averment, this incertainty may be helped.</p>
               <p>But if I Surrender to the uſe of my coſin, or my friend, this is ſo generall and ſo incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that no ſubſequent manifeſtation of my intention can any way ſtrengthen it.</p>
               <p>So if three Surrender, to the uſe of three or foure of S. <hi>Dunſtons</hi> Pariſh, not naming the Pariſhiones by their names, this Surrender is utterly void.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:61518:51"/>
               <p>And ſo if I Surrender in the disjunction to the uſe of <hi>I. L.</hi> or <hi>I. N.</hi> this is inſufficient for the incertainty.</p>
               <p>And in cuſtomary Grants upon Surrenders the Law is not ſo ſtrict, as in Grants at the common Law, for in Grants at the common Law, if the Grantee be not <hi>in rerum natura</hi> and able to take by vertue of the Grant, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon the Grant made, it is meerely voyd. But in cuſtomarie Grants upon Surrenders the Law is otherwiſe: for though at the time of the Surrender, the Grantee is not in <hi>eſſe,</hi> or not capable of a Surrender, yet if he be in <hi>eſſe</hi> and capable at the time of the Admittance that is ſufficient; and therefore if I Surrender to the uſe of him that ſhall be heyre to <hi>I. S.</hi> or to the uſe of <hi>I. S.</hi> next child, or to the uſe of <hi>I. S.</hi> next wife; though at the time of the Surrender <hi>I. S.</hi> had no heyre, child, or wife: yet if afterwards he hath a childe, or taketh a wife, his heyre, his childe, or his wife may come into the Court and compell the Lord to admit according to the Surrender. So if I Surrender to the uſe of him that ſhall come next into <hi>Pauls</hi> after ſuch an houre, whoſe fortune ſoever it is to come firſt, the Lord muſt admit, and I ſhall never avoyd it.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:61518:52"/>
               <p>The ſame Law is if I ſurrender to the uſe of him that <hi>I. S.</hi> ſhall nominate, or that I my ſelfe ſhall nominate to the Lord at the next meeting; the reaſon of the Law is this, a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render is a thing executory which is executed by the ſubſequent Admittance, and nothing at all is inveſted in the Grantee, before the Lord hath admitted him according to the Surrender, and therefore if at the time of the Admittance the Grantee be in <hi>rerum natura</hi> and able to take, that will ſerve.</p>
               <p>Beſides in Cuſtomarie Grants the intent of the Grantor is more reſpected than it ſhould be by the ſtrict rules of the Law, which appeareth by this, that if a Surrender be made of a Copiehold to the uſe of a laſt Will, and the Surrender deviſeth it unto two, the one is admitted according to the purport of the Will, this ſhall inure to both, but though the Surrender bee a thing executory and the intent of the Grantor ſo much favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: yet if a Copyholder will Surrender to the uſe of the right heires of <hi>I. S.</hi> he being alive, this is voyde becauſe it cannot take effect according to the intent of the Grantor; for he would have the grant to bee executed preſently, which cannot bee in regard that <hi>I. S.</hi> can have no heyre till after his death:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61518:52"/> So much of the Grantee, and I come now to the Grant it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXV.</head>
               <p>A Copyhold intereſt connot be transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by any other, aſſurance then by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of Court Roll, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</p>
               <p>If I will exchange a Copyhold with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I cannot doe it by an ordinary exchange at the Common Law, but we muſt ſurrender to each others uſe, and the Lord admit us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
               <p>If I will deviſe a Copyhold I cannot doe it by will at the Common Law, but I muſt ſurrender to the uſe of my laſt Will and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and in my Will I muſt declare my intent.</p>
               <p>If I am ouſted by a Copyholder, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe made to him is voyde, becauſe it would be a prejudice to the Lord, and beſides there is no Cuſtomary right, upon which the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe may inure, but a releaſe inuring by the way of extinguiſhing where no prejudice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crueth to the Lord, will ſerve to drowne a Copyhold right, and therefore if I ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out of Court upon condition,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4 <hi>fo.</hi> 25.</note> to the uſe of <hi>I. S.</hi> and the preſentment is made abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61518:53"/> in Court, and the admittance framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, this admittance and preſentment differing from the effect of the Surrender are both voyde. Yet becauſe upon the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance the Lord is ſatisfied of his fine and ſo nothing at all prejudiced, and beſides here is a cuſtomary right, upon which the releaſe may be grounded, I may by a releaſe at the Common Law, ſufficiently confirme this voyde eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. And ſo upon the ſame reaſon if I am ouſted of a Copyhold, and the Lord admit him according to the Cuſtome, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe made by me at the Common Law, will extinguiſh my right, but if I make a Leaſe for yeares of a Copyhold, I cannot by my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe paſſe my Reverſion, becauſe this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe injureth by way of inlargement to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre an intereſt, and not by way of extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment, to drowne a right, but my way is to ſurrender my Reverſion into the hands of the Lord, and he to Grant it over to the Leſſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXVII.</head>
               <p>IF Copyhold Land come into that plight that it cannot paſſe by Copie, it is become not alienable; and therefore if the Lord of a Manor will grant to me a Copihold in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61518:53"/> Fee, and after will grant the inheritance of this Copihold to a ſtranger in regard that now my Copihold is become no parcell of the Manor, and ſo I cannot ſurrender into the hands of the Lord and the Grantee of the inheritance, though I am to him a Tenant, and am tyed to doe unto him all manner of ſervices which are due without keeping of Court, as to pay Rent, to diſcharge Herriots and all other Duties, of the ſame nature: yet becauſe the Grantee cannot keepe a Court, and ſo is incapable of taking a Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or making an admittance, therefore I cannot by any meanes alien for no convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at the Common Law will ſerve, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it remaineth ſtill Copihold notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and what Cuſtomes ſoever were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the Land before ſeverance, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill undeſtroyed, as if the land were Burrow Engliſh, or Gavelkind before, it ſo continueth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 24.</note> and a decree in Chancery will not ſerve no more than an ordinary aſſurance at the Common Law; for that bindeth my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon onely, not my intereſt: ſithence therefore Copihold eſtates cannot be conveyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way otherwiſe than by Copie of Court Roll, according to the cuſtome, let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the nature of theſe cuſtomarie grants, wherein three branches are to bee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:61518:54"/>
                  <item>1. The Surrender.</item>
                  <item>2. Preſentment.</item>
                  <item>3. Admittance.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In ſome Grants a Surrender is ſufficient without Preſentment or Admittance.</p>
               <p>In ſome an Admittance without a Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Preſentment.</p>
               <p>In ſome a Surrender and Admittance and both neceſſary; and in ſome, a Surrender, Preſentment, and Admittance are all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>IF a Copiholder will Surrender to the uſe of the Lord the intereſt of the Copihold is ſufficiently veſted in the Lord immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Surrender without any Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Lord, becauſe the Lord cannot admit himſelfe.</p>
               <p>If the Lord will make a voluntary grant of a Copiehold, no Surrender is requiſite, for by the Admittance of the Lord accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome, the Copieholder is
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61518:54"/> ſufficiently ſetled in his Land without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ceremonie.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder will Surrender in Court to the uſe of a ſtranger, beſides the Surrender the Admittance is requiſite, and if the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render he made out of Court into the hands of the Lord himſelfe, which the generall cuſtome will warrant, or into the hands of the Bailiffe or of two Tenants of the Manor, which by ſpeciall cuſtome onely is warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, beſides a Surrender, two other ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are requiſite, the one a true preſentment of the Surrender in Court by the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into whoſe hands the Surrender was made, the other is an Admittance of the Lord according to the effect and tenor both of the Surrender and preſentment.</p>
               <p>But now more particularly of every one of them apart, and firſt of a Surrender.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XXXIX.</head>
               <p>THis word Surrender, is <hi>vocabulum artis,</hi> and therefore where a Surrender is needfull, if this one word be wanting, all other words, uſed in ordinary conveiances, are uneffectuall and inſufficient to convey
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61518:55"/> any Copyhold eſtate, for if a Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der come into Court, and offer to paſſe his Copyhold by word of grant, of gift, of bargaine, or ſale, or ſuch like, I doubt hee will faile of his purpoſe, for as he is tyed to a ſingular forme of aſſurance, ſo is he reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to peculiar words in his aſſurance.</p>
               <p>Surrenders are made in ſeverall ſorts accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeverall cuſtomes of Manors.</p>
               <p>In ſome Manors where a Copyholder ſurrendreth his Copyhold, he uſeth to hold a little rod in his hand, which he delivereth to the Steward or Bayliffe, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Manor, to deliver it over to the party to whoſe uſe the Surrender was made in the name of Seiſin, and from thence they are called Tenants by the Verge.</p>
               <p>In ſome Manors in ſtead of a wand a ſtraw is uſed, and in other Manors a glove is uſed, <hi>Et conſuetudo loci ſemper eſt obſervanda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Surrender (where by a ſubſequent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance the grant is to receive his perfection and confirmation) is rather a manifeſting of the Grantors intention than of paſſing away any intereſt in the poſſeſſion, for till Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61518:55"/> the Lord taketh notice of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor as Tenant, and he ſhall receive the profits of the Land to his owne uſe, and ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge all Services due to the Lord, but yet the intereſt is in him, but <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> and not abſolutely; for he cannot paſſe away the Land to any other, or make it ſubject to any other incumbrance than it was ſubject to, at the time of the ſurrender, neither in the Grantee is any manner of intereſt inveſted before admittance; for if hee enter he is a treſpaſſer, and puniſhable in treſpaſſe; and if he ſurrender to the uſe of another, this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render is meerely void, and by no matter, <hi>ex poſt facto</hi> can be confirmed; for though the firſt ſurrender be executed before the ſecond; ſo that at the time of the admittance of him, to whoſe uſe the ſecond ſurrender was made, his ſurrenderer hath a ſufficient intereſt as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute owner; yet becauſe at the time of the ſurrender, he had but a poſſibility of an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; therefore the ſubſequent admittance, cannot make this act good which was void, <hi>ab initio:</hi> but though the Grantee hath but a poſſibility upon the ſurrender, yet this is ſuch a poſſibility as is accompanied with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, for the Grantee cannot poſſibly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, or defrauded of the effect of his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, and the fruits of his Grantee: for if
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61518:56"/> the Lord refuſe to admit him, he is compela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do it by a <hi>Sub paena</hi> in the Chancery, and the Grantors hands are ever bound from the diſpoſing of the Land, any other way, and his mouth ever ſtopped from revoaking, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termanding his ſurrender. But peradventure, if a Copyholder languiſhing in extremity ſurrendreth out of Court, to the uſe of his Coſin, in conſideration of conſanguinitie, or to the uſe of his ſonne, in conſideration of naturall love and affection, and after, recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his health before preſentment, this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render is revocable, or countermandable: but if it be granted upon valuable conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as for the diſcharge of debts, or for a ſumme of money paid, though it be made out of Court, yet it is as binding as any ſurrender whatſoever made in Court. And thus much for a Surrender; a word of a Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XL.</head>
               <p>THe Preſentment by the generall Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of Manors, is to be made, at the next Court day, immediately after the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, but by ſpeciall Cuſtome; in ſome places, it will ſerve at the ſecond or third Court. And it is to be made by the ſame
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61518:56"/> perſons, that tooke the ſurrender, and in all points materiall, according to the true tenure, of the ſurrender. And therefore if the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render be conditionall, and the Preſentment be abſolute, both the Surrender, Preſentment and Admittance thereupon are wholly void.</p>
               <p>But if the Conditionall ſurrender be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and the Steward in entring of it, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth the Condition; yet upon ſufficient proofe made in Court, the ſurrender ſhall not be avoided, but the Roll amended, and this ſhall be no concluſion to the partie, to plead or give in evidence the truth of the matter.</p>
               <p>If I ſurrender out of Court, and die before Preſentment; if Preſentment be made after my death, according to the Cuſtome,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>39.</hi> b.</note> this is ſufficient; ſo if hee, to whoſe uſe the ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is made dieth before Preſentment, yet upon Preſentment made after his death, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cuſtome, his heire ſhall be admitted: and ſo, if I ſurrender out of Court, to the uſe of one for life, the Rendrour, and the Leſſee for life dieth before Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet upon Preſentment made, he in the remainder ſhall be admitted. And ſo, if I ſurrender to two joyntly, and one dieth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Preſentment, the other ſhall be admitted
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61518:57"/> to the whole. The ſame Law is, if thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe hands the ſurrender is made, dye before Preſentment, upon ſufficient proofe in Court, that ſuch a ſurrender was made, the Lord ſhall be compelled to admit according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and if the Steward, the Bailiffe, or the Tenants, into whoſe hands the ſurrender is made, refuſe to preſent, upon a Petition or a Bill exhibited in the Lords Court; the party grieved ſhall finde remedy. But if the Lord will not doe him right, he may both ſue the Lord, and them that took the ſurrender in the Chancery, and ſhall there finde reliefe. Thus much of Preſentments. A word of Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLI.</head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>ADmittances are threefold;</head>
                     <item>1. An Admittance upon a voluntary Grant.</item>
                     <item>2. An Admittance upon Surrender.</item>
                     <item>3. An Admittance upon a Diſcent.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Involuntary Admittances the Lord is an inſtrument; for though it is in his power to keepe the Land in his owne hands; or to diſpoſe of it at his pleaſure, and to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent may be reputed as abſolute owner, yet becauſe in diſpoſing of it, he is bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61518:57"/> the Cuſtome preciſely in every point, and can neither in Eſtate nor Tenure bring in any alteration, in this reſpect the Law ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts him Cuſtomes inſtrument. If the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome doth warrant an eſtate onely, <hi>Durante viduitate,</hi> and the Lord admits for Life; this ſhall not bind his heire or ſucceſſor, becauſe Cuſtome hath not ſufficiently confirm'd it. So if the Lord faile in reſerving <hi>verum &amp; anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum redditum;</hi> as if he reſerveth ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, where the uſuall rent Cuſtomably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, is twenty ſhillings: this may be a meanes to avoide the admittance, and the Law is very ſtrict in this point of reſervation: for though the ancient accuſtomable rent be reſerved according to the quantity; yet if the quality of the rent be altered, the heire may avoid this Grant: for if the ancient rent from time to time hath been twenty ſhillings in Gold, and the Lord reſerveth it in Silver, this variance of the qualitie of the rent is in force to deſtroy the Grant: ſo if the ancient rent hath beene accuſtomably paid at foure Feaſts in the yeare, and the Lord reſerveth it at two Feaſts. So, if two Copyholds Eſcheate to the Lord, the one of which hath beene uſually demiſed for twentie ſhillings rent, th'other for ten ſhillings rent, and he gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them both by one Copy, for one rent
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61518:58"/> of thirty ſhillings, this is not good; and ſo if a Copyhold of three acres Eſcheates, which hath beene ever granted for three ſhillings rent, and the Lord granteth one Acre, and reſerveth <hi>pro rata,</hi> one ſhilling rent, <hi>verus &amp; antiquus reddit,</hi> is not reſerved: but if a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold of ſixe Acres, which hath ever beene demiſed for ſixe ſhillings rent, Eſcheateth to two Coparteners, and one granteth three Acres, reſerving thre ſhillings <hi>pro rata,</hi> this is a perfect reſerving. In Admittances upon ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, the Lord to no intent is reputed as owner, but wholly as an inſtrument, and the party admitted, ſhall be ſubject to no other charges or incombrances of the Lord, for he claimes his eſtate under the party that made the ſurrender: and in the plaint, in the nature of a Writ of entry in the <hi>per,</hi> it ſhall be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the <hi>per</hi> by him, not by the Lord; and as in admittances upon ſurrenders; ſo in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittances upon deſcents, the Lord is uſed as a meere inſtrument,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>27.</hi> b.</note> and no manner of intereſt paſſeth out of him, and therefore, neither in the one nor in the other, is any reſpect had unto the quality of his eſtate in the Manor; for whether hee hath it by right, or by wrong it is not materiall, theſe admittances ſhall never be called in queſtion for the Lords Title,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>1</hi> fo. <hi>140.</hi> b.</note> becauſe they are judiciall acts, which
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:61518:58"/> every Lord is enjoyned to execute.</p>
               <p>Beſides in admittances upon Surrenders, the Lord being accounted nothing but a neceſſary inſtrument, it followeth that he hath a bare Cuſtomary power to admit, <hi>ſecundum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam &amp; effectum ſurſum reddendi:</hi> therefore if there be any variance betweene the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and the ſurr. either in the perſon, in the eſtate, or in the tenure, or in any other colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall points, the Lord doth onely transferre an eſtate according to the ſurr. and his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity if it can take ſuch effect. As if I Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the uſe of <hi>I.S.</hi> and the Lord admits <hi>I.N.</hi> this admittance is wholly voide; and notwithſtanding this admittance the Lord may afterwards admit <hi>I. S.</hi> according to the effect of his authoritie: but had he admitted <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>I.N.</hi> joyntly, then the admittance had beene void for the one, and good for the other, like the Caſe of a Deviſe: where a Deviſe of a terme is made to <hi>I. S.</hi> and the Executors agree, that <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>I.N.</hi> ſhall have this terme;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4 <hi>fo.</hi> 28</note> this conſent is voide to <hi>I.N.</hi> for after the conſent of the Executors, <hi>I. N.</hi> is in by the Deviſe. Yet ſome are of opinion, that if I ſurr. to the uſe of <hi>I. S.</hi> in Fee, and the Lord admits <hi>I. S.</hi> together with his eldeſt ſonne and heire apparent, that this is an eſtate
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:61518:59"/> by Eſtoppell to <hi>I.S.</hi> and that he ſhall onely claime joyntly with his ſonne, becauſe hee might have refuſed an admittance in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; but I can hardly be brought, to thinke that this admittance, giving a preſent intereſt in theſon, who by ſurrender was to have no intereſt till the death of his father, ſhould be any ſuch eſtopell.</p>
               <p>If I ſurr. to the uſe of <hi>I.S.</hi> for life, and the Lord admits him in Fee, an eſtate for life onely paſſeth.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 29.</note> So if I ſurr. without mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any certaine eſtate, becauſe by implica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law, eſtate for life onely paſſeth, though the Lord admit in Fee, no more doth paſſe, than the implication of Law will war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. If I ſurr. with the reſervation of a rent, and the Lord admits not, reſerving any rent, or reſerving a leſſe rent than I reſerved upon the Surrender, this admittance is wholly void: but if the Lord reſerveth a greater rent, then is the reſervation void, only for the ſurpluſage, and the admittance, ſo far currant as it agreeth with my ſurrender. If I ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon Condition, and the Lord omits the Condition, the admittance is wholly void; but if my ſurrender be abſolute,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 25.</note> and the Lords admittance be conditionall, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is void, but the admittance in all points elſe is good.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:61518:59"/>
               <p>The reaſons of theſe diverſities are theſe, where an Authority is given to any one to execute any act, and he executeth it contrary to the effect of his authority, this is utterly voyd, but if hee executeth his authority and withall goeth beyond the limits of his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, this is voyd for that part onely, wherein he exceedeth his authority. Theſe admittan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon Surrender, differ from admittances upon Diſcents in this, that in admittances upon ſurrender, nothing is veſted in the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee before admittance, no more then in the Voluntary admittances; but in admittances upon Diſcents, the heire is Tenant by Copy immediately upon the death of his Anceſtor, not to all intents and purpoſes; for peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he cannot be ſworne of the homage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, neither can hee maintaine a plaint in the nature of an Aſſize in the Lords Court before, becauſe till then he is not compleate Tenant to the Lord, no further forth then the Lord pleaſeth to allow him for his Tenant. And therefore, if there bee Grandfather, Father, and Sonne; and the Grandfather is admitted, and dyeth, and the Father entreth, and dyeth before admittance, the Sonne ſhall have a plaint in the nature of a writ of Ayell, and not an Aſſize of <hi>Mort d'aunceſtor,</hi> ſo that to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes, the Heire, till admittance
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61518:60"/> is not compleat Tenant, yet to moſt intents, eſpecially as to ſtrangers, the Law taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 23.</note> as of a perfect Tenant of the Land, inſtantly upon the death of his Aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, for he may enter into the Land; before admittance, take the profits, puniſh any treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe done upon the ground, Surrender into the hands of the Lord, to whoſe uſe he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſatisfying the Lord his fine, due upon the Diſcent, and by eſtoppell, hee may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice himſelfe of his inheritance, for if an Eſtrange come and ſurrender to the uſe of him and his Wife, before admittance, hee ſhall ever claime joyntly with his Wife, and never be taken as ſole Tenant, and the Lord may avow upon him before admittance, for any arrearages of Rent, or other Services, and laſt of all,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>22.</hi> b.</note> upon an actuall poſſeſſion, there ſhall be <hi>poſſeſsio fratris,</hi> before admittance, for if a Copyholder in Fee, have iſſue a Sonne, and a Daughter by one Venter, and a Sonne by another venter, and dyeth ſeiſed, and his Sonne by the firſt Venter, entereth into the Land, and dyeth before admittance, the Daughter ſhall inherit, as Heire to her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and not the Sonne by the ſecond Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as Heire to his Father: and many times the poſſeſſion of a Guardian, or a Tearmer, without an actuall entry, or any claime made
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61518:60"/> by the Heire, will make a <hi>poſſeſsio fratris.</hi> As if a Copyholder in Fee, having iſſue a Sonne or a Daughter, by one venter, and a Sonne by another Venter; by Licence of the Lord, maketh a Leaſe for yeares, and dyeth, and the Sonne of the firſt Venter dyeth, before the expiration of the Terme, being neither ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, nor having made any actuall entry, or any claime. Yet this poſſeſſion of the Leſſee is ſufficient, and the Reverſion ſhall diſcend to the daughter of the firſt Venter, and not to the ſonne of the ſecond Venter. But if the Leaſe had beene determined living, the Son by the firſt Venter, and afterwards he had dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before any actuall entry made, the Law would have fallen out otherwiſe, becauſe there was a time, when he might have lawfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; therefore, where ſome have imagined that nothing ſhould be inveſted in the Heire before admittance; becauſe every admittance of an Heire, upon a Diſcent, amounteth to a Grant, and ſo may be pleaded, they are in an errour, for though it be true, that after ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance, the Heire may in pleading, alledge this as a Grant, and that hath beene allowed, to avoid the inconveniencies that otherwiſe ſhould enſue; For if the Copyholder ſhould be driven in pleading, to ſhew the firſt Grant,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>22.</hi> b.</note> either that being made before the memory of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61518:61"/> man, is not pleadable, or ſince the memory of man, and then Cuſtome failes, for this reaſon the Law hath allowed a Copyholder, in pleading to alledge any admittance aſwell upon a Diſcent, as upon a Surrender, as a Grant: and yet he may if he will, alledge the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his Anceſtors as a Grant, and ſhew the Diſcent to him, and that he entred; and well without any admittance; but the Heire cannot plead that his Anceſtor was ſeiſed in Fee, at the will of the Lord, by Copy of Court Roll, of ſuch a Manor, according to the Cuſtome of the Manor, and that he dyed ſeiſed, and that the Copyhold diſcended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, becauſe in truth ſuch an intereſt is but a particular intereſt at will, in judgement of Law, although it bee diſcendable by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</p>
               <p>So that I conclude, that an admittance is principally for the benefit of the Lord, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title him to his Fyne, and not much neceſſary for ſtrengthning of the Heires title.</p>
               <p>Then will ſome ſay, if the benefit which the Heire ſhall receive by the admittance, will not countervaile the charges of the Fyne, he will never come in, and take up his Copyhold in Court, and ſo defeat the Lord of his Fyne:
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61518:61"/> I aſſure my ſelfe, if it were in the election of the Heire to be admitted, or not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he would be beſt contented without admittance, but the Cuſtome in every Manor is compulſary in this point, for either upon paine of forfeiture of their Copihold or of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring ſome great penalty, the Heires of Copyholders are inforced in every Manor to come into Court, and be admitted according to the Cuſtome within a ſhort time after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice given of their Anceſtors deceaſe. And thus much of the Grant it ſelfe. A word of the things granted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLII.</head>
               <p>THings that lye not in Tenure, are not Grantable by Copy. As Rents, Baili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickes, Stewardſhips, Common in groſſe, Advowſions in groſſe, and ſuch like. All which are incorporate Hereditaments, and therefore no Rent can iſſue out of them; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they be held by any manner of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but an Advowſion appendant, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon appendant, or a Faire appendant may paſſe by Copy, by reaſon of the principall thing, to which they are appendant, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally what things ſoever are parcell of the Manor, and are of perpetuity, may be granted
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:61518:62"/> by Copy, according to the Cuſtome, as Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwoods growing upon the Manor, being things of continuance, (for after they are cut they will grow againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4 <hi>fo.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>ex ſtipitibus</hi>) may well be granted by Copy; and ſo of herbage or any other profit of the Manor; and ſometime of the grant of a Copyhold, things ſhall paſſe that are ſevered from the Manor. As if the Lord of a Manor grant his Manor for yeares, <hi>except. boſc. &amp; ſaboſc.</hi> growing in certaine Copyhold ground, and the Leſſee by his Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward granteth a Copyhold within which Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor there is a Cuſtome that every Copyholder may take within his Copyhold Woods, and Vnderwoods, growing upon the ground for his neceſſary fuel, notwithſtanding this excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Leaſe of the Manor, the Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may cut downe Woods or Vnderwoods according to the Cuſtome, though by excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſevered from the Manor, for though the Leſſee of the Manor, in reſpect of the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could not meddle with the Woods or Vnderwoods, and ſo it might ſeeme, <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ima facie,</hi> very probable that the Copyholder, comming in by the voluntary admittance of the Leſſee, ſhould have no more Authority nor intereſt then the Leſſee himſelfe had; yet becauſe the Copyholder being once in by Cuſtome, and ſo his title being grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61518:62"/> Cuſtome is paramount the exception; Therefore, the exception in the Leaſe of the Manor, though preceeding the Grant of the Copyhold, cannot any way touch or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the Copyholder. And ſo, if there be a Cuſtome, within a Manor that Copyholders have uſed to have Common in the Waſtes of the Lord, and the Lord granteth away his Waſtes, and after granteth a Copyhold, the Copyholder ſhall have Common, but in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the Cuſtome, he ſhall not ſay, <hi>Quod infra Maner. praed. talis habetur conſuetudo.</hi> but that till ſuch a time, <hi>viz.</hi> before the ſeverance, <hi>talis habebatur &amp; toto tempore, &amp;c. conſuetudo,</hi> and then ſhew the ſeverance. If there be an incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in the things granted, the Grant is not therefore inſufficient; for by the election of him that is the firſt Agent, it may be made certaine.</p>
               <p>As if I grant by Copy, twenty loads of Haſell, or twenty loads of Maple in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive to bee cut downe,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>31.</hi> a Co. <hi>2</hi> fo. <hi>37.</hi> a</note> and taken by the Grantee in my Manor of Dale, there the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee hath election to make choyce of which he pleaſeth, becauſe he is to performe the firſt Act of cutting downe, and taking them, but if I am to cut them downe, and deliver them to the Grantee, then have I the election, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61518:63"/> obſerve this difference touching this point of election.</p>
               <p>If a Grant be made in the diſ-junctive of two annuall things, and things of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; if the election belong to the Grantor, and he faileth at the day to make election, yet his election is not determined, but continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame after the day, that it was before the day, but otherwiſe it is, where things are not annuall, but are to be performed <hi>unica vice tantum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore if the Lord of a Manor granteth by Copy, twenty trees growing upon Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acre, or Whiteacre, to be cut downe yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by himſelfe, and to be delivered to the Grantee at ſuch a day, though the Grantor faile at his day to make his election, yet his election is not gone, becauſe the things gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are annuall, but had theſe trees beene to be delivered to the Grantee once onely, and not yearely, then by the failor of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor at the day, the election is devolved to the Grantee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:61518:63"/>
               <head>SEC. XLIII.</head>
               <p>ANd thus much of the thing granted, a word of the Inſtruments, through whoſe hands, as through Conduit-pipes, the Lands are <hi>gradatim,</hi> conveyed to the purchaſor; I will not ſpeake of thoſe men, that are uſed as Inſtruments by ſpeciall Cuſtome to preſent in Court ſurrenders taken out of Court. Theſe I have ſufficiently ſpoken of already. I will here point onely at theſe perſons; that by the generall Cuſtome of every Manor, are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as neceſſary Inſtruments in Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary admittances, and will curſarily examine the extents of their authorities, and the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of their offices.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>The perſons I ayme at are theſe;</head>
                     <item>1. The Lord.</item>
                     <item>2. The Steward.</item>
                     <item>3. The Vnder-Steward.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLIV.</head>
               <p>THe Lords Authority conſiſteth chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe foure things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In puniſhing offences, and miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors committed within his precincts, as not
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61518:64"/> performance of Cuſtomes, breach of By-lawes, not diſcharging of du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In deciding controverſies ariſing about the Title of Copyhold-Land, lying within his bounds; and when he ſitteth as Judge in Court, to end debates of this nature, he is not tied to the ſtrict forme of the Common Law, for he is a Chancellor in his Court, and may redreſſe matters in Conſcience upon Bill exhibited, where the Common Law will afford no remedy in the ſame kinde, as to inſiſt in one familiar example.</p>
               <p>If I ſurrender a Copyhold to the uſe of a ſtranger, upon confidence, that ſuch debts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by me diſcharged, he ſhall ſurrender backe this Copyhold; I upon diſcharge of the debts demand a ſurrender, and he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, at the Common Law I were left reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe, this being a bare confidence, and no Condition, but upon Bill exhibited in the Lords Court I ſhall be relieved, for the Lord upon proofe of the matter may ſeize the Copyhold, and readmit me, according to the effect of the Confidence.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In admitting Copyhold. And in this
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61518:64"/> Cuſtomary power of admittance, the Lord doth ſomewhat outſtrippe the Steward, for the Lord may make either admittances upon voluntary Grants,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4 <hi>fo.</hi> 27.</note> admittances upon ſurrren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, admittances upon diſcents, in any place where he pleaſeth out of the Manor, but ſo cannot the Steward: and in giving Licence to Copyholders to aliene by deede, and in this point of Licence, the Lords au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority doth exceede the Stewards authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; for though ſome are of opinion, that it is both uſuall and warrantable, for the Steward of a Manor in abſence of his Lord, to Licence a Copyholder in full Court to aliene by Deede, for as many yeares as he ſhall thinke good, becauſe he is Judge in the Court, and beſides the entry of it in the Court Roll is in this manner. <hi>Ad hanc curiam. P.S. petit Licentiam Domini dimittendi, &amp;c. Cui Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus licentiam dat, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence being granted in the Lords name in full Court, the Lord ſhall never enter for a forfeiture, but ſhall ever be eſtopped, to ſay the contrary, but that he did give licence, yet (under reformation be it ſpoken) I muſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt the truth of this opinion; for this power of Licenſing Copiholds to alien by Deede, is not Cuſtomary, for then it were as proper to the Steward, as to the Lord; but it is a power
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:61518:65"/> of intereſt annexed to the perſon of the Lord, in reſpect of his eſtate in the Manor, and not in any other Collaterall reſpect; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Steward having a bare authority to execute what the Cuſtome of the Manor doth warrant, ſans doubt, hee cannot, <hi>virtute officii,</hi> grant any unwarrantable Licence to aliene by deede, no more than to commit waſte: for the one act, as well as the other, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the breach of Cuſtome, and both of them without a ſufficient allowance, amounts to the forfeiture of a Copyhold, but by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words in the Stewards Patent, or by ſpeciall authority given him by the Lord, or by ſome particular Cuſtome warranting the ſame, the Steward may in Court lawfully Licence Copyholders, to aliene as well as the Lord may. And thus much of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLV.</head>
               <p>STeward, is derived from thoſe two words, Stede, and Ward; and ſo any that doth ſupply anothers place, or that is in any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment deputy to another, may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true ſenſe of the word be termed a Steward; as the high Steward of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe the King appointeth him in divers matters to exerciſe his place: and ſo the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61518:65"/> Sheriffe may be termed by the name of the Sheriffes Steward, being his Deputy, and how properly the Lords Steward is ſo named, any man may judge by this, that the whole authority of the Steward is derived from the Lord, as from the Head; and not only ſo, but withall he repreſenteth the Lords perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in many imployments; for in the Lords abſence, he ſitteth as judge in Court to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh offences, determine controverſies, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe injuries, and the like; and further, ſome things he performeth in the Lords name, and not in his owne name, for if the Steward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth any Copyholder, or by ſpeciall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or particular Cuſtome, licenceth a Copyholder to aliene, this admittance and licence ſhall be made in the Lords name, and the entry in the Court Roll, ſhall be, <hi>Quod Dominus per Seneſcallu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admiſit, &amp; licentiav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> and not that the Steward did admit, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; therefore fithence the Steward hath this meaſure of authoritie and confidence committed unto him, the Lord ſhall doe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well to be very carefull in making choiſe of his Steward; for if he be defective in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of theſe three qualities, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Truſt, or Diligence, the Lord may be much prejudiced and damnified; therefore <hi>Fleta</hi> wiſely giveth the Lord this counſell.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:61518:66"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fleta l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Provideat ſibi Dominus de Seneſcallo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecto &amp; fideli &amp; pacifico &amp; modesto, qui in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus conſuetudinibuſque provinciae Domini ſui in omnibus tueri affectet, quiſque Ballivos Domini in ſui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> erroribus &amp; ambiguis ſciat inſtruere &amp; docere, quique egenis parcere, &amp; nec prece vel pretio velit à tramite juſtitiae devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are &amp; pervenſe judicare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Stewards for the moſt part, have Patents for their Offices, yet they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by paroll, &amp; this reteiner by paroll, is as effectuall in all points before diſcharge, as the moſt effectuall inſtitution by Patent: for a Steward thus retained, may take ſurrender out of Court, or make voluntary admittances, or any other Act incident to the office of a Steward,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>30.</hi> b.</note> as well as a Steward inſtituted by Patent. But in the Kings Manors, a Steward cannot be retained by paroll by the mouth of the Auditor or Receiver; but to make the Stewards authoritie currant,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>30.</hi> a.</note> eſpecially to make voluntary admittances; it is neceſſary he have a Patent, and then, by vertue of his Patent, without any ſpeciall Authority, or particular Cuſtome, he may juſtifie the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of any voluntary admittance, upon Eſcheates or forfeitures, or the doing of any Act belonging to his Office; but though hee
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:61518:66"/> may <hi>Ex officio,</hi> doe thoſe things without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall warrant, yet dutie bindes him before he make any voluntary admittance to informe the Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and Barons of the Exchequer, or any of them for his better direction, and the Kings better benefit, the Law is not very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in examining the imperfections of the Stewards perſon; nor the unlawfulneſſe of his authoritie, for be he an Infant, or <hi>non comps mentis,</hi> an Idiot, or Lunatique, an Out-law, or an Excommunicate; yet what things ſoever hee performeth, as incident to his place, can never be avoided for any ſuch diſabilitie, becauſe he performeth them as a Judge, or at leaſt as Cuſtomes Inſtrument: and for his authority, though it prove but counterfeit, if it come to exact triall; yet if in appearance or outward ſhew, it ſeemeth currant, that is, ſufficient. As if I grant the Stewardſhip of my Manor of Dale by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and in the Patentees abſence, a ſtranger by my appointment keepeth Court, this is au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall. If a Grant of a Stewardſhip be made to one, and for ſome fault or defect in the Grant, it is avoidable, yet Courts kept by him before the avoidance, ſhall ſtand in force: and whatſoever hee did as Steward, are ever unavoidable. As if a Corporation,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:61518:67"/> retaineth a Steward by paroll, and he keepeth a Court, puniſheth offences, decideth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, taketh ſurrenders, maketh admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, either upon ſurrenders or diſcents: theſe Acts being judiciall ſhall ever ſtand for currant, though his authority be grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a wrong foundation, for a Corporation cannot inſtitute any ſuch officer without writing. And ſo if the Kings Auditor or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, retaine a Steward by paroll, he may lawfully execute any judiciall Act, but things which he performeth, as Cuſtomes inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not as Judge, ſuch as are voluntary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittances, neither in the retainer by the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, or in this retainer by the Kings Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, ſhall any whit binde, but if a ſtanger without the appointment of the Lord, or conſent of the right Steward, or without any colour of authoritie, will of his owne head, come into a Manor, and keepe a Court; it ſeemeth that the performance of any judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all duty, or the executing of any act whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will not be warranted, eſpecially if the Court be kept without warning given to the Bayliffe by precept, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Office of a Steward may be forfeite three manner of wayes.</head>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:61518:67"/>
                  <item>1. By Abuſer.</item>
                  <item>2. By non uſer.</item>
                  <item>3. By Refuſer.</item>
               </list>
               <p>By abuſer, As if the Steward burne the Court Rolles, or if he taketh a bribe to winke at any offence, or uſe partiality, in any cauſe depending before him, theſe and the like abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will make him ſubject to a forfeiture.</p>
               <p>By non uſer, as if the Steward by his Patent being tyed to keepe Court at certaine times of the yeare, without requeſt to be made by the Lord if he faileth, and by his failer the Lord receive any prejudice, this is a forfeiture. But if the Lord be not damnified, then this non uſer is no forfeiture. As if a Parker attends not for the ſpace of three or foure dayes, and no prejudice or damage hapneth in the interim, this is no forfeiture: and in Offices, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the adminiſtration of Juſtice, or the Commonwealth the Law is more ſtrict then in theſe Offices which concerne private men: for where an officer <hi>ex officio,</hi> or of neceſſity ought to attend for the adminiſtration of Juſtice, or for the good of the Commonwealth, there non uſer, or non attender in Court is a forfeiture, though this be prejudiciall to no man, as the office of the Chamberlaine in the Exchequer, a Protonotary Clarke of the Warrants <hi>Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentur Filizar,</hi> or the like in the Common Pleas, becauſe the attendance of theſe and the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:61518:68"/> like officers, is of neceſſity for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice, ſo the attendance of the Clarke of the Market, is of neceſſity for the good of the Commonwealth, and ſo is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Sheriffes turne, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By refuſer the office of a Steward may be thus forfeited, if the Steward be tyed by his Patent to keepe Court upon a demand or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, to be made by the Lord, if the Lord demandeth or requeſteth him to keepe a Court, and he faileth; this is a forfeiture, though the Lord be thereby nothing damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, and thus much of the Steward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLVI.</head>
               <p>THe under ſteward is the Stewards depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſometimes appointed by writing, ſometimes by paroll, and the extent of his Authority, is as great as the Stewards owne Authority, and his office conſiſteth in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the ſelfe ſame duties, that the high Steward himſelfe is to performe, onely in this point the power of the Steward goeth beyond the power of the underſteward, that the Steward can make an admittance out of Court, and it ſhall ſtand good if entry be made in the Court Roll, that he that is admitted, hath paid his fine and hath done fealty, but the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:61518:68"/> underſteward though he may take a ſurrender out of the Court, yet he cannot make any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance out of Court, without eſpeciall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or particular Cuſtome.</p>
               <p>Some have thought, that an underſteward may be made without ſpeciall words in the Stewards Patent, authorizing him to make a Deputy, but ſurely ſince it is an office of knowledge, truſt, and diſcretion it cannot, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be in caſes of neceſſity. As if an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Stewardſhip deſcend unto an Infant, he may make a Deputy, becauſe the Law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth he is himſelfe uncapable to execute it, ſo if it be granted to an Earle in reſpect of th'exility of the Office in a baſe Court, and of the dignity of the perſon, who is <hi>Praepoſitus Comitatus,</hi> and had in ancient time the charge and cuſtody of the whole ſhire, whoſe atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance the Law intendeth to be moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, upon the King and the Commonwealth, therefore it is implyed in Law for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency, that hee may make a Deputy, for whom he ought to anſwer. This is one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation touching underſtewards, in admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances made by underſtewards, aſwell as in admittances made by the Stewards themſelves it is good order to expreſſe in the Copy, and in the Court Roll, the name of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteward,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:61518:69"/> or of the Steward, becauſe in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any admittance a man muſt ſay that hee was admitted by ſuch a one underſteward or Steward, naming his name. And this ſhall ſuffice touching the manner and meanes of granting Copiholds: Suffer mee now in the fourth place to point at the ſeverall eſtates of Copiholders, together with their ſeverall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities incident to their ſeverall eſtates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLVII.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>ALl eſtates whatſoever may be reduced to one of theſe three heads.</head>
                  <item>1. Inheritance.</item>
                  <item>2. Francktenant.</item>
                  <item>3. Chattells.</item>
               </list>
               <p>All Inheritances are of two ſorts, either Fee ſimples, or Fee tailes.</p>
               <p>Of Fee ſimples, ſome are determinable, ſome are undeterminable.</p>
               <p>Determinable, as where Land is given to a man and his heires, for ſo long time as <hi>Pauls</hi> ſteeple ſhall ſtand.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:61518:69"/>
               <p>Vndeterminable, as where Land is given to a man and his heires, without further limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Of Fee tailes, ſome are generall, ſome are ſpeciall.</p>
               <p>Generall, as where Land is given to a man and the heires of his body, or heires males, or females of his body.</p>
               <p>Speciall, as where Land is given to a man, and the heires, males or females, which he ſhall beget of ſuch a woman.</p>
               <p>All Francketenants are of two ſorts, either created by the act of the party, or by the Act of the Law.</p>
               <p>Of Francketenants created by the act of the party, ſome are determinable by death, ſome by collaterall meanes.</p>
               <p>By death, as eſtates granted during the life of the Grantor, of the Grantee, or of a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>By collaterall meanes, as eſtates granted <hi>quia diu fuerit innupta,</hi> to a Widdow <hi>qùia diu
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:61518:70"/> remanſerit vidua,</hi> or to a Miniſter, <hi>quamdiu Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotium exercuerit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of Francke tenants created by the act of the Law, ſome are Francketenants <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> ſome <hi>ſecundum quid ſimpliciter,</hi> as the eſtates of a tenant in Dower, of a tenant by the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie of an occupant, a tenant in taile, after poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of iſſue extinct, <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> as the eſtates of a tenant by Statute, Merchant, <hi>Stat. Staple &amp; Elegit.</hi> who though they are to have the Land, but for ſo many yeares as will give a plenary ſatisfaction to their debts, yet by the <hi>Stat.</hi> of <hi>Weſtmin.</hi> 2. they may mainetaine an Aſſize, which no other tenant having but a Chattell can have.</p>
               <p>All Chattells are either certaine, or incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, of Chattells certaine, ſome are in themſelves certaine, ſome are made certaine by relation to a certainty. Certaine in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as where Lands are granted for 20. 30. or 40. yeares. Certaine by relation to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety, as where Land is granted for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares as <hi>I. S.</hi> hath acres of Land.</p>
               <p>Of incertaine Chattells, ſome are incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in their commencement, ſome incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in their determination.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:61518:70"/>
               <p>In their commencement, as where a Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian hath an eſtate during the minority of the heire, all theſe eſtates either by the generall or by the particular Cuſtomes of Manors, are of Copyholds aſwell as of Freeholds, in what manner ſoever an eſtate in Fee ſimple is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the Cuſtome,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 23.</note> moſt inferior eſtates are by implication likewiſe warranted. All Francke tenants created by the act of the party, the eſtate of an occupant, and all Chattells whatſoever, without any other particular Cuſtome, are hereby warranted.</p>
               <p>But the Law is otherwiſe,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>22.</hi> a.</note> of eſtates in Dower by the courteſie, by Statute Merchant, Statute Staple, or Elegit, for as long as ſuch a Copyhold, by the Cuſtome of the Manor grantable in Fee ſimple, continueth in the Copyholders hands, it is not lyable to any of theſe eſtates, but if once it commeth to the Lord by Eſcheate forfeiture, or by other meanes, ſo long as it remaineth reunited to the Manor, it is in the nature of a Freehold, and ſhall be ſubject to the charges and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances, as Land at the Common Law, and howſoever by implication theſe eſtates are not allowed in Copyholds, continuing in the Copyhold poſſeſſion, yet by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:61518:71"/> Cuſtome the Wife may bee Tenant in Dower, the Husband Tenant by the Curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, a ſtranger Tenant by Stat. Merchant, Stat. Staple, or Elegit, of a Copyhold, reſting in the Copyhold, aſwell as if it reſted in the Lord, whether an eſtate tayle, or an eſtate Tayle, after poſſibility of iſſue extinct, which hath a neceſſary depending upon an eſtate Taile may by any particular Cuſtome bee allowed, that I may diſpute, but cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; for it is <hi>vexata quaeſtio,</hi> much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted; but nothing concluded, I will briefely touch the reaſons alledged on both ſides. They which are againſt the validity of Intailes by ſpeciall Cuſtome, doe chiefely urge theſe two reaſons, that no eſtates tayles were before the <hi>Stat. de donis conditionalibus,</hi> but all Inheritances were Fees conditionall, and the Statute being made 13. <hi>E.</hi> 1. which is within the memory of man, it cannot be that any ſpeciall Cuſtomes have any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement, ſince the Statute, for then a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome might begin within time of memory, which is altogether repugnant to the rules of Cuſtome.</p>
               <p>Two great inconveniencies would enſue, if a Copyholder might be Intailed by ſpeciall Cuſtome, becauſe neither fine nor Common
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:61518:71"/> recovery can barre it; ſo that he hath ſuch an eſtate, that he cannot of himſelfe, without the aſſent of the Lord, diſpoſe of it, either for the payment of his debts, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his wife, or preferment of his yonger ſonnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLVIII.</head>
               <p>THe maine reaſons inſiſted upon in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of intailing Copyholds are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In divers Manors they have beene from time to time, not onely reputed as Tenants in tayle, but in every mans mouth termed by that name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Formed on in the Deſcender lyeth of a Copyholder, which Writ none can bring but Tenant in tayle.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A remainder limitted upon ſuch an eſtate in ſuch Manors hath beene allowed, and therefore is no Fee conditionall; for upon a Fee, whether abſolute or conditionall, a Render can by no meanes depend.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a common uſage there by a Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to docke intayles of Copyhold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:61518:72"/> defeate theſe eſtates by preſentment, that the Copyholder hath committed a forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo the Lord to ſeize, and then to ſurrender it to the purchaſer; and therefore there is not that inconvenience which is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Copyhold, <hi>ſcilicet,</hi> want of power to diſpoſe of ſuch an eſtate without the Lords conſent.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Much inconvenience would depend upon this if Copyholds might not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed, for it would tend to the ſubverſion and deſtruction of many mens eſtates, which from time to time they have enjoyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction, and therefore for the quiet of the Common-wealth how neceſſary it is, that Copyholds ſhould be intayled, let any man judge.</p>
               <p>Thus much of the ſeverall eſtates of the Copyhold. A word of their ſeverall quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties incident to ſeverall eſtates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
               <head>SEC. XLIX.</head>
               <p>WHat qualities ſoever are neceſſarily incident to eſtates at the Common Law, are incident to eſtates by Cuſtome. In illuſtrating this I will confine my ſelfe to the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:61518:72"/> diſcuſſing of theſe two points.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What words will create Copyholds of inheritance, and what Copyholds of Franck-Tenant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How Copyholds of inheritance ſhall deſcend.</p>
               <p>Touching their creation, Copyholds of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and Copyholds of Franck-Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are created by the ſame words that Inheritance and Franck-Tenement at the Common Law are created by.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be granted to a man, and to his heires males, or heires females.</p>
               <p>If to a man <hi>&amp; ſanguini ſuo hereditabili.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If to a Deane and Chapter, or to a Major &amp; Commonalty, without any expreſſe eſtate, or without a limitation of ſome inferior e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. In all theſe Grants, a perfect eſtate in Fee paſſeth.</p>
               <p>And ſo peradventure if I ſurrender a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold to a man and his heires, and he reciting this eſtate, re-ſurrendreth in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to me, that I ſurrendred to him, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any mention of my heire, yet this reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſeemeth ſufficient to paſſe a good Fee-ſimple.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:61518:73"/>
               <p>So, if I ſurrender unto you as large an eſtate, as I.<hi>S.</hi> hath in his Manor of <hi>D.</hi> and he hath a Fee-ſimple in his Manor, it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what probable, that an eſtate in Fee ſimple ſhould paſſe, by reaſon of his relation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word heires.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be ſurrendred to a man, <hi>&amp; ſemini ſuo haereditabili de corpore,</hi> or to a man, <hi>&amp; haeredibus ex ipſo precreatis,</hi> or to a man in Franck-marriage with his wife, in theſe Grants an eſtate tayle paſſeth in the firſt, without the word heires, in the ſecond, without the word body; in the third without either.</p>
               <p>If the King by his Steward granteth a Copyhold to a man, and to his heires males, or heires females, no Fee-ſimple paſſeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord never intended to paſſe ſuch an eſtate.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be Granted to an Abbot, and to his heires, an eſtate for life onely paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
               <p>So if I Grant a Copyhold to a man in Fee-ſimple, <hi>ac ſanguini ſuo imperpetum,</hi> or <hi>ſibi &amp; aſsign. ſuis impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pectum;</hi> yet the word heires wanting no greater eſtate than for life paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:61518:73"/>
               <p>The ſame Law is, if a Copyhold be granted to a man, and to his heires, as long as <hi>I. S.</hi> ſhall live, this is onely an eſtate, <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vie, &amp; a rend.</hi> limitted upon this eſtate, is good.</p>
               <p>But if a Copyhold be granted to a man, and to his heires, as long as ſuch a tree ſhall grow in ſuch a ground, this is a good Fee, and a render limitted upon it is void.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be granted to <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>I. N. &amp; haeredibus,</hi> they are joynt Tenants for life; and no inheritance paſſeth unto either, becauſe of the uncertainty for want of this word <hi>(ſuis)</hi> but if a Copyhold be granted to <hi>I. S.</hi> onely <hi>&amp; haerend.</hi> a good Fee-ſimple paſſeth without the word <hi>ſuis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be granted to a man, <hi>&amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red bus,</hi> an eſtate tayle doth not paſſe, for want of the words <hi>de corpore.</hi> And if a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold be granted to a man, <hi>&amp; liberis aut puer. ſuis de corpore;</hi> an eſtate taile doth not paſſe for want of this word (heires) for what eſtates ſoever are intayles ſince the Statute <hi>De donis Conditionalibus</hi> were Fee-ſimples Conditionall; but this could be no Fee-ſimple conditionall before the Statute with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word (heires) and therefore no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:61518:74"/> ſince the Statute. And for the ſame reaſon, if a Copyhold be granted to a man, and to the iſſues males of his bodie an eſtate for life onely paſſeth.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be granted to a man, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expreſſing any certaine eſtate by impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Law, an eſtate for life onely paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; and if I grant a Copyhold to three <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum ſucceſsive,</hi> they are joynt Tenants, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe by ſpeciall Cuſtome the word <hi>ſucceſsive</hi> make their eſtates ſeverall. Thus much touching the creation of Copyhold eſtates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
               <head>SEC. L.</head>
               <p>THe diſcents of Copyhold of inheritance are guided and directed by the rules of the Common Law, as well as the creation of Copyhold eſtates.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder in Fee-ſimple having iſſue, a ſonne and a daugher by one <hi>venter,</hi> and a ſonne by an other <hi>venter,</hi> dieth, and the ſonne by the firſt <hi>venter</hi> entreth and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; the Land ſhall diſcend to the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Quia-poſſeſsio fratris de feodo ſimplici facit ſororem eſſe haeredem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if a Copyholder in tayle, have iſſue, a
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:61518:74"/> ſon and a daughter by one <hi>venter,</hi> and a ſon by another, <hi>venter</hi> dieth, and the ſonne by the firſt <hi>venter</hi> entreth and dieth, the ſonne of the ſecond <hi>venter</hi> ſhall inherit.</p>
               <p>If a man having iſſue, a ſonne and a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by one <hi>venter,</hi> and a ſonne by another <hi>venter,</hi> the eldeſt ſonne purchaſeth a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in Fee, and dieth without iſſue, the daughter ſhall have the Land, not the yonger ſonne, becauſe he is but of the halfe blood to the other.</p>
               <p>If a man hath a Copyhold, by diſcent from his mothers ſide, if he die without iſſue, the Land ſhall goe to the heires of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide, and ſhall rather eſcheate, than goe to the heires of the fathers ſide; but if I purchaſe a Copyhold, and die without iſſue, the Land ſhall goe to the heires of my Fathers ſide: but if I have no heires of my fathers ſide, it ſhall goe to the heires of my mothers ſide rather than eſcheate.</p>
               <p>If there be Father, Vnckle and Sonne, and the ſonne purchaſeth a Copyhold in Fee, and dieth without iſſue, the Vncle ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit and not the Father, becauſe an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may lineally diſcend, but not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:61518:75"/>
               <p>If there be three brothers, and the middle brother purchaſeth a Copyhold in Fee, and dieth without iſſue, the eldeſt ſhall inherit, becauſe the worthieſt of blood.</p>
               <p>If there be two Coparteners, or two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in Common of a Copyhold, and one dieth having iſſue, the iſſue ſhall inherit, and not the other by the ſurviverſhip; but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is of two joynt Tenants. Should I give way to my Penne, and write of this Theame till I wanted matter to write on, I ſhould make a large Volume in dilating this one point; therefore I will contract my ſelfe, intreating you to ſupply by your private co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, what I have either willingly or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittingly paſſed over in ſilence, onely take this caveat by the way.</p>
               <p>Though all qualities neceſſarily incident to eſtates at the Common Law, are likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to Copyhold eſtates; yet the Law is not ſo of collaterall qualities without ſpeciall Cuſtome;<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>22.</hi> a.</note> and therefore a Copyhold ſhall be no aſſets to the heire.</p>
               <p>A diſcent of a Copyhold, ſhall not toll an entry. A ſurrender made by Tenant in tayle (admit a Copyhold may be intayled) or by a Baron of a Copyhold, which he hath in right
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:61518:75"/> of his wife ſhall make no diſcontinuance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe are collaterall qualities, and not neceſſarily incident.</p>
               <p>Thus much of the ſeverall eſtates of Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds together with their ſeverall qualities incident to their ſeverall eſtates. I come now in the firſt place to examine how Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are to impleade, and be impleaded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LI.</head>
               <p>A Copyholder cannot in any Action re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or that ſavoureth of the realty, or hath a dependance upon the realty implead or be impleaded in any other Court, but in the Lords Court, for or concerning his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, but in actions that are meerely perſonall, he may ſue or be ſued at the Common Law.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder be ouſted of his Copyhold by a ſtranger, he cannot implead him by the Kings Writ, but by Plaint in the Lords Court, and ſhall make proteſtation to proſecute the ſute in the nature of an Aſſize of novell diſſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, of an Aſſize of <hi>Mort D'anceſtor</hi> of a <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medon</hi> in the Diſcender, Reverſer, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, or in the nature of any other Writ, as his cauſe ſhall require, and ſhall put in <hi>pleg. de proſequend.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:61518:76"/>
               <p>If a Copyholder be ouſted by the Lord he cannot maintaine an Aſſize at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, becauſe he wanteth as Franck-Tenant, but he may have an action of treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt him at the Common Law; for it is againſt reaſon, that the Lord ſhould be Judge where he himſelfe is a party.</p>
               <p>If in a plaint in the Lords Court touching the tytle of a Copyholder, the Lord giveth falſe judgement, he cannot maintaine a Writ of falſe judgement, for then he ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to a Francke-Tenant where he loſt none.</p>
               <p>No Copyholder of baſe Tenure in ancient Demeſne can maintaine a Writ of <hi>droit cloſe,</hi> or a Writ of <hi>Monſtravêrunt,</hi> but Tenants of Francke-tenure in ancient demeſne can.</p>
               <p>A Copyholder that may cut downe Timber trees by Cuſtome, by licence of the Lord, maketh a Leaſe for yeares, the Leſſee cutteth downe trees, the Copyholder ſhall not have a Writ of waſte, but ſhall ſue at the Lords Court to puniſh this waſte.</p>
               <p>If a <hi>feme</hi> Dowable, by Cuſtome of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold; by plaint in the Lords Court, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:61518:76"/> Dower and damages, no action of debt lieth at the Common Law for theſe da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, becauſe the action, though it be in it ſelfe perſonall, yet it dependeth upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitiy.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder maketh a Leaſe by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for Yeares, or by Deede with Licence, an action of debt lieth for the Rent, reſerved upon either Leaſe at the Common Law; but I much doubt whether he can avow for the Rent, either in the one or in the other, no more than <hi>Cestuy que uſe,</hi> before the Statute 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. could avow for the Rent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by him upon a Leaſe for yeares, and yet he could maintaine an action of debt for ſuch a Rent, becauſe an action of debt is grounded upon the contract.</p>
               <p>If a ſtranger cut downe trees growing in the Copyhold ground, an action of treſpaſſe lieth at the Common Law againſt him; ſo doth it againſt the Lord, where hee cutteth them downe, when by Cuſtome they belong to the Tenant, becauſe this is a meere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall action, and damages onely are to be recovered.</p>
               <p>And if a copyholder without Licence, maketh a Leaſe for one yeare, or with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence maketh a Leaſe for many yeares, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:61518:77"/> the Leſſee be ejected, he ſhall not ſue in the Lords Court by plaint, but ſhall have an ejection firme at the Common Law, becauſe hee hath not a Cuſtomary eſtate by Copy, but a warrantable eſtate by the rules of the Common Law. Thus much of the manner how Copyholders are to impleade, and be impleaded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LII.</head>
               <p>I Come now in the ſixt place, to ſhew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what Statutes Copyholders are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. Copyholders are comprehended under Statute, either by expreſſe limitation in preciſe words, or by a ſecret implication upon generall words: by expreſſe limitation in preciſe words;</p>
               <p>As by the Statute of the firſt of <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. it is expreſſely provided, that a Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der having Copyhold Land, to the yearely value of twenty ſixe ſhillings and ſixe pence; above all charges may be impanelled upon a Jury, as well as he that hath twenty ſhillings, <hi>per annum</hi> of Freehold-Land.</p>
               <p>So by the Statute of 1. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provided, that upon the diſſolution of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes, and Monaſteries, Copyholds ſhould
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:61518:77"/> continue as they did before the Statute, and ſhould fall into the Kings hands.</p>
               <p>So by the Statute of 2. <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly provided, that the intereſt of a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, ſhould be preſerved, notwithſtanding it be not found by Office, after the deceaſe of the Kings Tenant.</p>
               <p>So by the Statute of 1. <hi>Mar. cap.</hi> 12. it is expreſly provided, that if any Copyholder being Yeoman, Artificer, Husbandman, or Labourer; and being of the age of eighteene or more, under the age of ſixtie; not ſicke, impotent, lame, maymed, nor having any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſt or reaſonable cauſe of excuſe upon requeſt made by any man in authourity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to aide Juſtices in ſuppreſſing of rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous perſons, that then immediately he ſhall forfeit his Copyhold to the Lord, of whom it is held during the Copyholders naturall life.</p>
               <p>So by the Statute of 5. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 14. it is expreſly provided, that the forging of a Court Roll, to the intent to defraud a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, ſhall be as well puniſhable, as the forging any other Charter, Deede, or Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſealed, whereby to defeate a Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Freeholder.</p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:61518:78"/>
               <p>So by the Statute of 13. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 7. It is expreſly provided, that the Copyhold Land, as well as the Freehold Land of a Bankerupt, ſhall be ſold for the ſatisfying of the Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
               <p>So by the Statute of 14. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 6. It is expreſly provided, that if any of the Queenes ſubjects goeth beyond the Seaes without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, that then the Queene ſhall not onely take the ordinary profits of the fugitives Copyhold Land, as they ariſe, but ſhall let, ſet, and make Grants by Copy, and uſuall Wood-ſales, and other things, to all intents and purpoſes, as a Tenant pro terme <hi>durante vie,</hi> may doe.</p>
               <p>So by the Statute of the 35. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 2. It is expreſly provided, that if any perſon or perſons being convicted of recuſancie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire not home to their uſuall place of abode, not removing from thence above five miles diſtant, that then any perſon; or perſons thus offending, ſhall not onely forfeit their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Land to the Queene; but withall their Copyhold Land to the Lord, or Lords of whom it is holden.</p>
               <p>Thus have I ſhewed in briefe under what Statute Copyholders are comprehended by
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:61518:78"/> expreſſe limitation in preciſe words. Now I will ſhew you as briefely as I can, under what Statute they are comprehended by ſecret implication upon generall words.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LIII.</head>
               <p>SOme hold that all Statutes that ſpeake ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of Tenants, extend to Tenants by Copy: but it is much to be feared that wee ſhall wander from the Truth, if we give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to this conceit: for if wee peruſe the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, we ſhall meete with an infinite number of them, that ſpeak generally of Tenants, and yet touch not Tenants by Copy; wherefore not giving way to this opinion, as being er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious, I will ſet you downe an infallible rule, which will truely direct you in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the generall words in Statutes; and that is thus.</p>
               <p>When an Act in Parliament altereth the ſervice tenure intereſt of the Land,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 3. <hi>fo.</hi> 8.</note> or other thing in prejudice of the Lord, or of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Manor, or in prejudice of the Tenant, there the generall words of ſuch an Act in Parliament extend not to the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; but when an Act is generally made for the good of the Common-wealth, and no
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:61518:79"/> prejudice may accrue, by reaſon of the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of any intereſt, Service, Tenure or Cuſtome of the Manor there uſually Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds are within the generall purveiw of ſuch Acts.</p>
               <p>The Statute of <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. of intailes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth not to Copyholds, becauſe it would be prejudiciall to the Lord; for by this meanes the Tenure is altered: for the Donee intayle, without any ſpeciall reſervation ought to hold of the Doner by the ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that the Doner holdeth over; beſides the words of the Statute are, <hi>Quod voluntas Donator in charta Domini ſui manifesta expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa decetero obſervit,</hi> which proveth, that the intent of the Statute was, that no heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be intailed within this Statute, but ſuch an one as either was given, or at leaſt may be given by Charter, or Deede; but Copyholds are no ſuch hereditaments, and therefore not within the body of the Act; yet it is holden, that Cuſtome with the coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Statute will make an eſtate tayle.</p>
               <p>The Statute of <hi>W.</hi> 2. <hi>ca.</hi> 20. which giveth the Elegit, extendeth not to Copyhold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it would be prejudiciall to the Lord,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:61518:79"/> and a breach of the Cuſtome, that any ſtranger ſhould have intereſt in the Lands holden by Copy without the admittance, and ordinary allowance of the Lord.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 16. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it a forfeiture of Lands, Tenaments, and Hereditaments, to the purchaſor of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, Bulls, &amp;c. in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt the King, &amp;c. extendeth not to Copyhold, becauſe it would be prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to the Lord to have the King ſo farre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terereſſed in his Copyhold without his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>The Stature of 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 7. of Heretiques extends not to Copyholds; for though the Lord of a Manor is yearely to receive a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, in having the Lands after the yeare and the day forfeited unto him; yet becauſe the King is a ſharer in this for feiture; therefore Lands by Copy are not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under the generall words; beſides the Statute ſpeaketh of the Kings having <hi>annuum diem, &amp; vastum</hi> of theſe Lands forfeited for hereſie, as in Lands forfeited for felony; whereby it appeareth, that the meaning of the Statute is, that ſuch Lands onely ſhould be forfeited; in which the King by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:61518:80"/> courſe of the Law ſhould have <hi>An nuum diem &amp; vaſtum:</hi> if the Tenant of them had committed felony, but ſuch lands are not Lands by Copy; for if a Copyholder committeth felony, his Copyhold is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently forfeited to the Lord; therefore Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyholds are out of the generall purview of this Statute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LIV.</head>
               <p>THe Statute of 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 10. of Vſes, toucheth not Copyholds, becauſe the tranſmutation of poſſeſſion, by the ſole operation of the Statute without allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Lord, or the Agreement of the Tenant, would tend to the prejudice, both of the Lord, and of the Tenant, and the branch of the ſame Statute which ſpeaketh of Joyntures toucheth not Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, becauſe Dowers of Copyholds are warranted by ſpeciall Cuſtome onely, and not by the Common Law, or by the generall Cuſtome.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 31. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 32. by which joynt-Tenements and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in Common are compellable to make partition by a Writ <hi>de partitione faciend.</hi> As Coparteners at the Common Law, touch
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:61518:80"/> not Copyholds, becauſe this alteration of the Tenure without the Lords conſent may ſound to the prejudice of the Lord.</p>
               <p>The Statute of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 28. which confirmeth Leaſes for 21. yeares, or three Lives made by Tenants in tayle, or by the husband and wife, of the Lands of the wife, touch not Copyhold: for the Statute ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of Leaſes made by Deede onely; ſo that the intent of the Statute is to warrant the Leaſing of ſuch Lands only as are Grantable by Deede, but ſuch are not Copyhold-lands: for though they may by Licence of the Lord be demiſed by Indenture, yet in their owne name they are demiſeable onely by Copy; and therefore out of the generall purview of the Statute, for the ſame reaſon, the ſame Statute <hi>cap.</hi> 34. which giveth an entry to the Grantee, of a Reverſion, upon the breach of a Condition by the particular Tenant toucheth not Copyholds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LV.</head>
               <p>THe Stat. of 17. <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. which giveth the Wardſhips of Idiots Land unto the King, toucheth not the Idiots Copyhold; for thereby great prejudice would accrue to the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:61518:81"/>
               <p>But the Statute of <hi>Marton, cap.</hi> 1. which giveth damages to a <hi>feme,</hi> upon a Recovery in a Writ of Dower,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>30.</hi> b.</note> where the Baron dieth ſeiſed, extendeth to Copyhold.</p>
               <p>So that the Statute of <hi>Weſtm,</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3 and the three ſeverall branches of the ſame Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The one which giveth the <hi>Cui in vita,</hi> upon a diſcontinuance made by the Baron.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond which giveth the receit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>feme</hi> upon the Barons refuſall to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the wives title.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And the third, which giveth a <hi>quod ei deforceat</hi> to particular Tenants extends to Copyhold.</p>
               <p>So that the Statute of 31. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 13. of <hi>Monaſter.</hi> which provideth for the avoidance of doubling of eſtates,</p>
               <p>And the Statute 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. againſt Champertie, and buying of Litigious Titles, and <hi>chap.</hi> 28. which giveth an entry in Liew of a <hi>Cui in vita,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 26.</note> extendeth all to Copyholds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe Statutes are beneficiall to the Common-wealth, and not at all prejudiciall
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:61518:81"/> to the Lord in the alteration of Tenure eſtate Service, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So the Statute of 4. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. of Fines extendeth to Copyholds; for if a Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be diſſeiſed, and the Deſſeiſor levieth a Fine with proclamations, and five yeares paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without any claime made; this is a barre both to the Lord, and to the Copyholder.</p>
               <p>So if a Copyholder make a Feoffment in Fee, and the Feoffee levieth a Fine with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, and five yeares paſſe, the Lord is barred; but if a Copyholder levie a Fine, and five yeares paſſe, the Lord is not barred, for the Fine levied the Copyhold, having no Franck-Tenant, is utterly voide. And whereas it hath beene doubted, that this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute ſhould not extend to Copyhold; but the Lord ſhould hereby receive grand prejudice;<note place="margin">Co. <hi>9.</hi> fo. <hi>105.</hi> a.</note> for he ſhould not onely loſe the Fines, upon alienations or deſcents, and the benefit of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, but ſhould withall be in hazard to be barred of his Franck-tenant and inheritance.</p>
               <p>To that I anſwer, if the Lord receive any ſuch prejudice, it is through his owne default, for not making claime, for in regard of the privitie in eſtate, that is betweene him and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:61518:82"/> the Copyholder he may make claime, as well as the Copyholder himſelfe; <hi>Et vigilantibus non dormientibus jura ſubveniunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I ſhewed under what Statutes Copyholds are comprehended. I come now in the ſeventh place, to ſpeake of Fines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LVI.</head>
               <p>A Fine is a ſumme of money paide to the Lord of the Mannor for an Income into any Lands or Tenements. In ſome Manors Fines are certaine, in ſome incertaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fines of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyholds.</note>By ſpeciall Cuſtome Copyholders are to pay Fines upon Licences granted unto them to demiſe by Indenture, but by generall Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome they are to pay Fines onely upon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittances.</p>
               <p>If the Lord having a Copyhold by Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheate forfeiture, or other meanes, maketh a voluntary admittance, a Fine is due unto the Lord.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder ſurrendreth to the uſe of a ſtranger, and the Lord admitteth, a Fine is due to the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:61518:82"/>
               <p>So if a Copyhold deſcendeth, and the Lord admitteth the heire, where by the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Manor, the wife is to have Dower, and the husband is to be Tenant by the curteſie of a Copyhold, either of them ſhall be admitted, and ſhall pay a Fine to the Lord.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be granted <hi>du rante vie,</hi> and the Grantee dieth, living <hi>Ceſtuy que vie,</hi> and a ſtranger entreth as a generall occupant he ſhall be admitted, and ſhall pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>And ſo if a Copyhold be granted to one and his heires, <hi>durante vie;</hi> and the Grantee dieth, and his heire entereth as a ſpeciall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupant, where by the Cuſtome of the Manor, a Copyhold may be extended, upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the party ſhall be admitted, and ſhall pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>Where by the Cuſtome of the Manor, the Bailiffe of the Manor, is to have the Wardſhip of the Copyhold heire; being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the age of fourteene, ſuch a Guardian ſhall neither be admitted, nor pay a Fine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is but a partnor of the profits, and that not in his owne right, but in the right of him to whom he is Guardian.</p>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:61518:83"/>
               <p>If the Copyhold Lands of a Bankerupt be ſold according to the Statute of the 13. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 7. the Vendee ſhall be admitted and pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>If a Villaine purchaſeth a Copyhold, the Lord of the Villaine may enter and ſeize it, and the Lord of the Manor ſhall admit him and have a Fine.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be granted upon Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Condition be broken, and the Granter entreth, hee ſhall not be admitted, neither pay a Fine, becauſe upon the breach of the Condition, and the entry, he is to all intents, <hi>in Statu quo prius,</hi> as if no grant at all had beene made.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder in Fee ſurrendreth for life, reſerving the Reverſion, and the Leſſee for life dieth, the Copyholder ſhall not be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Reverſion, neither ſhall he pay a fine, becauſe the Reverſion was never out of him.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder be diſſeiſed, and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth upon the Deſſeiſor, or recovereth by plaint, in the nature of an Aſſize, he ſhall not be admitted, neither ſhall he pay a Fine, for he continueth ſtill Tenant by Copy, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:61518:83"/> the diſſeiſin, but where by a plaint a Copyhold is recovered upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruer of a new Tytle, where he that recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth was never admitted nor paid Fine; there upon his recovery, an admittance is requiſite, and a Fine is due: as if a Copyholder dieth ſeiſed, a ſtranger abateth, and the heire reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth by plaint in the nature of an Aſſize of <hi>Mort d'auncester</hi> upon this recovery hee ſhall be admitted and pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>If I take a wife, Copyhold in Fee, though by this inter-marriage, there accrueth a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent intereſt to me; yet becauſe I am ſeiſed, <hi>non jure proprio,</hi> but <hi>jure alieno,</hi> therefore I ſhall not be admitted, neither ſhall I pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>The ſame Law is,<note place="margin">Vid. Plowden com. <hi>4 18.</hi> b.</note> if ſhe be a Termor of a Copyhold; for though the terme by the inter-marriage be ſo veſted in me, that I may diſpoſe of it without controule; yet becauſe before diſpoſer I am poſſeſſed of it, but in the right of my wife; therefore I ſhall neither be admitted, nor pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>If a Copyhold be ſurrendred for life, the remainder to a ſtranger, though the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of Tenant for life be ſufficient to inveſt the eſtate in him in the Remainder, yet upon
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:61518:84"/> the death of Tenant for life, hee in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder ſhall be admitted and pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>So if a Copyhold be granted to three <hi>habend. ſucceſs. vie</hi> whereby Cuſtome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive is in force; if any one dieth, he that next ſucceedeth ſhall be admitted and pay a Fine.</p>
               <p>If two Coparteners, or Tenants in Common of a Copyhold be, and the one dieth, and the other hath all by diſcent, hee ſhall be admitted, and ſhall pay a Fine. But if two joynt-Tenants be of a Copyhold, one dieth, the other ſhall have all by the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivorſhip without admittance, or paying Fine, becauſe joynt-tenants to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, are ſeiſed <hi>per my, &amp; per tout.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If two ſeverall Copyholders joyne in a Grant of their Copyhold by one Copy; or if one Copyholder having ſeverall Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, granteth them by one Copy; yet the Grantee ſhall pay ſeverall Fines, for they ſhall inure as ſeverall Grants.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Co. <hi>4</hi> fo. <hi>27.</hi> b.</note>But if two joynt-Tenants, two Tenants in Common, or Tenant for life, and hee in the Remainder joyne in the Grant of a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, one Fine onely is due, and it ſhall inure,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:61518:84"/> as one Grant onely: ſo if a ſurrender be made, and after a common Recovery is had by plaint in the nature of a Writ of entry, in <hi>Le poſt,</hi> for the better aſſurance, one Fine onely ſhall be paid.</p>
               <p>And thus much of Fines. I come now in the next place to Forfeitures; wherein I will chiefely rely upon theſe foure points.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What Acts amount to a Forfeiture.</item>
                  <item>2. What perſons are able to forfeit.</item>
                  <item>3. What perſons are able to take benefit of a Forfeiture.</item>
                  <item>4. What Acts amount to a confirmation of an eſtate forfeit.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LVII.</head>
               <p>OF Acts which amount to Forfeiture, ſome are Forfeits, <hi>eo inſtante,,</hi> that they are committed: ſome are not Forfeits till preſentment. Offences which are apparant and notorious, by which the Lord by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preſumption, cannot chuſe but have notice are Forfeitures, <hi>eo inſtante,</hi> that they are committed, as if by ſpeciall Cuſtome, upon the diſcent of any Copyhold of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:61518:85"/> the heire is tyed upon three ſolemne Proclamations made at three ſeverall Courts, to come in and be admitted to his Copyhold, if he faileth to come; in this failer is a forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if a Copyholder be ſufficiently warned to appeare, and he faileth, this is a forfeiture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if he be hindred by ſickneſſe, or by over flowing of waters, or if he be much in debt, and feare to be arreſted, or if hee be a Bankerupt, and keepeth his houſe, then his default is no forfeiture.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder in the Court be called, and ſummoned to be ſworne of the homage, and refuſeth; this is a forfeiture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if a Copyholder be ſworne of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and then refuſeth to preſent the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles according to his Oath; this is a forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if a Copyholder will ſweare in Court, that he is none of the Lords Copyholder, this is a forfeiture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if a Copyholder in preſence of the Court ſpeaketh unreverent words of the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:61518:85"/> Lord, as that the Lord exacteth &amp; extorteth unreaſonable Fines, and undue-Services, this is fineable only, but no forfeiture; and if he ſaith in Court, that he will deviſe a meanes no longer to be the Lords Copyholder, this is neither cauſe of fine not forfeiture; for perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the meanes that hee intended was lawfull, <hi>viz.</hi> by paſſing away his Copyhold; <hi>Et ubi ſenſus verborum eſt multiplex, verba ſemper ſunt accipienda in meliori ſenſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Steward ſheweth a Court roll to a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyholder, to prove, that his Land is holden by Copy, and that the Copyholder ſaith he is a Freeholder, and ſheweth a Deed, pretending thereby to procure his Land to be Freehold, and teareth in peeces the Court-Roll, this is a forfeiture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if the Lord,<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>27.</hi> b.</note> upon the admittance of a Copyholder; the Fine, by the Cuſtome of the Manor being certaine, demandeth his Fine, and the Copyholder denieth to pay it upon demand, this is a forfeiture <hi>ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if a Copyholder will ſue a Replevin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, upon the Lords lawfull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe for his Rent or Services, this is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:61518:86"/>
               <p>But if the Copyholdder be in doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be due or not, and therefore intreateth the Lord, that the homage may inquire the truth, this is no forfeiture.</p>
               <p>If the Fine by the Cuſtome of the Manor, be incertaine, though a reaſonable Fine be aſſeſſed, yet becauſe no man can provide for an incertainty, the Copyholder is not bound to pay it preſently upon demand, but ſhall have convenient time to diſcharge it, if the Lord limit no certaine day for payment thereof, and if within convenient time it be not diſcharged, this is a forfeiture without preſentment.</p>
               <p>But if the Fine be unreaſonable, though it be never paid, it is no forfeiture, and it ſhall be determined by the opinion of the Juſtices before whom the matter dependeth, either upon a demurre, or in Evidence to the Jury, upon the confeſſion or proofe of the yearely value of the Land, whether the Fine be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable or not; for if the Lords might Aſſeſſe unreaſonable Fines at their pleaſures, then moſt eſtates by Copy, which are a great part of the Kingdome, and which have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued time out of minde, might now at the will of the Lords be defeated, and deſtroyed, which would be very inconvenient.</p>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:61518:86"/>
               <p>If the Lord demandeth his Rent, and the Copyholder denieth to pay it, this is a forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So if the Copyholder ſaith, that hee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth money to diſcharge the Rent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore intreateth the Lord to forbeare, untill he be better provided, unleſſe the Lord giveth his conſent; this non payment is a forfeiture, <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For a Copyholder knowing his day of payment is to provide againſt the day; but if the Lord commeth upon the Copyholders ground, and demandeth his Rent, and neither the Copyholder himſelfe, nor any other by his appointment, is there preſent to anſwer their demand, though this be a deniall in Law of the Rent, yet this is no forfeiture.</p>
               <p>But if the Lord continueth in making de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand upon the ground, and the Copyholder is ſtill abſent, this continuall deniall in Law, amounteth to a deniall in fact, and maketh the Copyholders eſtate ſubject to a forfeiture without preſentment.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder for life ſuffereth a Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very by plaint in the Lords Court, as Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold of the inheritance, this is a forfeiture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:61518:87"/>
               <p>But if he ſurrender in Fee, this is no forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe it did not paſſe by Livery.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder committeth waſte volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily or permiſſive, this is a forfeiture <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Voluntary, as if hee plucketh downe any ancient built houſe, or if he buildeth any new houſe, and then pulleth it downe againe; or if he ploweth medow, ſo that thereby the ground is made worſe; or loppeth the trees, or ſelleth the lopping; or if he cutteth downe any fruit-trees for fuell, having other wood ſufficient, this and the like voluntary waſte are forfeitures <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Permiſſive, as if he ſuffereth his houſe to decay, or fall to ground for want of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary reparations; or if hee ſuffereth his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes for want of mending his banckes to be ſurrounded, ſo that it becomes Ruſhy, or worth nothing; or his arrable ground, ſo to be ſurrounded, that it is become unprofitable. Theſe and the like permiſſive waſts are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures <hi>Ipſo facto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus much of Acts which are forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>eo instante,</hi> that they are committed. A word of thoſe Acts which are ſaid not forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures till preſentment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:61518:87"/>
               <head>SEC. LVIII.</head>
               <p>ANd ſuch are thoſe offences, which by common preſumption, the Lord cannot of himſelfe, have notice of without notice given, as if a Copyholder committeth felony or treaſon.</p>
               <p>So, if a Copyholder be Out-lawed, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, that the Lord may have the profits of his Copyhold Land, a preſentment is neceſſary.</p>
               <p>So, if a Copyholder goeth about in any other Court to intytle any other Lord unto his Copyhold, or if hee alieneth by Deede; theſe and the like ought to be preſented.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder maketh a bargaine and ſale of his Copyhold, and it is not in-rolled according to the Statute; this is no forfeiture; no more than a Feoffment without Livery, becauſe nothing paſſeth.</p>
               <p>So if a Copyholder maketh a Feoffment of all his Lands in Dale, and maketh Livery in his Charter Lands, no part of his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold-Land is thereby forfeited; but if Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be made in any part of the Copyhold
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:61518:88"/> Lands; all his Copyhold Lands are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder by Deede of bargaine and ſale inrolled according to the Statute, doth bargaine and ſell all his Lands in Dale, having both Copyhold and Freehold; his Copyhold is not thereby forfeited; for the Law will conſtrue this to extend to his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold onely, rather than by any over large conſtruction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make a forfeiture in this kinde.</p>
               <p>And if a Copyholder by Deed inrolled, bargaineth or ſelleth all his Copyhold Lands in Dale, or all his Lands in Dale gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, having no Freehold Lands, this is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture.</p>
               <p>Thus I have ſhewed you what Acts amount to a forfeiture. Now I will ſhew you what perſons are able to forfeit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LIX.</head>
               <p>A Man of <hi>non ſanae memoriae,</hi> an Idiot, or a Lunatique, though they be able to take a Copyhold, yet they are unable to forfeit a Copyhold, becauſe they want common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nay common ſenſe.</p>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:61518:88"/>
               <p>So an Infant that is under the age of foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene is unable to forfeit his Copyhold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wanteth diſcretion, and till then hee is to be in Ward to the next of his kindred, to whom th'inheritance cannot deſcend, or to the Lord, or the Bayliffe of the Manor, as the Cuſtome ſhall warrant.</p>
               <p>So a <hi>feme</hi> covert by any Act ſhe can doe of her ſelfe, cannot poſſibly forfeit her Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold, becauſe ſhe is not <hi>ſui juris ſed ſub po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate viri:</hi> but if ſhee doe any act which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth to a forfeiture by the conſent of her husband, this is in her a forfeiture.</p>
               <p>An Infant at the age of diſcretion may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit his Copyhold, not by offences which proceede from negligence or ignorance, but by ſuch as proceede from contempt.</p>
               <p>If an Infant come not in to be admitted, according to the Cuſtome at three ſolemne proclamations made at three ſeverall Courts; or if he will ſuffer his houſes to goe to ruine, or his ground to be ſurrounded; theſe Acts ſavouring of negligence onely are no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures.</p>
               <p>So if an Infant Copyholder ſueth a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevin againſt the Lord, upon a diſtreſſe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:61518:89"/> taken; or if hee alieneth by Deede, or the like; theſe Acts reliſhing of ignorance onely are no forfeitures.</p>
               <p>But if he denieth from time to time to pay the Lord the Rent, or committeth volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry waſte, notwithſtanding often warning gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him by the Lord; theſe Acts proceeding from malice and contempt are forfeitures; and ſo if he comitteth felony or treaſon.</p>
               <p>If a Guardian of a Copyholder commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth waſte, hee ſhall forfeit the Wardſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppe onely, not the inheritance of the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Cestuy que uſe,</hi> of a Copyhold commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth waſte, he ſhall not forfeit the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
               <p>If the husband committeth waſte in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold Lands, which he hath in the right of his wife;<note place="margin">Co. <hi>4.</hi> fo. <hi>27.</hi> a.</note> this is a forfeiture of the wives Copyhold.</p>
               <p>But if a ſtranger committeth waſte without the conſent of the husband, this is no forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture though the wife conſenteth.</p>
               <p>If a Diffeiſor of a Copyhold committeth waſte; this is no forfeiture.</p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:61518:89"/>
               <p>So, if a Copyhold be ſurrendred to the uſe of <hi>I. S.</hi> and before admittance, <hi>I. S.</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth waſte; this is no forfeiture, for by the ſame reaſon that hee cannot grant before ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance, hee cannot forfeit before admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>If two joynt Tenants be of a Copyhold, and one committeth waſte, he forfeiteth his part onely, for no man can forfeit more than he hath granted.</p>
               <p>And therefore if there be Tenant for life with a remainder over of a Copyhold, and the Copyholder for life purchaſeth the Manor, committeth waſte, or doth any Act, which amounteth to the extinguiſhment, or the forfeiture of a Copyhold, yet the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is not hereby touched.</p>
               <p>And ſo if a Copyholder be granted to three <hi>habend. ſucceſsivie,</hi> whereby the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Manor, this word <hi>Succeſsivie</hi> taketh place, the firſt Copyholder cannot prejudice the other two by any Act: he can doe no more, than if a Copyholder in Fee by Licence, maketh a Leaſe for yeares by Deed, or without Licence by Copy, and either of theſe Leſſees committeth waſte, the reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not hereby forfeited.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:61518:90"/>
               <p>If I have two ſeverall Copyholds, by two ſeverall Copies, and I commit waſte in one, this is a forfeiture of this one onely, and not of the other.</p>
               <p>And ſo if I grant theſe ſeverall Copyholds by one Copy, yet they continue ſeverall as they did before, and the forfeiture of the one is not the forfeiture of the other.</p>
               <p>The ſame Law is, if two ſeverall Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds Eſcheated to the Lord, and hee regran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them againe by one Copy.</p>
               <p>And thus have I ſhewed what perſons are able to forfeit. I will now in a word ſhew what perſons are able to take benefit of a forfeiture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LX.</head>
               <p>REgularly it is true, that none can take be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of a forfeiture; but he that is Lord of the Manor at the time of the forfeiture.</p>
               <p>And therefore if a Copyholder maketh a Feoffment, and then the Lord alieneth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Granter, nor the Grantee can take benefit of this forfeiture, for neither a right
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:61518:90"/> of entry, nor a right of action can ever be transferred from one to another. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if a Freeholder alieneth in Mortmaine, and then the Lord granteth away his Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory, neither the one nor the other can ever take benefit of this forfeiture.</p>
               <p>So if a Leſſee for life committeth waſte, and then the Leſſor granteth away the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, this waſte is made diſpuniſhable.</p>
               <p>But if Tenant for life be of a Manor, with remainder over in Fee to a ſtranger,</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder committeth waſte, and then Tenant for life of the Manor dieth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore entry; yet he in Remainder may enter, for he had an intereſt in the Manor at the time of the forfeiture committed, though hee could not enter, by reaſon of the State in Tenant for life, which being determined, his entry is now accrued unto him for the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture committed in the life of Tenant for life.</p>
               <p>And ſometimes, he that is neither Lord of the Manor, at the time of the forfeiture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, nor ever after ſhall take benefite of a forfeiture.</p>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:61518:91"/>
               <p>As if a Lord of a Manor granteth a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyhold in Fee, and then granteth the Franck-Tenement, or the inheritance of this Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold to a ſtranger; the Grantee, though no Lord of the Manor, nor able to keepe any Court,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 24.</note> ſhall take benefite of forfeitures made by the Copyholder, as if the Copyholder do make a Feoffment, Leaſe, waſte, deny the Rent, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus have I ſhewed what perſons are able to take benefit of a forfeiture. I will now in one word ſhew what Acts amount to a confirmation of an eſtate forfeited.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LXI.</head>
               <p>IF the Lord doth any thing whereby hee doth acknowledge him his Tenant after forfeiture; this acknowledgement amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to a Confirmation; as if he diſtreyneth upon the ground for Rent due after forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; or if he admitteth after the forfeiture, or the like: theſe are eſtoppells to the Lord, ſo that he can never enter, ſo the Lord have notice of ſuch forfeitures before any ſuch act, which may amount to a confirmation be done, yet ſome make this difference, that theſe forfeitures onely which deſtroy not the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:61518:91"/> Copyhold are onely conformable by ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent acknowledgement, and not thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures which tend to the deſtructions of a Copyhold, as if the Copyholder maketh a Feoffment; by this the Copyholder is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and therefore no ſubſequent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of the Lord will ever ſalve this ſore.</p>
               <p>And this ſhall ſuffice for forfeitures. I come now in the laſt place, to ſhew what Acts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to the extinguiſhment of a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
               <head>SEC. LXII.</head>
               <p>VVHereſoever a Copyhold is become not demiſable by Copy, either by the Act of the Lord, by the Act of the Law, or by the Act of the Copyholder himſelfe, it is extinguiſhed for ever.</p>
               <p>By the Act of the Lord, as if a Copyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Eſcheateth, and the Lord granteth away any eſtate by Deede, this is an extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> 4. <hi>fo.</hi> 31.</note> So if hee maketh a Feoffment upon Condition, and then entereth for breach of the Condition: yet the Copyhold is extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, becauſe once not demiſable.</p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:61518:92"/>
               <p>But if the Lord keepeth the Copyhold-Lands, for never ſo many yeares, or gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at will, this deſtroyes not the Copyhold, becauſe it continueth ever demiſable by Copy.</p>
               <p>By the Act of the Law, as if the Copyhold eſcheated be extended upon a Statute or Recognizance acknowledged by the Lord, or if the <hi>feme</hi> of the Lord hath this Land aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned unto her for her Dower, although theſe impediments be by the Act of the Law: yet becauſe they are lawfull, the Land can never after be granted by Copy.</p>
               <p>By the Act of the Copyholder himſelfe, as if he accepteth a Leaſe for yeares at the Common Law, either mediate or immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate from the Lord; of the Copyhold, this is an abſolute extinguiſhment.</p>
               <p>But if he accepteth a Leaſe for yeares of the Manor, the Copyholder by this hath not continuance, but this is no extinguiſhment, becauſe the Land continueth ſtill grantable by Copy.</p>
               <p>If a Copyholder with Licence make a Leaſe for yeares to a ſtranger; or without
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:61518:92"/> Licence, maketh a Leaſe for yeares to the Lord, the Copyhold is not hereby extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and yet it is not demiſable by Copy.</p>
               <p>So if a Copyholder intermarrieth with a <hi>feme Seignioreſſe;</hi> this is a ſuſpenſion onely of the Copyhold, no extinguiſhment.</p>
               <p>So if the interruption be <hi>torcious,</hi> as the Lord be diſſeiſed, and this diſſeiſor dieth ſeiſed, or if the Land be recovered by falſe verdict, or erronious judgement; and after the Land is recontinued, it is not extinguiſhed, but may be granted arere by Copy; for <hi>Non valet impedimentum quod de jure non ſortitur effectum, &amp; quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra legem fit pro infecto habetur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I conclude with Copyholders, wiſhing that theſe may ever be a perfect union betwixt them and their Lords, that they may have a feeling of each others wrongs and injuries; that their ſo little Common-wealth, having all his members knit together, in compleate order, may flouriſh to the end.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
